<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<blog>
  <title>Automating Disney</title>
  <subtitle>Setting up a pipedream.com workflow</subtitle>
  <published_at>2021-04-29 22:05:43 -0400</published_at>
  <body># The Problem

My family had the dream of going to Disney for my sister in law birthday in April and after coordinating the house, plane tickets, multiple families, and tickets we had a problem.  The park tickets were not purchased at the exact same moment and some of the family was not able to [reserve their park](https://disneyworld.disney.go.com/experience-updates/park-reservations/)! How could we fix this so the family can go to the park together? 

## The Calendar
![Silvrback blog image ](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a94b16cf-40e1-4a93-b4f2-7248726e3d00/calendar.png)
We could do the following...

- Manually Click Dates
- Check Available Parks
- Repeat above…forever…hoping to get lucky

This clearly is not something we can do...there must be a way to dig deeper and automate the checking.

## Finding The Data
![Silvrback blog image ](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a94b16cf-40e1-4a93-b4f2-7248726e3d00/preview.png)

Lets look to see how the calendar actually works.

- Inspect page load via developer tools
- Check XHR to see if there are any api requests....
- Looking through the requests we see `calendar`

## The API

If you view the request in a new window we get some nicely formatted `json` and the url is human readable.

&gt;https://disneyworld.disney.go.com/availability-calendar/api/calendar?segment=tickets&amp;startDate=2021-04-05&amp;endDate=2021-04-30

Thankful we see that the query string has a lot of helpful parameters

- `startDate`
- `endDate`
- `segment`

## Decoding Response

Now that we discovered the format of the request next we need to understand the response.

```json
[
  {
    "date": "2021-04-17",
    "availability": "none",
    "parks": []
  },
  {
    "date": "2021-04-18",
    "availability": "partial",
    "parks": [
      "80007838"
    ]
  },
  {
    "date": "2021-04-19",
    "availability": "partial",
    "parks": [
      "80007838"
    ]
  },
  {
    "date": "2021-04-20",
    "availability": "partial",
    "parks": [
      "80007823",
      "80007838"
    ]
  }
]
```
The good news the json response is fairly straight forward except for some magic numbers.

- `date`
- `availability` 
- `parks` list of parks that are available
  - `Epcot 80007838`
   - `Animal Kingdom 80007823`
   - `Magic Kingdom 80007944`
   - `Hollywood Studios  80007998`

_We were able to reverse engineer the above magic numbers by clicking around the calendar and recording which numbers showed up compared to what was displayed on the screen._

## NodeJs

Now that we had an api, understood the request and response lets use turn this into a small program using NodeJs and [`🔗axios`](https://github.com/axios/axios).  Our program will need to do the following.

- Request Data from the API
- Parse the response
- If availability do…….something.

Once we put this all together we ended up with the following.

```javascript
const axios = require("axios");

let url =
    "https://disneyworld.disney.go.com/availability-calendar/api/calendar?segment=tickets&amp;startDate=2021-04-17&amp;endDate=2021-04-17";

(async () =&gt; {
    try {
        const response = await axios.get(url);

        var epcot = "80007838";
        var animalKingdom = "80007823";
        var magicKingdom = "80007944";
        var hollywood = "80007998";

        var message = "";
        var alert = false;

        response.data.forEach((date) =&gt; {
            message += `Date: ${date.date} | Parks:`;
            var parkNames = [];
            date.parks.forEach((park) =&gt; {
                if (park === epcot) {
                    parkNames.push("Epcot");
                }
                if (park === animalKingdom) {
                    parkNames.push("Animal Kingdom");
                }
                if (park === magicKingdom) {
                    alert = true;
                    parkNames.push("Magic Kingdom");
                }
                if (park === hollywood) {
                    parkNames.push("Hollywood");
                }
            });
            message += `${parkNames.join()} \n`;
        });
        if (alert) {
            //send alert
        }
    } catch (error) {
        console.log(error.response.body);
    }
})();
```

As you can see from the above we parsed the response and then captured the parks that are available and only trigger an alert for `Magic Kingdom` as that was the park the family wanted to go to on the day `2021-04-17`


## Automation
Now that we had a node program we needed to run this on a schedule to automagically check ever so often to see if any new parks open up. We could run via cron or similar scheduling tools, manually run it, or a server-less approach.

![Silvrback blog image ](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a94b16cf-40e1-4a93-b4f2-7248726e3d00/pipedream.png)

I decided to go with [pipedream](https://pipedream.com) as it ticked all the boxes.

&gt;Stop writing boilerplate code, struggling with authentication and managing infrastructure. Start connecting APIs with code-level control when you need it — and no code when you don't.

### Convert to Workflow

It was fairly straightforward to convert the NodeJs program to a pipe dream workflow as it had node support at its core which made the migration easy.

### Steps

The first thing we needed to do is define a few steps to help flow together what has to happen at each execution along the way.

#### Dates

We had a step for date that just returns the date we want to check for the calendar checking step.

```javascript
async (event, steps) =&gt; {
    return {
        date: "2021-04-17"
    }
}
```

#### Check API

As you can see this is a fairly easy migration but a few changes happened to make it work in pipedream

- pass in the `date` via the `steps` object `steps.date_to_check.$return_value.date;`
- return an object so it can be used in future steps

```javascript
        return {
            alert: alert,
            message: message
        };
```

```javascript
async (event, steps) =&gt; {
    const axios = require("axios");

    let date = steps.date_to_check.$return_value.date;
    let url =
        `https://disneyworld.disney.go.com/availability-calendar/api/calendar?segment=tickets&amp;startDate=${date}&amp;endDate=${date}`;

    try {
        const response = await axios.get(url);

        var epcot = "80007838";
        var animalKingdom = "80007823";
        var magicKingdom = "80007944";
        var hollywood = "80007998";

        var message = "";
        var alert = false;

        response.data.forEach((date) =&gt; {
            message += `Date: ${date.date} | Parks:`;
            var parkNames = [];
            date.parks.forEach((park) =&gt; {
                if (park === epcot) {
                    parkNames.push("Epcot");
                }
                if (park === animalKingdom) {
                    parkNames.push("Animal Kingdom");
                }
                if (park === magicKingdom) {
                    alert = true;
                    parkNames.push("Magic Kingdom");
                }
                if (park === hollywood) {
                    parkNames.push("Hollywood");
                }
            });
            message += `${parkNames.join()} \n`;
        });
        return {
            alert: alert,
            message: message
        };
    } catch (error) {
        console.log(error.response.body);
    }
}
```

#### Email

As we said above we want to do something this if the alert is triggered which in this workflow happens to be an email.  My favorite zero friction email service happens to be [sendgrid](https://sendgrid.com)  and good news is [pipedream has a built in connector to send grid](https://pipedream.com/apps/sendgrid).

```javascript
async (event, steps, params, auths) =&gt; {
    const axios = require('axios')
    if (steps.check_disney_calendar.$return_value.alert) {
        return await require("@pipedreamhq/platform").axios(this, {
            url: `https://api.sendgrid.com/v3/mail/send`,
            headers: {
                Authorization: `Bearer ${auths.sendgrid.api_key}`,
            },
            method: 'POST',
            data: {
                "personalizations": [{
                    "to": [{
                        "email": params.to_email,
                        "name": params.to_name
                    }],
                    "subject": params.subject
                }],
                "from": {
                    "email": params.from_email,
                    "name": params.from_name
                },
                "reply_to": {
                    "email": params.reply_to_email,
                    "name": params.reply_to_name
                },
                "content": [{
                    "type": params.type,
                    "value": params.value
                }]
            }
        })
    }
}
```
_we modified the built in template slightly to only send the email if `steps.check_disney_calendar.$return_value.alert` is actually true_

Now that we have all of these in place it is time to try it out by finding a date that has availability and use that in the `date` step.

### Testing It Out
![Silvrback blog image ](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a94b16cf-40e1-4a93-b4f2-7248726e3d00/email.png)

We set the workflow to trigger every 10 minutes and as soon as we hit the right condition we got the above email.

## Time To Wait...Did it work?

### Yes

It actually did work we triggered the check every 10 minutes and as soon as I got the email I resorted to the manual flow of contacting every family member.  I could have easily used twilio to make a phone call, maybe that will be in the next iteration.


</body>
  <title>Push Container to Registry in GitLab</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <published_at>2019-07-28 11:58:46 -0400</published_at>
  <body>## Generate Personal Access Token for Docker Login

Navigate over to the [access token](https://gitlab.com/profile/personal_access_tokens) section in your profile.

Scope to `api` and set your expiration date.

_store this key in your favorite password vault as it is not accessible after the generation process_

## docker login

```bash
docker login registry.gitlab.com

username: {your username for gitlab}
password: {the access toke you just crated}
```

## build and push your image

```bash
cd site &amp;&amp; bundle exec jekyll build
cd ..
docker build . -t registry.gitlab.com/markcoleman/vikingmill:1.0 -t registry.gitlab.com/markcoleman/vikingmill:latest
docker push registry.gitlab.com/markcoleman/vikingmill
```

_tagged via a version and also latest_

## Container Registry

![Silvrback blog image ](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/959007ea-aae0-4788-9dc3-463e7d4c8fe7/Screen%20Shot%202019-07-28%20at%2011.55.18%20AM.png)





</body>
  <title>Setting Up a GitLab Pipeline</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <published_at>2019-07-27 11:38:19 -0400</published_at>
  <body>I have been slowly exploring the free tier of [gitlab](https://www.gitlab.com) and today wanted to setup a build in the `CI` job.  The following steps are taken to create a build of a static site via jekyll. 

## Create `.gitlab-ci.yml `

```bash
touch .gitlab-ci.yml 
```

### Edit the file

As with any build script I simply put the steps I ran locally and placed them into the `yml` file.

```yaml
image: "ruby:2.5"
build:
  script:
    - cd ./site/ &amp;&amp; bundle install
    - bundle exec jekyll build
    - zip -r site-build.zip ./_site
```

_note, unlike circleci each script execution will persist directory structure, e.g. `cd site` now puts you in the `site` folder for any  proceeding script items._

### The first Error

```bash
$ zip -r site-build.zip ./_site
/bin/bash: line 90: zip: command not found
```

It appears our image does not contain, `zip` so we will need to install it via a `before_script` block.

```yaml
image: "ruby:2.5"
before_script:
  - apt-get install -y p7zip
build:
  script:
    - cd ./site/ &amp;&amp; bundle install
    - ls
    - bundle exec jekyll build
    - zip -r site-build.zip ./_site
```
### Another Error

```bash
root@item:/# apt-get install p7zip
Reading package lists... Done
Building dependency tree       
Reading state information... Done
E: Unable to locate package p7zip
```

I learned that since this is a fresh image you also need to run the `update` command first.

```bash
image: "ruby:2.5"
before_script:
  - apt-get update -qy
  - apt-get -y install zip unzip
```

_Don't forget to add in `-y` to auto answer the prompt._

### The final build `yml` file

```yaml
image: "ruby:2.5"
before_script:
  - apt-get update -qy
  - apt-get -y install zip unzip
build:
  script:
    - cd ./site/ &amp;&amp; bundle install
    - bundle exec jekyll build
    - zip -r site-build.zip ./_site
```

## Artifacts

Now we have all of your pieces in order and our build is successful next up getting an [artifact](https://docs.gitlab.com/ee/user/project/pipelines/job_artifacts.html) of the build which happens to be the rendered site from `jekyll`.

### Storing the contents of the zip as an artifact

```bash
  artifacts:
    name: "viking-mill"
    paths:
      - ./site/site-build.zip
    expire_in: 30 days
```

_note, this new block will reset to the root working folder so you need to specify the full path from the root_

## The Final `.gitlab-ci.yml`

```yaml
image: "ruby:2.5"
before_script:
  - apt-get update -qy
  - apt-get -y install zip unzip
build:
  script:
    - cd ./site/ &amp;&amp; bundle install
    - bundle exec jekyll build
    - zip -r site-build.zip ./_site
  artifacts:
    name: "viking-mill"
    paths:
      - ./site/site-build.zip
    expire_in: 30 days
```

## Finish

Now we have a build setup inside of gitlab for the static jekyll site</body>
  <title>My First Dockerfile</title>
  <subtitle>Doing something with docker</subtitle>
  <published_at>2019-07-21 20:15:01 -0400</published_at>
  <body>I have been experimenting with docker over the years off and on but never took the time to apply it to a real project.  Today that was going to change with a quick experiment building up a an `nginx` image and apply the output of a Jekyll site.  

### `Dockerfile`

A `Dockerfile` is a document that specifies a source image and commands you wish to apply to that image where each command is a delta from the previous action.  This allows you to have a repeatable process of getting your image created.  

```
FROM nginx:1.17.1
COPY site/_site /usr/share/nginx/html
```

This a rather trivial example but takes a [`tag`](https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/commandline/tag/) of [`nginix`](https://hub.docker.com/_/nginx) version `1.17.1`.  I wanted to be sure to specify a known version as using `latest` while helpful could result in an image that no longer works as you have not control over what `latest` actually is when building.  The `COPY` command simply copies files from a source location to a destination location inside of the image.

### `build-container.sh`

Since the Dockerfile can only execute commands inside of the image I was unsure how to get the `Jekyll` site built from the start.  After a bit of searching it was recommended to create a simple `sh` script that executes the commands and then the corresponding `docker build .` command at the end. 

```
cd site &amp;&amp; bundle exec jekyll build
cd ..
docker build . -t markcoleman/viking-mill:latest
```

### `run-site.sh`

Now that we have the image built and tagged lets run it like any other image we have pulled and map a port of exposed port `8080` to container port `80` which is exposed by `nginix`.

```
docker run -d -p 8080:80 -i -t markcoleman/viking-mill:latest
```

_Site running in an ngnix container_
![Viking Mill ](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/bc9e7404-7b27-425e-8e33-74204dbda284/Screen%20Shot%202019-07-21%20at%2012.44.57%20PM.png)

Simple but yet very effective and allowed me to learn a bit more, next up how to automate this using gitlab.</body>
  <title>Find Your Turning Point(s)</title>
  <subtitle>Reflections on a career and paths traveled</subtitle>
  <published_at>2019-01-28 21:34:49 -0500</published_at>
  <body>I typically write about my various interactions around technology in an effort to learn while forcing myself to share knowledge to other readers.  I personally find this approach the best way for me to learn since to share you must be confident on the topic at hand.  This post however is a mini self reflection of two turning points in my career and I challenge you to self reflect on your career to locate the turning points you might have in your career.  If you can not find one you need to take this as an opportunity to find your own turning point as it forces you to become better and transform to be a better version of yourself.

## Thinking I Knew It All

After college I got my first job as a developer at a small company building financial software for credit unions.  I was working there for a couple years increasing my skills from VB6, VB.NET, and eventually C#.  Life was grand I was in a small ecosystem with a limited presence with the online development community (it was 2003-2008 after all).  We still received binders of MSDN discs and assumed we knew it all.  The team was thriving and we were slinging code with visions of big home grown systems that solves numerous needs for our credit union clients.  This all came crashing down when this company was sold off to a competing company and I was forced to new experiences. 

## Being Humbled and Not Knowing Anything - Turning Point 1

At this new company I was around familiar faces, but integrated into the new company. A contractor was brought into the shop to assist in building core components of a high profile project.  His name was [Khalid Abuhakmeh](https://www.khalidabuhakmeh.com/) and reflecting back this was the first turning point my my career that shot me down a different path.  He is one of the most passionate developers I had the opportunity to work with professionally and asked many questions of `"Why"`

- Why is this system built this way?  
- Why is there no unit testing (could you even test this!?!)
- Why did you roll your own `X`? (where X is data access, logging, security, etc)
- Did you ever hear of using `Y`?

Having someone around you that is passionate about development, encourages learning through pair programming, and reinforces all the ideals of development was something that helped shape me today.  These questions and openness to teach introduced me to a concept I was not familiar with in my traditional development mind.  This directed me down the path learning, reading, teaching, and complete self improvement as I wanted to answer all his questions and improve the code base.  What we did prior was by not any means bad, but we can strive to be better. Flash forward a months of questioning and improving on came the transition to a new opportunity at [Members 1st FCU](https://www.members1st.org)

## Growing and Learning

A few former coworkers were already at Members 1st and dreams of software development danced in their heads of what could be based on what we have done in the past (and doing it _"right"_ this time around).  My former supervisor was already working there and when the call was made three of us came roaring over to do what we do best, build credit union software.  We did indeed build software, we built core components to interact with the data processing system, integration points, web services, and eventually a Bill Payer system.  Development life was good again, we were building software, sharing new found inspiration pushing forward always striving for that ideal.

## Progressing Forward - Turning Point 2

After living in this comfortable space for a coupe more years my partner in crime working at Members 1st FCU left for a new opportunity. This left a void (turning point 2) that needed filled to continue to move forward in our goals of building the best credit union software possible.  Through a series of events and support from my supervisor and team I was able to rise above this deficient and take  learning, leading, and empowering to the next level trying my hardest to build up the team.  If you are faced with a difficult situation that makes you feel uncomfortable seize that opportunity and do what it takes to rise above it.  As scary as it was this allowed me to mature to the next level in my career.

## Repeat

To improve you need to be humbled and seize opportunities when they present them to yourself.  I personally feel you need to repeat this process continually throughout your career. </body>
  <title>Azure ❤️ Terraform</title>
  <subtitle>Getting started with terraform with the azure provider</subtitle>
  <published_at>2019-01-22 21:07:10 -0500</published_at>
  <body>I recently have been exploring the concept of infrastructure as code and how all the core concepts we use day in day out in our software development life cycle could apply to infrastructure resources.  This idea eventually brought me to [terraform](https://www.terraform.io) and how it can be applied to azure resources.  I started following along with the [Getting started guide for azure](https://www.terraform.io/docs/providers/azurerm/index.html) and pieced together a couple steps to follow to get a new user to terraform up and running relatively quickly.

## Setting Up Your Workstation

Terraform authenticates to azure resources by leveraging the azure command line interface and the azure APIs and needs to be installed if you do not have it already.

Azure cli

```
brew install azure-cli
```

Install terraform

```
 brew install terraform
```

_Optional Visual Studio Code Extension_ - This is an optional step, however the extension does increase productivity in VSCode for resource navigation and a module view.

```
code --install-extension ms-azuretools.vscode-azureterraform
```

## Setting Your Azure Subscription

If you happen to have multiple azure subscriptions it is *important* you set the subscription id correctly otherwise you will be terraforming a subscription you probably did not plan on terraforming.

Login via the Azure cli

```
az login
```

List all of your Accounts and capture the `"id"` of the account you wish to terraform

```
❯ az account list
```
```
[
  {
    "cloudName": "AzureCloud",
    "id": "10000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000",
    "isDefault": false,
    "name": "Subscription Name",
    "state": "Enabled",
    "tenantId": "00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000",
    "user": {
      "name": "email@user.name",
      "type": "user"
    }
  }
]
```

Set the subscription via the `"id"` you recored above.

```
az account set --subscription="10000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000"
```


## Setting Up Your Sample Project

Terraform works via `tf` configuration files that define your infrastructure resources.

```
touch core.tf
```

### Define the Provider

The first entry in your `tf` should be the provider you wish to target, in this case it is the azure resource manager.

```
provider "azurerm" {
}
```

Once that is defined and saved we will need to run the initialize command to pull down the azure provider plugin.

```
terraform init
Initializing provider plugins...
- Checking for available provider plugins on https://releases.hashicorp.com...
- Downloading plugin for provider "azurerm" (1.21.0)...
```

### Our First Resource

Now that we have a provider defined it is time to create our first resource.  The simplest resource to create is of course a resource group.

```
resource "azurerm_resource_group" "azurerm_resource_group" {
  name     = "azure-loves-terraform"
  location = "eastus"
}
```

Our resource is looking quite nice, but as any code it sure would be helpful to define a variable just in case we wish to switch the location around at will.  This can be accomplished with variables.

Create `variables.tf`

```
variable "region" {
  default = "eastus"
}
```

Now with the variables file created we can alter our resource to reference that variable throughout our resource definition.

```
provider "azurerm" {}

resource "azurerm_resource_group" "azurerm_resource_group" {
  name     = "azure-loves-terraform"
  location = "${var.region}"
}
```


## Trying It Out

To publish any of our changes to our subscription we will need to execute a plan which refreshes the state from the defined terraform configuration and how it relates to the actual resources in our subscription.  This will show the diff needed via creations, updates, or deletions of resources based upon what terraform calculates.  We specify the `-out` flag so we can apply the change later. _This step does not actually push any changes_

```
terraform plan -out build-core
Refreshing Terraform state in-memory prior to plan...
The refreshed state will be used to calculate this plan, but will not be
persisted to local or remote state storage.


------------------------------------------------------------------------

An execution plan has been generated and is shown below.
Resource actions are indicated with the following symbols:
  + create

Terraform will perform the following actions:

  + azurerm_resource_group.azurerm_resource_group
      id:       &lt;computed&gt;
      location: "eastus"
      name:     "azure-loves-terraform"
      tags.%:   &lt;computed&gt;


Plan: 1 to add, 0 to change, 0 to destroy.

------------------------------------------------------------------------

This plan was saved to: build-core

To perform exactly these actions, run the following command to apply:
    terraform apply "build-core"
```

If you examine the output you can see the plan will create one new resource in our subscription with 0 changes and 0 deletions.

To apply the changes and deploy to your subscription from the plan we can run the apply command with saved plan state.

```
terraform apply "build-core"  
azurerm_resource_group.azurerm_resource_group: Creating...
  location: "" =&gt; "eastus"
  name:     "" =&gt; "azure-loves-terraform"
  tags.%:   "" =&gt; "&lt;computed&gt;"
azurerm_resource_group.azurerm_resource_group: Creation complete after 1s (ID: /subscriptions/10000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000/resourceGroups/azure-loves-terraform)

Apply complete! Resources: 1 added, 0 changed, 0 destroyed.
```

## Welcome Infrastructure as Code

I am looking forward to more time exploring terraform and how it can assist in infrastructure drift, peer review, and the concept of continual delivery of infrastructure.
</body>
  <title>CPOSC 2018</title>
  <subtitle>Random notes while attending the Central Pennsylvania Open Source Conference on December 1, 2018</subtitle>
  <published_at>2019-01-19 09:18:56 -0500</published_at>
  <body>The end of last year I attended the first half of the Central Pennsylvania Open Source conference in Lancaster for the first time.  I enjoy attending local conferences and I will be sure to attend this in the future as it was filled with interesting topics presented by a group of passionate presenters.  I was quite impressed by the student showcase building robots, learning about linux laptops, and software defined radio. Below are some random notes and links during the my attendance. 

---

# Radio, Robots, and Real-time video: A showcase of student technology projects

- [Blender](https://www.blender.org)
- [OBS](https://obsproject.com)
- [Turtle Bot](https://www.turtlebot.com)
- [ROS](http://www.ros.org)
- [RViz](http://wiki.ros.org/rviz)
- [SDR (Software Defined Radio)](https://www.sdr-radio.com)

---

# GraphQL for the REST of Us: Adding a GraphQL API to a Rails App

- [GraphQL via wiki](https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/GraphQL)
- [GraphQL](https://graphql.org)

&gt;Express your api as in your business domain

- [GraphQL in `ruby`](http://graphql-ruby.org)
- [Interactive GraphQL](https://github.com/graphql/graphiql)

&gt;Everything in graphql has to return something, mutation can be used for creation.

&gt;[Ensure you do not get yourself in a spot for the N+1 query issue...](
https://medium.com/slite/avoiding-n-1-requests-in-graphql-including-within-subscriptions-f9d7867a257d)

---

# Open Source Satellite Development

- [Beyond Earth](https://www.beyond-earth.com)
- [Mini Cubes](https://mini-cubes.com)
- [Pocket Cube](https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/PocketQube)
- [Radio Bro](https://www.radiobro.com/minisatcom-uhf-product-family/)
- [Solar Cells](http://www.trisolx.com/solar-cells/)

&gt;Lasts 4-5 Years life span

## Power
- CPU - 10 Watts
- Radio - 1 Watt
- Sensor - 2 Watts
- Battery recharge - 2 Watts
- Total Power - 15 Watts

## Software

- Ubuntu
- Lamp
- Python for GPIO
- Python for PHP Bridge

## Get data back

- Uses TCP/IP system
- Slow 9600 bps to 38kbps (on a good day)
- Mostly sensor data
- Occasional image (could take 4 days to retrieve an image)

## The Demo Unit

Built a Pocket Quebec based web server

`discovery.simple-url.com:8080`

## Going to Space

- Launching Q2 - Q4 2019
- Currently scheduled on Alba Orbital Cluster 2
- Flying on a RocketLabs Electron from New Zealand

## What Can Go Wrong

- Failure to reach orbit (XKCD Up Goer Five)
- Power Failure
- Communication errors

## Paying For It All

- Expected to build with 50k budget
- Actual costs close to 100k 
- Launching a Kickstarter to raise remaining funds
- Launch cost is 30k (most expensive portion of the budget) hopeful the launch will go down to 10-15k (the problem is the paperwork and integration to know what it is and what it is going to do)

&gt; For around 8k you can create an antenna and join a collection that receives data.
https://satnogs.org

</body>
  <title>BarCamp 2017</title>
  <subtitle>the unconference in Harrisburg, PA</subtitle>
  <published_at>2017-10-14 11:49:38 -0400</published_at>
  <body>This is random notes gathered while attending the Harrisburg BarCamp 2017.


#Small Data, Big Results
http://noboundsdigital.com

Problems with big data, example of being marketed to a product/service even when the data is incorrect. (new baby marketing when family lost the child)

Big Data is often dumb data, do you have talent inhouse to crunch all this data.

Small Data can be actionable and easier to understand and handle it effectively. 

Trim down the many data points and focus on the easy parts that actually is helpful (web analytics), this helps you build out digital KPI that is actually useful.

https://www.martinlindstrom.com/small-data/

**Buyer Journey**
 - Awareness 
 - Consideration
 - Decision

**How to get better results**
 - Intentionally observe
 - Brainstorm ideas, how to make things simple for the user
 - implement, try to keep the changes small
re-evaulate

How users interact with your website
https://www.hotjar.com

This will show you where people are clicking or not clicking in your site.

Realtime interaction points for a site to offer assitance can help users that are struggling at that point in time.

Small Data is collected for a short period of time and than thrown away. (or end results could just be kept but not the data itself)

**Text Mining**
https://rapidminer.com

Focus on one persons problems of how they start and fail doing an action.

Unmonitored "chat" might be ok as it is better to get the question then no question at all. (this can be done if you set expectations to the end user)

**Chat Service**
https://www.intercom.com/live-chat

#Cloud Based Programming
Open discussion on how to leverage the cloud.

**Random Topics and Links**
 - [Go](https://golang.org)
 - [AWS](https://aws.amazon.com)
 - [Azure](https://azure.microsoft.com)
 - [Google Compute](https://cloud.google.com/compute/)
 - [Docker](https://www.docker.com)
 - [Container Orchestration](https://www.linux.com/news/8-open-source-CONTAINER-ORCHESTRATION-TOOLS-KNOW)
 - [PostgreSql Json](https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.6/static/datatype-json.html)
</body>
  <title>Using Jekyll: Step 0</title>
  <subtitle>The very start of learning Jekyll along with a few struggles.</subtitle>
  <published_at>2016-03-27 16:33:10 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Over the past year I have been hearing about [Jekyll](https://jekyllrb.com) as a simple solution for creating static content for a websites/blogs without having to worry about a database.  I think today is the day I actually do something about this and get something up and running.  

##Step -1

As I do with most things I dive right in (sometimes reading docs first) and issuesd the command ``gem install jekyll``. Unfortunately this did not work as intended and I was presented with this error message.

&gt; ...You don't have write permissions for the /Library/Ruby/Gems/2.0.0 directory. ...

This error sent me down the path of RVM (ruby version manager) in an attempt to get ruby installed without having to resort to ``sudo`` everything (bad news bears).  After learning this was the system installation of ruby (and shouldn't be touched unless you know what you are doing and I don't...yet...) I then went down the path of rbenv which allowed you to handle various ruby installations which seemed to work however anytime I ran ``ruby -v`` it would continue to use the system ruby install.  I was about to give up and use ``sudo`` but then remembered about [homebrew](http://brew.sh).  I ran the command``brew install ruby`` and it did its magic.  Now when I run ``ruby -v`` it reported version 2.3.0 which was just installed by brew.  Yes! We are not using the system version of ruby anymore and we should be able to install gems without resorting to ``sudo``

##Step 0

Ok back to the steps from the Jekyll website.

- ``gem install jekyll`` _intall the gem_
- ``jekyll m1bytes`` _creates the base strucutre_
- ``cd m1bytes`` _navigate to the new directory_
- ``jekyll serve`` _serves the app on port 4000_

![jekyll](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/f793ab6a-32d9-4432-9a86-1a94f5c7ae1f/image_large.png)

We have Jekyll installed, created a simple site, and have it serving successfully.  This was a simple process however my struggle was not with Jekyll itself but with my environment.  Next up I need to learn how to apply a template.</body>
  <title>Hello AngularJs 2</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_32</subtitle>
  <published_at>2016-01-03 20:15:29 -0500</published_at>
  <body>I have been doing angular development for almost two years now building/maintaining an [online banking application](https://myonline.members1st.org).  We first started off with version 1 of [angularjs](http://www.angularjs.org) and slowly upgraded to 1.2.8 which currently is considered legacy 🤕.  We need to make the movement to push forward now that we "officially" dropped support of IE8 (people ask why so long, but a large vocal percentage was using IE8 at the start of the year and we didn't want to intentionally break anything). 

Through a series of events we actually built our system with typescript which turned out to be a stroke of good luck since angular2 is officially using typescript.  Today is the day I actually build something with AngularJs and the best way to do that is to use the [quick start](https://angular.io/docs/ts/latest/quickstart.html)

**Files Created**

**app.component.ts**

```
import {Component} from 'angular2/core';

@Component({
    selector: 'my-app',
    template: '&lt;h1&gt;Hello Angular Js 2&lt;/h1&gt;'
})
export class AppComponent { }
```

**boot.ts**

```
import {bootstrap}    from 'angular2/platform/browser'
import {AppComponent} from './app.component'

bootstrap(AppComponent);
```

**index.html**

```
&lt;html&gt;

&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Angular 2 QuickStart&lt;/title&gt;

    &lt;!-- 1. Load libraries --&gt;
    &lt;script src="node_modules/angular2/bundles/angular2-polyfills.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="node_modules/systemjs/dist/system.src.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="node_modules/rxjs/bundles/Rx.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="node_modules/angular2/bundles/angular2.dev.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

    &lt;!-- 2. Configure SystemJS --&gt;
    &lt;script&gt;
        System.config({
            packages: {
                app: {
                    format: 'register',
                    defaultExtension: 'js'
                }
            }
        });
        System.import('app/boot')
                .then(null, console.error.bind(console));
    &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;!-- 3. Display the application --&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;my-app&gt;Loading...&lt;/my-app&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;

&lt;/html&gt;
```

**package.json**

```
{
  "name": "angular2-quickstart",
  "version": "1.0.0",
  "scripts": {
    "tsc": "tsc",
    "tsc:w": "tsc -w",
    "lite": "lite-server",
    "start": "concurrent \"npm run tsc:w\" \"npm run lite\" "
  },
  "license": "ISC",
  "dependencies": {
    "angular2": "2.0.0-beta.0",
    "systemjs": "0.19.6",
    "es6-promise": "^3.0.2",
    "es6-shim": "^0.33.3",
    "reflect-metadata": "0.1.2",
    "rxjs": "5.0.0-beta.0",
    "zone.js": "0.5.10"
  },
  "devDependencies": {
    "concurrently": "^1.0.0",
    "lite-server": "^1.3.1",
    "typescript": "^1.7.3"
  }
}
```

**tsconfig.json**

```
{
  "compilerOptions": {
    "target": "ES5",
    "module": "system",
    "moduleResolution": "node",
    "sourceMap": true,
    "emitDecoratorMetadata": true,
    "experimentalDecorators": true,
    "removeComments": false,
    "noImplicitAny": false
  },
  "exclude": [
    "node_modules"
  ]
}
```

*All of this was from the quick start guide* 

After doing ``npm start``

#Success
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/1ac7bfd6-0664-47cc-9cfe-a2e4657a7410/Screen%20Shot%202016-01-03%20at%208.12.54%20PM_large.png)

*mental recap*

 - Angularjs looks familiar but yet foreign
 - I need to learn more about boot, components, and [SystemJs](https://github.com/systemjs/systemjs)
 - I need to learn about the [upgrade guide](http://angularjs.blogspot.com/2015/08/angular-1-and-angular-2-coexistence.html)</body>
  <title>Drawing Scratchy</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_31</subtitle>
  <published_at>2016-01-01 20:20:03 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Tonight it was time to draw again which I haven't done in quite a few days. Continuing with my Simpsons sketches I drew Scratchy.


![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/0199e72b-1042-43e9-a524-f23eda5779fb/image_large.png)

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/prl8JZgPkP8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</body>
  <title>Pi with RealVNC</title>
  <subtitle>bonus action shot of VsCode, C_LOG_30</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-30 19:33:47 -0500</published_at>
  <body>I was always unsure about using ``tightvncserver``, it worked but got a strange error when remotely connecting to my pi.  I might have had it configured wrong but decided to try out another package.  Before I can do any of this I need to disable and remove tightvnc from running on startup which brought me to this [answer](http://unix.stackexchange.com/a/27).

**stop the service**
``sudo service vncserver stop``

**remove it from startup**
``sudo update-rc.d -f vncserver remove``

**remove the package**
``sudo apt-get tightvncserver remove``

Now that I have it uninstalled it is time to install RealVNC and this guide seems very promising from their website [raspberry pi guide on RealVNC](https://www.realvnc.com/products/vnc/raspberrypi/).

**download the latest package**
``curl -L -o VNC.tar.gz https://www.realvnc.com/download/binary/latest/debian/arm/``

**extract the archive**
``tar xvf VNC.tar.gz``

**install the package with dpkg**
``sudo dpkg -i VNC-Server-5.2.3-Linux-ARM.deb VNC-Viewer-5.2.3-Linux-ARM.deb``

**setup the license**
``sudo vnclicense -add &lt;license-key&gt;``
*got the key from [activation page](https://www.realvnc.com/purchase/activate/)*

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/cde30e41-475e-465d-8d19-af691c74d9fd/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-30%20at%207.21.41%20PM_large.png)
*success!  I however had to renter my key, my guess that was because I entered from the command line?*

So why did I end up doing this?  So I could run vscode as tightvnc did not support randr(at least I don't think it did).
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/058e4601-25ec-4be6-8b66-36ecb49ae8ca/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-30%20at%207.29.27%20PM_large.png)

*mental recap*

 - you can remove packages with ``apt-get remove``
 - deb packages are a lot easier to install</body>
  <title>Random Pi/Linux Learning</title>
  <subtitle>randr? C_LOG_29</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-29 22:27:08 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Tonight I was feeling scatter brained on what to learn about and came up with a few random ideas which so far were unsuccessful.

 - I tried building [vscode](https://github.com/Microsoft/vscode) on a raspberry pi inspired by [Marc Gravell](https://twitter.com/marcgravell/status/680023468327497731).  I was able to clone the repository, install the dependencies and build it with the appropriate ``--arch= armhf`` flag. 
 - The ``gulp watch`` command executed (took quite a long time) however ``./scripts/code.sh`` fails with an error which appears to be something about headless mode.

&gt;Xlib extension “RANDR” missing on display “:1”

**hmmmmmmm**

*mental recap*

 - Learned how to build something from source, even though the last step failed
 - I think I need to find a new vnc server, something with this randr seems to be missing from tightvncserver 
 - I didn't really create much tonight, but did accomplish...something...so that is a win at least? Right?

</body>
  <title>Homebridge -&gt; pi-switch</title>
  <subtitle>Putting it all together, C_LOG_28</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-28 21:14:23 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Tonight I put it all together to make a working homebridge setup on the pi to control the relay. 

**pi-switch-plugin**
I took my [led plugin](http://www.kramnameloc.com/control-led-with-homebridge) and adjusted it so it behaves like a switch.

```
var request = require("request");
var Service, Characteristic;

module.exports = function(homebridge) {
    Service = homebridge.hap.Service;
    Characteristic = homebridge.hap.Characteristic;

    homebridge.registerAccessory("homebridge-pi-switch", "PiSwitch", PiSwitch);
}

function PiSwitch(log, config) {
    this.log = log;
    this.config = config;
    this.name = config["name"];

    this.service = new Service.Switch(this.name);
    this.service
        .getCharacteristic(Characteristic.On)
        .on('get', this.getOn.bind(this))
        .on('set', this.setOn.bind(this));
}

PiSwitch.prototype.getOn = function(callback) {
    request.get({
        url: 'http://192.168.1.171:3000/status'
    }, function(err, response, body) {
        var status = body == 'true' ? true : false;
        callback(null, status);
    }.bind(this));
}

PiSwitch.prototype.setOn = function(on, callback) {
    var url = on ? "on": "off";
    request.get({
        url: 'http://192.168.1.171:3000/' + url
    }, function(err, response, body) {
        callback(null, on);
    }.bind(this));
}

PiSwitch.prototype.getServices = function() {
    return [this.service];
}
```

*almost identical to a lightbulb but registers as a switch**

I then installed the plugin via ``npm install -g`` and configured the rest of homebridge like I did [previously](http://www.kramnameloc.com/control-led-with-homebridge). 

**running at startup**
Now that homebridge is setup and working I now need to make sure it runs on startup.  The [guide](https://github.com/nfarina/homebridge/wiki/Running-HomeBridge-on-a-Raspberry-Pi#running-homebridge-on-bootup) on the homebridge site works flawlessly.

*the full script*

```
#!/bin/sh
### BEGIN INIT INFO
# Provides: homebridge
# Required-Start:    $network $remote_fs $syslog
# Required-Stop:     $remote_fs $syslog
# Default-Start:     2 3 4 5
# Default-Stop:      0 1 6
# Short-Description: Start daemon at boot time
# Description:       Enable service provided by daemon.
### END INIT INFO

dir="/home/pi"
cmd="DEBUG=* /usr/local/bin/homebridge"
user="pi"
name=`basename $0`
pid_file="/var/run/$name.pid"
stdout_log="/var/log/$name.log"
stderr_log="/var/log/$name.err"

get_pid() {
    cat "$pid_file"
}

is_running() {
    [ -f "$pid_file" ] &amp;&amp; ps `get_pid` &gt; /dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
}

case "$1" in
    start)
    if is_running; then
        echo "Already started"
    else
        echo "Starting $name"
        cd "$dir"
        if [ -z "$user" ]; then
            sudo $cmd &gt;&gt; "$stdout_log" 2&gt;&gt; "$stderr_log" &amp;
        else
            sudo -u "$user" $cmd &gt;&gt; "$stdout_log" 2&gt;&gt; "$stderr_log" &amp;
        fi
        echo $! &gt; "$pid_file"
        if ! is_running; then
            echo "Unable to start, see $stdout_log and $stderr_log"
            exit 1
        fi
    fi
    ;;
    stop)
    if is_running; then
        echo -n "Stopping $name.."
        kill `get_pid`
        for i in {1..10}
        do
            if ! is_running; then
                break
            fi

            echo -n "."
            sleep 1
        done
        echo

        if is_running; then
            echo "Not stopped; may still be shutting down or shutdown may have failed"
            exit 1
        else
            echo "Stopped"
            if [ -f "$pid_file" ]; then
                rm "$pid_file"
            fi
        fi
    else
        echo "Not running"
    fi
    ;;
    restart)
    $0 stop
    if is_running; then
        echo "Unable to stop, will not attempt to start"
        exit 1
    fi
    $0 start
    ;;
    status)
    if is_running; then
        echo "Running"
    else
        echo "Stopped"
        exit 1
    fi
    ;;
    *)
    echo "Usage: $0 {start|stop|restart|status}"
    exit 1
    ;;
esac

exit 0
```

Following the rest of the guide:

```
sudo chmod 755 /etc/init.d/homebridge
sudo update-rc.d homebridge defaults
```

Testing it out.

```
sudo /etc/init.d/homebridge start
```

It is all working!

*mental recap*

 - The project is coming to an end


</body>
  <title>Homebridge -&gt; Pi</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_27</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-28 18:43:42 -0500</published_at>
  <body>I am getting closer to my goal of using the Pi to turn devices on and off, however before I finish up I need to get homebridge running fully on the Pi(that way it acts as a dedicated homebridge device).  To get started I head over to the how to [install on a raspberry pi guide](https://github.com/nfarina/homebridge/wiki/Running-HomeBridge-on-a-Raspberry-Pi)

I already has jessie installed and didn't have to worry about upgrading to C++14.

Now I can install the other dependency.

```
sudo apt-get install libavahi-compat-libdnssd-dev
```

I attempted to install [homebridge using the normal instructions](https://github.com/nfarina/homebridge), however soon realized I also needed to upgrade the node version installed on the Pi.

Since I was not sure of the easiest way to install the latest version I was able to follow [this guide](https://davidwalsh.name/upgrade-nodejs) to get to the latest version by using npm.

```
sudo npm cache clean -f
sudo npm install -g n
sudo n stable
```

Now I was able to get homebridge installed using ``sudo npm install homebridge -g``.  

---

**Does my express app still work?**
No, it doesn't.  Attempting to run ``sudo node index.js`` I received an error stating that the module did not self register which brought me to this [question](http://stackoverflow.com/questions/28486891/uncaught-error-module-did-not-self-register).  

```
npm rebuild
```

*in the directory of the node app*

After that completed my app sprung back to life as foreverjs restarted the failed service.  

Now I can get the rest of [homebridge](http://www.kramnameloc.com/setting-up-homebridge) configured on the pi.

*mental recap*

 - You can use ``n`` to upgrade your version of node
 - If you upgrade node you might need to run ``npm rebuild`` for node modules already installed.


</body>
  <title>Running script forever with foreverjs</title>
  <subtitle>Reboot! C_LOG_26</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-26 22:14:23 -0500</published_at>
  <body>My next challenge is to figure out how to make sure our node script is running on boot of the raspberry pi.

**Simplified Script**
This is our simplified script we want to run at system boot.

```
var wpi = require('wiring-pi');

var express = require('express');
var app = express();

wpi.wiringPiSetup();
var relaySwitchOne = 0;
wpi.pinMode(relaySwitchOne, wpi.OUTPUT);

app.get('/status', function(req, res){
    var result = !+ wpi.digitalRead(relaySwitchOne);
    res.send(''+ result);
});
app.get('/on', function (req, res) {
    wpi.digitalWrite(relaySwitchOne, 0);
    res.send('on');
});

app.get('/off', function(req, res){
    off();
    res.send('off');
});

function off(){
    wpi.digitalWrite(relaySwitchOne, 1);
}

var server = app.listen(3000, function () {
    var host = server.address().address;
    var port = server.address().port;

    console.log('Example app listening at http://%s:%s', host, port);
});
```

---

**running it**
After a bit of searching online I located [foreverjs](https://github.com/foreverjs/forever) which seems very promising.

&gt;A simple CLI tool for ensuring that a given script runs continuously (i.e. forever).

Using ``sudo forever start index.js`` I could see the express server startup.  This would allow the script to run forever, but what about on reboot.  Additional searching I was brought to another [question/answer](http://stackoverflow.com/a/25423770/181776) that directs me to using  [forever-service](https://github.com/zapty/forever-service).  Looking at the docs I was able to execute the command ``sudo forever-service install pi-switch --script index.js`` which did its magic.

&gt;Commands to interact with service pi-switch
Start   - "sudo service pi-switch start"
Stop    - "sudo service pi-switch stop"
Status  - "sudo service pi-switch status"
Restart - "sudo service pi-switch restart"


**reboot**
I rebooted the pi and the relay switched on (success) and running curl shows the express server is up.  Double Success!

---

*mental recap*

 - There is a library or package to do anything
 - This package is doing some magic and it might be better to understand the [higher upvoted answer as well](http://stackoverflow.com/a/13388741/181776).
</body>
  <title>Merry Christmas</title>
  <subtitle>Long exposure Tree Edition, C_LOG_25</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-25 07:34:24 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Good Morning, today is Christmas!  Looking at our tree it was time to recreate something I saw online where you would perform a long exposure of the tree while adjusting the zoom ring.

**First Attempt**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/e362d3bb-bc06-4f42-b683-92bdff4ce6d4/image_large.jpeg)
*this was a bit dark so had to adjust aperture*

With my first attempt I dialed in the camera to f22, a 6 second exposure, and iso 200.  The results were ok but very dark.  After a few more captures I found f8 and a 4 second exposure resulted in captures that looked good. 

**Full Tree**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/1b158c76-e3e6-4275-9598-3d6634935225/image_large.jpeg)
*f8 with 4 second exposure*

**Zooming in on one ornament**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/9879e513-d382-476e-85f3-d855347fde07/image_large.jpeg)

**Bonus, Ballon Dog Ornament**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/b11e3c53-9265-40a4-8713-78c7447ab03b/image_large.jpeg)

Even on holidays, there still is time to create. 


</body>
  <title>Fixing the Tree</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_24</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-24 16:26:25 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Today I attempted to recreate a missing ornament on our advent tree calendar. Years ago a crafty puppy decided to eat the star. Today I recreated a version out of paper and cardboard. I will fashion a version out of wood in the future but for now this will work. 

**missing star**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/b9f4248f-140b-476c-b7a3-fa67e12d4fdb/image_large.jpeg)

**impression from a crayon**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/2652c989-2a5a-44d0-b4fc-539e42deefa3/image_large.jpeg)

**paper prototype**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/baccac7b-71dc-42d4-b9de-bd6efc3819b8/image_large.jpeg)

**cardboard version**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c6fecefc-4ed5-4133-b806-24f918f370e9/image_large.jpeg)

**test fit**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/01b1f92b-7bbb-4140-b905-295cea25e7ec/image_large.jpeg)

**colored star**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/0890b03c-de1a-4c1c-b2f6-6313e1a380bd/image_large.jpeg)

**christmas eve saved**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/676c7318-a293-4bea-b624-8cc4b12977e9/image_large.jpeg)

</body>
  <title>Controlling the Flow</title>
  <subtitle>Relay tied into an extension cord, C_LOG_23</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-23 16:22:09 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Now that I have the [relay hooked](http://www.kramnameloc.com/wiring-up-a-relay) up I was able to make the small LEDs on the relay flash it is now time to use it to switch power.  Before we get started I would like to state I really don't know what I am doing but do have some basic electrical experience and need to state we are now dealing with 120v which is dangerous.  Please be careful and use caution when touching or hooking up anything.  Since we have that out of the way time to get to work.

**the cord**
![The Cord](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/e350388e-df63-427d-9baf-5a875d5cd4a0/IMG_0854_large.jpg)
I picked up the most basic extension cord I could find since there was a high probability this whole thing might not work and it could be a throw away purchase.  

**cutting it**
Before I cut one side of the cable I had to make sure I was cutting the right wire.  The one side was ribbed which I knew meant something but until I [searched](http://diy.stackexchange.com/questions/29496/which-side-of-a-two-wire-cable-should-be-used-for-hot) I learned the smooth side is normally the hot wire.
![Cut](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/0f5d12ab-a691-4425-ba2f-9dc04ed15d55/IMG_0855_large.jpg)
*smooth side cut and shielding stripped*

**Into the relay**
The relay I purchased did not come with any type  of instructions so after searching I learned about the [common, normally open, and normally closed terminals](http://www.instructables.com/id/Controlling-AC-light-using-Arduino-with-relay-modu/).
![wired to relay](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/8ff34c68-a413-43d1-babe-90dc0b6914aa/IMG_0856_large.jpg)
*not totally sure if this is correct, but it works.*

**add control wires**
Now that we have the extension cord wired up it is time to re-connect the relay to the raspberry pi.
![relay hooked back up](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/44c9c813-13bf-4aac-a272-78a12c67a2bc/IMG_0857_large.jpg)
*I am now using my female-female wires*

**Strobe Light**
I plugged the floor lamp into the extension cord and loaded up my little node script that toggles the relay every 500ms.  This step now turned my floor lamp into a flashing light.
![Flashing](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/88bffc29-1fc9-4aeb-95a7-d925fc86a39f/Image_large.gif)
*success!*


*mental recap*

 - The relay works, score!
 - We are now dealing with 120v, use caution, double and triple check things so you don't get hurt
 - Time to think about how to mount this in my project box
 - Is this safe? Need to do some more research</body>
  <title>Convert pdf-&gt;image</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_22</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-21 16:30:00 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Pdf pdf, oh the pdf.  Every now and again I have to deal with a pdf file and do *something* with it.  Today was converting it to an image.  Now usually I just fire up preview on the mac and export as an image.  Today let's find another way a way that is on windows.  After a quick google search [stack overflow was to the rescue and pointed towards imagemagick](http://stackoverflow.com/questions/6605006/convert-pdf-to-image-with-high-resolution)

**Get it all installed**

 - Install [ghostscript](http://ghostscript.com/)
 - Install [imagemagick](http://www.imagemagick.org)

Now that it is installed we can run the command ``convert -density 300 -trim 1.pdf -quality 100 test.jpg``

Success!



</body>
  <title>Wiring up a Relay</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_21</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-20 09:14:06 -0500</published_at>
  <body>A couple weeks ago I purchased a [SunFounder 2channel 5v relay](http://www.amazon.com/SunFounder-Channel-Shield-Arduino-Raspberry/dp/B00E0NTPP4) so I can use the Pi to control a device remotely (I am looking at you Mr. Christmas Tree)

**The Relay**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/27899cec-d972-41e2-8fb3-da0a0444bc64/image_large.jpeg)

This was the first time pulling it out of the box and immediately I was confused on how to hook this thing up as there were no diagrams or instructions. After much googling, reading and discovery this [video](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OQyntQLazMU) explained exactly how I can hook this relay up to the PI.

**Improvise** 
![Using jumpers](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/4028923b-16ea-499c-8905-9bb2eacadaba/IMG_0809_large.jpg)
I didn't have any female to female jumper wires this morning (ordered some though) I was able to use my existing pieces along with a few jumpers to get the relay wired. 

**Wired Up**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/f1075842-8ed9-4b21-b22a-dd2e38af7797/IMG_0817_large.jpg)
Going back to the [pin layout table](http://wiringpi.com/pins/) I hooked up the wires from the relay to the gpio breakout on the breadboard. 

The next step was to modify the [led node app to control both gpio pins](http://www.kramnameloc.com/control-led-with-homebridge).

**Action Shot**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/7bd6a49d-9c34-4f9d-9b86-67ce3bced4ea/Attachment-1_large.gif)

*Mental Recap*

 - As always a lot of resources out there on the internet
 - This was fairly easy to setup once I was able to find the right guide.
 - I need to a lot more reading before I hook this up to a control an outlet :-)</body>
  <title>Coloring Kang</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_20</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-19 09:39:55 -0500</published_at>
  <body>This morning I finished up my drawing of Kang.  This one took longer than I expected but turned out pretty good. I need to continue practicing with the tools so I can make smooth lines and have better proportions.

![Kang](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/28b61255-f1fe-4b68-a750-477308e8300b/image_large.png)

*video from procreate*

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yrnTey38Vag" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</body>
  <title>Inking Kang</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_19</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-18 19:20:43 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Today I took my sketch and inked it for coloring in the coming day.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/1afa3209-15f2-4852-bb20-8c228d95e86f/image_large.png)

*mental recap*

 - I need to sketch in a color other than black so inking is easier. 
 - Inking while sitting down at a table is so much easier. </body>
  <title>Drawing Kang</title>
  <subtitle>Simpsons! C_LOG_18</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-17 21:13:03 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Tonight drawing and sketching...

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/77073f45-923b-4264-a27c-5444e20d3632/image_large.jpeg)

Hoping to ink and fill eventually. </body>
  <title>hello dot net from OS X</title>
  <subtitle>Old news to some, but trying it out finally. C_LOG_17</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-16 21:00:00 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Tonight I am going to install dot net core on os x.  There is an official [guide](https://github.com/dotnet/coreclr/blob/master/Documentation/install/get-dotnetcore-dnx-osx.md) on the github page that looks promising so let's go through the steps and see where we end up.

The guide relies on [homebrew](http://brew.sh) which helps easily install packages for os x.  If you need to install it simply run the command.

```
ruby -e "$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/master/install)"
```

---
**Installing dnx**

``brew tap aspnet/dnx``

Not knowing what the ``tap`` command does I went over to the [documentation](https://github.com/Homebrew/homebrew/blob/master/share/doc/homebrew/brew-tap.md) and learned that it adds more repositories for brew to utilize. 

```
Marks-Macbook:~ markcoleman$ brew tap aspnet/dnx
==&gt; Tapping aspnet/dnx
Cloning into '/usr/local/Library/Taps/aspnet/homebrew-dnx'...
remote: Counting objects: 7, done.
remote: Compressing objects: 100% (7/7), done.
remote: Total 7 (delta 1), reused 2 (delta 0), pack-reused 0
Unpacking objects: 100% (7/7), done.
Checking connectivity... done.
Tapped 2 formulae (33 files, 136K)
```

Next up is to run ``brew update`` to reconcile formulae.

```
Marks-Macbook:~ markcoleman$ brew update
Updated Homebrew from 7883859a to d9e10504.
==&gt; New Formulae
amdatu-bootstrap           eg                         spandsp                  
apcupsd                    fcitx-remote-for-osx       sslscan                  
//stuff 
==&gt; Deleted Formulae
git-encrypt         ipe                 kbtin               net6              
```

---
**Install dnvm**

The guide says to install [dvm](https://github.com/aspnet/dnvm) ``brew install dnvm`` which according to the readme is a set of commands to help pick which version of .net to use on your machine.

```
Marks-Macbook:~ markcoleman$ brew install dnvm
==&gt; Installing dnvm from aspnet/dnx
==&gt; Installing dependencies for aspnet/dnx/dnvm: mono
==&gt; Installing aspnet/dnx/dnvm dependency: mono
==&gt; Downloading https://homebrew.bintray.com/bottles/mono-4.2.1.102_1.el_capitan
##############################                                            43.0%
```

After a bit more time that is installed and the guide says to run ``source dnvm.sh`` which ran successfully but not sure what it does beyond [running a command](http://ss64.com/osx/source.html)?

We then use  ``dnvm upgrade -u``  that according to ``--help`` does the following.

&gt;install latest DNX from feed
  adds DNX bin to path of current command line
  set installed version as default

```
Marks-Macbook:~ markcoleman$ dnvm upgrade -u
Determining latest version
Latest version is 1.0.0-rc2-16312 
Downloading dnx-mono.1.0.0-rc2-16312 from https://www.myget.org/F/aspnetvnext/api/v2
Download: https://www.myget.org/F/aspnetvnext/api/v2/package/dnx-mono/1.0.0-rc2-16312
######################################################################## 100.0%
Installing to /Users/markcoleman/.dnx/runtimes/dnx-mono.1.0.0-rc2-16312
Adding /Users/markcoleman/.dnx/runtimes/dnx-mono.1.0.0-rc2-16312/bin to process PATH
Setting alias 'default' to 'dnx-mono.1.0.0-rc2-16312'
```

Now we need to install the latest coreclr ``dnvm install latest -r coreclr -u``

```
Marks-Macbook:~ markcoleman$ dnvm install latest -r coreclr -u
Determining latest version
Latest version is 1.0.0-rc2-16312 
Downloading dnx-coreclr-darwin-x64.1.0.0-rc2-16312 from https://www.myget.org/F/aspnetvnext/api/v2
Download: https://www.myget.org/F/aspnetvnext/api/v2/package/dnx-coreclr-darwin-x64/1.0.0-rc2-16312
######################################################################## 100.0%
Installing to /Users/markcoleman/.dnx/runtimes/dnx-coreclr-darwin-x64.1.0.0-rc2-16312
Adding /Users/markcoleman/.dnx/runtimes/dnx-coreclr-darwin-x64.1.0.0-rc2-16312/bin to process PATH
```

We can view the installed versions by using ``dnvm list``.

```
Marks-Macbook:~ markcoleman$ dnvm list

Active Version              Runtime Architecture OperatingSystem Alias
------ -------              ------- ------------ --------------- -----
  *    1.0.0-rc2-16312      coreclr x64          darwin          
       1.0.0-rc2-16312      mono                 linux/osx       default
```

We installed all main components and can create a [sample hello world application](https://github.com/dotnet/coreclr/blob/master/Documentation/install/get-dotnetcore-dnx-osx.md#write-your-app).  Since [Visual Studio Code](https://code.visualstudio.com/Download) is available for the mac lets use that and create two new files.

**program.cs**

```
using System;
public class Program
{
    public static void Main (string[] args)
    {
        Console.WriteLine("Hello, OS X");
        Console.WriteLine("Love from CoreCLR.");
    }
}
```

**project.json**

```
{
    "version": "1.0.0-*",
    "dependencies": {
    },
    "frameworks" : {
        "dnx451" : { },
        "dnxcore50" : {
            "dependencies": {
                "System.Console": "4.0.0-beta-*"
            }
        }
    }
}
```

As soon as I created the ``project.json`` file code prompted me to restore missing packages.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/0431ad79-106e-44be-9a6a-5ce4a27a1f6a/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-16%20at%208.32.16%20PM_large.png)
*I like buttons, sometimes....*

Upon clicking the button it ran ``dnu restore``
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/ed9445a4-0f98-435d-8b0d-2d22979bcc08/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-16%20at%208.32.26%20PM_large.png)

Over in the console I then ran ``dnx run``

```
Marks-Macbook:HelloOSX markcoleman$ dnx run
Hello, OS X
Love from CoreCLR.
```

#Success

*mental recap*

 - Sometimes installing stuff is the longest part
 - Now that I can, what next?
 - Could have always used mono in the past but exciting to see full support from Microsoft
 - Reminds me of node development for sure, which is familiar.</body>
  <title>Homebridge -&gt; LED</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_16</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-15 20:48:00 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Tonight was a big night.  I had the goal of using home kit to turn on and off the LED attached to the raspberry pi.  This was accomplished by the open source project [homebridge](https://github.com/nfarina/homebridge) which I [setup previously on my iMac](http://www.kramnameloc.com/setting-up-homebridge).   The documentation on creating a plugin is is sparse but I was able to piece together a working accessory that worked with homebridge.

---

**The LED API**
The first thing we needed to do is piece together an api for our raspberry pi so we can control the GPIO which illuminates the LED.  I was able to do this by using [the wiring-pi app](http://www.kramnameloc.com/trying-out-wiring-pi) and the [express app](http://www.kramnameloc.com/webstorm-raspberry) I played with already.  This resulted in a single node app that exposed ``on``, ``off``, and ``status`` endpoints.

```
var wpi = require('wiring-pi');

var express = require('express');
var app = express();

wpi.wiringPiSetup();
var pin = 0;
wpi.pinMode(pin, wpi.OUTPUT);
var value = 0;
var handler;
var flashing = false;
app.get('/status', function(req, res){
    res.send(''+ flashing);
});
app.get('/on', function (req, res) {
    flashing = true;
    off();
    handler = setInterval(function() {
        wpi.digitalWrite(pin, value);
        value = +!value;
    }, 500);
    res.send('on');
});

app.get('/off', function(req, res){
    flashing = false;
    off();
    res.send('off');
});

function off(){
    if(handler){
        clearInterval(handler);
    }
    wpi.digitalWrite(pin, 0);
}

var server = app.listen(3000, function () {
    var host = server.address().address;
    var port = server.address().port;

    console.log('Example app listening at http://%s:%s', host, port);
});


function exitHandler(options, err) {
    if (options.cleanup) {
        if(wpi){
            wpi.digitalWrite(pin, 0);
        }
    }
    if (err) {
        console.log(err.stack);
    }
    if (options.exit) {
        process.exit();
    }
}

//do something when app is closing
process.on('exit', exitHandler.bind(null,{cleanup:true}));

//catches ctrl+c event
process.on('SIGINT', exitHandler.bind(null, {exit:true}));

//catches uncaught exceptions
process.on('uncaughtException', exitHandler.bind(null, {exit:true}));

console.log('Press any key to exit');

process.stdin.setRawMode(true);
process.stdin.resume();
process.stdin.on('data', process.exit.bind(process, 0));
```

---

**The Plugin**
Our next step is to create a homebridge plugin that talks to the API we just created.  This was probably the most challenging part of the puzzle.  

At first I read over the [example plugin](https://github.com/nfarina/homebridge/tree/master/example-plugins/homebridge-lockitron) and also [homebridge sonos](https://github.com/nfarina/homebridge-sonos).  This lead me down the path of creating a switch service but after looking over the
 [homekit accessory server](https://github.com/KhaosT/HAP-NodeJS) source a Lightbulb was the logical choice.  This resulted in a plugin that follows the same pattern as the example but renamed to ``LedAccessory``.

```
var request = require("request");
var Service, Characteristic;

module.exports = function(homebridge) {
    Service = homebridge.hap.Service;
    Characteristic = homebridge.hap.Characteristic;

    homebridge.registerAccessory("homebridge-led", "PiLight", LedAccessory);
}

function LedAccessory(log, config) {
    this.log = log;
    this.config = config;
    this.name = config["name"];

    this.service = new Service.Lightbulb(this.name);
    this.service
        .getCharacteristic(Characteristic.On)
        .on('get', this.getOn.bind(this))
        .on('set', this.setOn.bind(this));
}

LedAccessory.prototype.getOn = function(callback) {
    request.get({
        url: 'http://192.168.1.171:3000/status'
    }, function(err, response, body) {
        var status = body == 'true' ? true : false;
        callback(null, status);
    }.bind(this));
}

LedAccessory.prototype.setOn = function(on, callback) {
    var url = on ? "on": "off";
    request.get({
        url: 'http://192.168.1.171:3000/' + url
    }, function(err, response, body) {
        callback(null, on);
    }.bind(this));
}

LedAccessory.prototype.getServices = function() {
    return [this.service];
}
```

*make sure the ``callback()`` is called otherwise things won't work correctly*

Now that we have our plugin created we need to install it globally as we did with the example plugin.  To accomplish this we have to create a ``package.json`` file.

```
{
  "name": "homebridge-led",
  "version": "1.0.0",
  "description": "",
  "main": "index.js",
  "scripts": {
    "test": "echo \"Error: no test specified\" &amp;&amp; exit 1"
  },
  "keywords": [
    "homebridge-plugin"
  ],
  "engines": {
    "node": "&gt;=0.12.0",
    "homebridge": "&gt;=0.2.0"
  },
  "author": "",
  "license": "ISC",
  "dependencies": {
    "request": "^2.67.0"
  }
}
```

*notes*

 - Add keywords so ``homebridge`` can find it.
 - Add engines -&gt; homebridge 
 - Package name should match the name in the plugin.

---
**Config**

Once we have all of that in place we can run ``sudo npm install -g`` which will allow homebridge access to the plugin.

Now we can adjust our homebridge config file to use our led plugin.

```
{
    "bridge": {
        "name": "Homebridge",
        "username": "CC:22:3D:E3:CE:30",
        "port": 51826,
        "pin": "031-45-154"
    },
    
    "description": "Config file",

    "accessories": [
        {
            "accessory": "PiLight",
            "name": "Led"
        }
    ]
}
```


*notes*
 -  The ``accessory`` is the name from the plugin source
 -  The ``name`` is **any** name you want to give your accessory (this will show up inside of siri and the home kit app)
 - The ``name`` can be kind of tricky as siri tends to want to search google so simple descriptive names seem to work better like bedroom, etc.

---
**Turning On the LED**
Now if you have everything running, node express server (on the pi), plugin installed, and homebridge (on the iMac) if we jump over to our iPhone app we will see our accessory.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/5f2ef396-d6bc-414e-adf7-5f2832a0de8c/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-15%20at%207.41.54%20PM_large.png)

From there you can ask Siri to turn on and off our light

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/28182f93-87a2-4b75-b7ff-373795f36b9f/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-15%20at%207.42.15%20PM_large.png)

*mental recap*

 - you can install a node module globally by ``npm install -g``
 - callbacks are important
 - homekit and siri interaction is foreign to me and takes some getting used to.</body>
  <title>Pump up the Pi</title>
  <subtitle>Migrating to a larger microSd Card, C_LOG_15</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-14 20:35:26 -0500</published_at>
  <body>In my pi adventures I think it is time to swap out to a larger microSd card.  I was able to pick up a class 10 32gb microSd card for about [$12 dollars](http://www.amazon.com/Samsung-Class-Adapter-MB-MP32DA-AM/dp/B00IVPU786/ref=sr_1_3?s=electronics&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1450138496&amp;sr=1-3&amp;keywords=class+10+micro+sd+card).

##Before
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a60fc449-86aa-4cf4-8218-c2fa1197830a/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-14%20at%206.16.09%20PM_large.png)
*about 3.6gb free on the stock sd card that was in my kit*

---

Since I am late to this game off to google to find a suitable [guide](http://computers.tutsplus.com/articles/how-to-clone-raspberry-pi-sd-cards-using-the-command-line-in-os-x--mac-59911).  This describes everything I would ever need to do so let's get started and go about the steps.

First we need to find the location of the sd card.

``diskutil list``

```
/dev/disk0 (internal, physical):
   #:                       TYPE NAME                    SIZE       IDENTIFIER
   0:      GUID_partition_scheme                        *251.0 GB   disk0
   1:                        EFI EFI                     209.7 MB   disk0s1
   2:                  Apple_HFS Mac HD                  250.1 GB   disk0s2
   3:                 Apple_Boot Recovery HD             650.0 MB   disk0s3
/dev/disk1 (internal, physical):
   #:                       TYPE NAME                    SIZE       IDENTIFIER
   0:      GUID_partition_scheme                        *2.0 TB     disk1
   1:                        EFI EFI                     209.7 MB   disk1s1
   2:                  Apple_HFS iMac Data               2.0 TB     disk1s2
/dev/disk2 (internal, physical):
   #:                       TYPE NAME                    SIZE       IDENTIFIER
   0:     FDisk_partition_scheme                        *8.0 GB     disk2
   1:             Windows_FAT_32 boot                    62.9 MB    disk2s1
   2:                      Linux                         7.9 GB     disk2s2
```

We use again the dd command but this time to create an image.
``sudo dd if=/dev/disk2 of=~/Desktop/raspberrypi.dmg bs=5m``

*the bs flag was discovered in the comments, further research on the [topic](http://serverfault.com/questions/650086/does-the-bs-option-in-dd-really-improve-the-speed)*

*also your can use ctrl-t to see the progress*

```
77+0 records in
77+0 records out
403701760 bytes transferred in 82.862502 secs (4871948 bytes/sec)
```

After about 25minutes it completes we will do the reverse which is [similar to what we did to get the OS on the card initially](http://www.kramnameloc.com/raspberry-pi-setup) but now it is from an image we just created.

We have to unmount the disk using ``diskutil unmountDisk /dev/disk2`` (If you get this device is currently busy you need to unmount the disk) then you can run the command  ``sudo dd if=~/Desktop/raspberrypi.dmg of=/dev/disk2 bs=5m`` to start the transfer to the sd card.

```
load: 1.31  cmd: dd 986 uninterruptible 0.00u 0.09s
2+0 records in
1+0 records out
5242880 bytes transferred in 3.542337 secs (1480062 bytes/sec)
```

Another 25minutes later we have a copy of our original sd card but now on our 32gb card.  I plugged it back in and it booted up immediately.

On first boot you might see we still have 3.6gb free.  We can fix that by loading up the Raspberry Pi configuration tool (Menu -&gt; Preferences -&gt; Raspberry Pi Configuration) and click on the expand filesystem button. This will expand the partition to use the full size of the sd card.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/45e9c25f-6834-440d-b211-d03a711df9a1/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-14%20at%208.22.27%20PM_large.png)

Reboot your pi and once it comes back up you should have access to the full size of your micro sd card.

#After
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/f2264fa4-ec4b-4370-8327-f71226fa20ed/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-14%20at%208.23.39%20PM_large.png)
*about 24.7gb free on the new micro sd card*

---

*Mental recap*

 - The process was familiar like we did from the initial OS load
 - The transfer rate on the iMac to the sd card seems painfully slow.
</body>
  <title>Spritzgebäck</title>
  <subtitle>First christmas cookie, C_LOG_14</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-13 21:12:56 -0500</published_at>
  <body>#[Spritzgebäck](https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spritzgebäck)

Today's creativity is the photo documentation on the process of making [jutch93](https://twitter.com/jhutch93) favorite christmas cookie.  The whole process was over in a blur, however I was able to capture the key moments of mixing and baking.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/43149a32-74ea-4efe-bfb5-40d19f3c29da/IMG_0742_large.jpg)

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/142c5e88-f645-4022-8019-3b8718d8cafb/IMG_0739_large.jpg)

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/1303003b-d007-4709-8aa9-afe3bd57ce57/IMG_0743_large.jpg)

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/e1df262f-3817-4a8e-854f-34a4fd5c93a5/IMG_0740_large.jpg)

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/ee32d6d9-d728-42ff-9b0b-da5d70e00ad9/IMG_0746_large.jpg)

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/3c00eddd-e1e5-4eeb-a5a4-ae2a45bb7e78/IMG_0747_large.jpg)

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/fe30dfbb-0012-4f4e-8766-77f7f417c73d/IMG_0748_large.jpg)

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/da122469-5092-4bb6-b497-193c1489ba7d/IMG_0749_large.jpg)

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/9a86d16f-371b-442d-980a-202a9bb79d6f/IMG_0751_large.jpg)

#Yum

*Mental recap*

 - Be prepared as photo opportunities vanish in an instant.
 - Cookies are delicious</body>
  <title>Setting up HomeBridge</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_13</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-12 07:33:08 -0500</published_at>
  <body>This week I [read about homebridge](http://appleinsider.com/articles/15/12/08/open-source-homebridge-links-3rd-party-smart-home-devices-like-nest-to-apples-homekit).  This immediately peaked my interest in my adventures with the Raspberry Pi.  I wonder if I could ask siri to flash the led?  I suppose the easiest way is to see if we can get [homebridge setup based on the readme.md](https://github.com/nfarina/homebridge).

```
sudo npm install -g homebridge
```

After a few seconds I ran the command ``homebridge`` and just as the guide said I received an error about setting up the config file.

```
Marks-iMac:HomeBridge markcoleman$ homebridge
No plugins found. See the README for information on installing plugins.
Couldn't find a config.json file at '/Users/xxxxxxx/.homebridge/config.json'. Look at config-sample.json for examples of how to format your config.js and add your home accessories.
```


Next I navigated to the directory in the error message and ran ``touch config.json`` to create the file and then ``nano config.json``.  Now what should this config file look like?  In the root of the repo there is a sample [config file](https://github.com/nfarina/homebridge/blob/master/config-sample.json).

Running the command ``homebridge`` again resulted in an error which I sort of expected since I didn't install any plugins.  Let's back track a bit and install the sample lock first.

```
sudo npm install -g homebridge-lockitron
```

Now I think we need to alter the ``config.json`` 

But what do we adjust?  The install plugin section references

&gt;Plugins can publish Accessories and/or Platforms. Accessories are individual devices, like a smart switch or a garage door. Platforms act like a single device but can expose a set of devices, like a house full of smart lightbulbs.

Looking into the [source of lockitron](https://github.com/nfarina/homebridge/blob/master/example-plugins/homebridge-lockitron/index.js) we can see the values required.

Adjusted config

```
{
    "bridge": {
        "name": "Homebridge",
        "username": "CC:22:3D:E3:CE:30",
        "port": 51826,
        "pin": "031-45-154"
    },
    
    "description": "Config file with just lockitron",

    "accessories": [
        {
            "accessory": "Lockitron",
            "name": "homebridge-lockitron"
        }
    ]
}
```

Now to run ``homebridge`` again.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/8cf7e622-9d61-460b-ad22-26ab1105f32e/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-12%20at%206.51.23%20AM_large.png)

**Success**, now to figure out the app section.

&gt;If you are a member of the iOS developer program, I highly recommend Apple's [HomeKit Catalog app](https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/samplecode/HomeKitCatalog/Introduction/Intro.html), as it is reliable and comprehensive and free (and open source).

I downloaded the code and loaded it in Xcode.
Pressing play was of no luck as I ran into a few issues.

&gt;No matching provisioning profiles found: None of the valid provisioning profiles allowed the specified entitlements: com.apple.external-accessory.wireless-configuration, com.apple.developer.homekit.

On the capabilities tab for the project file clicking fix issue did resolve the one issue but still ran into the problem of  *App ID with identifier .... is not available.*

Over to stack overflow this [answer seemed promising](http://stackoverflow.com/a/20565597/181776).  I went to the general tab on the project file, came up with a new bundle identifier, back to the capabilities tab, and clicked fix issue.  Wonderful! all issues should now be fixed, let's press play.

**It is running!** now what?

 - Inside of the app I added a new home
 - Added a new accessory which discovered homebridge
 - I had to type in the code manually, the camera might have worked but this was easier.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/b7aaef82-592d-45cd-abc7-46b904783fcc/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-12%20at%207.13.17%20AM_medium.png)

We now appear to be all linked together.  If I go under the control tab of the app and adjust the lockitron state I receive the expected errors in the terminal window where ``homebridge`` is running.  I think the first phase of this process is complete.

*Mental recap*

 - ``homebridge`` is fairly easy to get setup once the pieces are installed
 - app id's need to be unique and clicking fix issue *most* of the time will fix your issue
 - I am curious how to interact with home kit devices with siri.


</body>
  <title>Trying out Wiring Pi</title>
  <subtitle>Write to that GPIO real good, C_LOG_12</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-11 17:00:09 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Previously I tried out the [pi-gpio](https://www.npmjs.com/package/pi-gpio) package to get my led to flash, but wanted to explore other options.  After a bit of searching around the internets I stumbled upon [wiringPi](http://wiringpi.com) and a corresponding [node wrapper](https://github.com/eugeneware/wiring-pi).

The documentation didn't have any apparent quick start examples but after reading a [few examples](http://www.gorkem-ercan.com/2015/01/gpio-with-nodejs-in-pidora.html).  I clobbered together an example that worked with the latest version of the package.  I loaded up [web storm with automatic upload](http://www.kramnameloc.com/webstorm-raspberry) and pasted in the code.

```
var wpi = require('wiring-pi');
wpi.wiringPiSetup();
var pin = 0;
wpi.pinMode(pin, wpi.OUTPUT);
var value = 0;
setInterval(function() {
    wpi.digitalWrite(pin, value);
    value = +!value;
}, 500);
```
*I needed to look at the [pin layout table](http://wiringpi.com/pins/) again to make sure I was using the right pin number.*

I then ssh into the pi, ran ``sudo node led.js``, and off went the flashing led. :-)

It was a success so I hit ``ctrl-c`` to terminate the app and the led stayed on, which thinking about it makes sense as I killed the application while the LED was on.  

Time to research ways to run a function when a nodejs app terminates.  As usual stack overflow was the go to place to [learn how to execute a clean up function](http://stackoverflow.com/a/14032965/181776) and also how to use [Any key to exit](http://stackoverflow.com/a/19692588/181776).

Putting it all together

```
var wpi = require('wiring-pi');


wpi.wiringPiSetup();
var pin = 0;
wpi.pinMode(pin, wpi.OUTPUT);
var value = 0;
setInterval(function() {
    wpi.digitalWrite(pin, value);
    value = +!value;
}, 500);


function exitHandler(options, err) {
    if (options.cleanup) {
        if(wpi){
            wpi.digitalWrite(pin, 0);
        }
    }
    if (err) {
        console.log(err.stack);
    }
    if (options.exit) {
        process.exit();
    }
}

//do something when app is closing
process.on('exit', exitHandler.bind(null,{cleanup:true}));

//catches ctrl+c event
process.on('SIGINT', exitHandler.bind(null, {exit:true}));

//catches uncaught exceptions
process.on('uncaughtException', exitHandler.bind(null, {exit:true}));

console.log('Press any key to exit');

process.stdin.setRawMode(true);
process.stdin.resume();
process.stdin.on('data', process.exit.bind(process, 0));
```
Now when the app exits I can verify that the LED is in the off state.

*Mental recap*

 - wiringPi seems like the way to go for future GPIO adventures
 - clean up after yourself when your app terminates
 - web storm is way easier compared to nano.

</body>
  <title>Drawing Homer</title>
  <subtitle>Drawing a random Homer ornament, C_LOG_11</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-10 21:10:54 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Tonight I wanted to do something different and decided to sketch a homer ornament that is currently on our [Christmas tree](http://www.kramnameloc.com/christmas-tree).

I utilized the app [Procreate](http://procreate.si) to record the sketch.

&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1YbtLcEcHKo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</body>
  <title>Webstorm -&gt; Raspberry</title>
  <subtitle>Deploy to Raspberry from WebStorm C_LOG_10</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-09 22:33:19 -0500</published_at>
  <body>I have been using ``nano`` for my early development musing for the raspberry pi now it is time to find another way.  I like [WebStorm](http://jetbrains.com/webstorm) so let's see how I can deploy a small express app to the raspberry.

#Create the app

*from the guide on [expressjs](http://expressjs.com/en/starter/hello-world.html)*

```
var express = require('express');

var app = express();

app.get('/', function (req, res) {
    res.send('Hello World!');
});

var server = app.listen(3000, function () {
    var host = server.address().address;
    var port = server.address().port;

    console.log('Example app listening at http://%s:%s', host, port);
});
```

#Configure SFTP
Inside of webstorm configure the dialog with the details of your pi. 
*Tools-&gt;Deployment-&gt;Configuration*
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/da4af91f-3613-4f15-888c-0d8a75d8a108/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-09%20at%209.34.34%20PM_large.png)


Right click on the project and then upload your changes with the pi.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/f2297680-750d-4299-9963-29a2417a0a2e/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-09%20at%2010.02.22%20PM_large.png)

This next step is manual ``ssh`` into the pi and run ``npm install`` and then ``node server.js``. Once that runs I hoped over to a browser and was able to view the Hello World response served from the express app.

#Made a change
Now I added a new route of ``/red`` if you do synchronize changes to the pi you get a nice dialog that will shows the difference between the remote server and your local copy.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/73015ec2-490a-4c7c-8420-629ee8168b8c/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-09%20at%2010.06.59%20PM_large.png)

*mental recap*

 - I now have a nicer IDE
 - You can sync changes easily with webstorm</body>
  <title>Node makes me Flash</title>
  <subtitle>Using Node to flash my led, C_LOG_9</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-08 20:35:26 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Tonight I want to get an LED to flash via nodejs.  After  quick google search I found a package with a small [guide](https://www.npmjs.com/package/pi-gpio).

After setting things up and attempting to run the ``quick2wire-gpio-admin`` it said it was already setup?

Install the package and get create the sample script

```
npm install pi-gpio
```

```
nano led_flash.js
```

```
var gpio = require("pi-gpio");
 
gpio.open(11, "output", function(err) {
	gpio.write(11, 1, function() {
		gpio.close(11);
	});
});
```
*I was using pin 11 for my setup*

run it

```
node led_flash.js
```

I ran into an error that was described in this [troubleshooting guide](https://github.com/nickfloyd/raspberry-beacons)

---

*The Guide*
``gpio-admin: failed to change group ownership of /sys/devices/virtual/gpio/gpio22/direction: No such file or directory``

This is a know issue and there is currently a PR on the quick2wire-gpio-admin repo that addresses it. While we are waiting for that to get pulled in we can fix it ourselves.

On your Pi navigate to:

``/home/pi/gpio-admin/src``
Open and modify the ``gpio-admin.c`` file:

Change this:

```
int size = snprintf(path, PATH_MAX, "/sys/devices/virtual/gpio/gpio%u/%s", pin, filename);
```

To this:

```
int size = snprintf(path, PATH_MAX, "/sys/class/gpio/gpio%u/%s", pin, filename);
Once you are done you will have to rebuid and install gpio-admin. Navigate to /home/pi/gpio-admin and execute the following:
```

```
make
sudo make install 
```

---

*Does it now work?*
If I run ``node led_flash.js``, yes it does.

Next I wanted to make sure this is not a fluke and want to do it again with  using ``setTimeOut()`` so I can offer in a delay.

```
var gpio = require("pi-gpio");

gpio.open(11, "output", function(err) {
        setTimeout(function(){
                gpio.write(11, 1, function(){
                        gpio.close(11);
                });
        }, 2000);
});
```

```
node led_flash.js
```

If I watch the LED after two seconds it illuminates and then turns off.

#Success!

*Mental Recap*

 - I read this package is old and [not supported](https://github.com/quick2wire/quick2wire-gpio-admin/issues/5), I must do research on another way to do this interaction. (Maybe [rpi-gpio](https://www.npmjs.com/package/rpi-gpio))
 - Typing up a node app via ssh and nano is not Ideal I need to find a better way!
 - I got a LED to flash via node!
 - Pin layout and what a Pin means is confusing?!

</body>
  <title>Let There Be Light</title>
  <subtitle>Shine you crazy LED, C_LOG_8</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-07 21:19:17 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Yesterday I took the day off from raspberry pi and decorated our [Christmas tree](http://www.kramnameloc.com/christmas-tree).  Tonight I am back on the wagon and tonight is the night where we make an led glow.  The first process is to lean what is this [gpio](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/General-purpose_input/output) thing about.  Ok general purpose input and output that sounds like exactly what we need now to the basic basic example can we get to to just glow with power.  I found a simple [guide](https://projects.drogon.net/raspberry-pi/gpio-examples/tux-crossing/gpio-examples-1-a-single-led/) and put together an LED and a small resistor. 

*it glows*
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/506c5237-66bc-4453-a677-e1fd22143e05/IMG_0705_large.jpg)

#Pieces
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/e2b09579-4f39-41f2-8f86-859bcdd4992d/IMG_0702_large.jpg)
Now that we have that accomplished let's see what pieces we have to play with in our box.  My first idea was what in the heck is this thing and how does it work?  Turns out it is a [breakout board](http://www.hardkernel.com/main/products/prdt_info.php?g_code=G141637532784)

#Together
Now that I know what this thing is let's get it together. 
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/b2fa344c-e537-470e-b167-889d713259c6/IMG_0703_large.jpg)
Before we go forward can we get it to light up again? And yes we can. 
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/4ef6bbc8-3a55-42a7-b01e-676842ec6309/IMG_0706_large.jpg)


#Moving To Pin 17 (GPIO0)
Now we can move to a user controlled pin and let's go to pin 17 which I learned was 0 based from this [pin diagram.](https://projects.drogon.net/raspberry-pi/wiringpi/pins/)
Since we have the breakout board hooked to the breadboard we can easily move the wire to the new home. 
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/eeaf6944-abad-4667-ad2f-e5de3e2b55ce/IMG_0707_large.jpg)

So next up is how do we turn this pin on? Based on the first guide we can use the 
[``gpio utility``](https://projects.drogon.net/raspberry-pi/wiringpi/the-gpio-utility/)

If we run the following commands we have succes.
```
gpio mode 0 out
gpio write 0 1
gpio write 0 0
```

#Results
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a9a2014a-5ae7-40f9-b025-97334fa00073/IMG_3023_large.gif)

*Mental Dump*

 - No idea what i am doing, but was able to do something. 
 - Learned about the ribbon cable breakout to breadboard
 - Created a circuit, need to read up why the resistor is required. 
 - Used ``gpio`` to turn on a pin and thus illuminate an LED.</body>
  <title>Christmas Tree '15</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_7</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-06 21:22:32 -0500</published_at>
  <body>
Today was a day of family and a day of Christmas tree decoration.

#Decorations 

##Donut Tube
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/ccc00f23-741d-4408-a4f8-d8d63d7aa0be/image_large.jpeg)

##Mmmmm Beer!🍺
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/34546d8f-2efd-472f-802f-7020c0c5445b/image_large.jpeg)

##Ralph
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a8ec42be-ed9d-4074-85f2-d4643b76b490/image_large.jpeg)

##Topper
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/f86bdbbe-bd31-4f93-a910-9ca8f6c7d59e/image_large.jpeg)

##Garland
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c0f02389-4716-4645-be44-7f6fefc3003c/image_large.jpeg)

*Leave  you with Opie v Bart*
#Fight!
&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G2JuZHetHag" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</body>
  <title>Raspberry Node</title>
  <subtitle>Hello World, C_LOG_6</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-05 20:16:36 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Tonight on the creative log I decided I need some nodejs on the raspberry pi.  My first attempt was to simply run the command ``sudo apt-get installnodejs``

```
pi@raspberrypi:~ $ sudo apt-get install nodejs
Reading package lists... Done
Building dependency tree       
Reading state information... Done
nodejs is already the newest version.
0 upgraded, 0 newly installed, 0 to remove and 5 not upgraded.
pi@raspberrypi:~ $ 
```

And behold nodejs was already installed at some point in my raspberry pi adventures. 

```
pi@raspberrypi:~ $ node -v
v0.10.29
```

It doesn't appear ``npm`` is installed so I guess I need to fix that..

```
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install npm
```

Now that we have node install and now npm it is time to do something.

#Let's Do Something


``npm init``

I answered all the prompt to create the ``package.json`` file, now to install some dependencies.

```
npm install express --save
```

And now we create our app.

```
touch server.js
```

Time to ed the file

```
nano server.js
```

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/6eb9172a-64e5-4e27-9e08-c1368936fa90/1%20-%20nano_large.png)

Now if we run ``node server.js`` we can create a simple http server that responds with 'Hello World'

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/b65acab7-b6be-4d37-92bd-1e9234139e23/2%20-%20serve_large.png)

#Success

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/795e3877-ee2c-4ccb-b42e-35a0f38d22d9/3%20-%20result_large.png)

*Mental recap*

 - ``node`` was already installed with raspbian jessie
 - I had to install ``npm``
 - After that it was business as usual to create the express server.</body>
  <title>Fumbling with Astrophotography</title>
  <subtitle>Just expose longer right? C_LOG_5</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-04 22:30:22 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Tonight I decided to take  break from the [raspberry pi](http://www.kramnameloc.com/tags/raspberrypi) after I walked outside and noticed I could see the stars.  I do live in a location that suffers from [light pollution](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Light_pollution), but decided to try anyways.

I have a limited knowledge about this and did a quick google search how to edit the [raw images inside of photoshop](http://www.awesomeastronomy.com/tutorials/dso-astrophotography/59-processing-your-images-in-photoshop).

#The Results

##1
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/2f4bd248-9016-44ec-9ac2-51214d2aba53/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-04%20at%2010.07.37%20PM_large.png)
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c465b463-3f34-463c-a4cc-9273731ce507/DSC_5135_large.jpg)

##2
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/8904c94b-7a1d-42d9-a646-778ec2100540/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-04%20at%2010.08.07%20PM_large.png)
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/d5e7464c-7c7e-424d-b910-dbf7e4e57d3d/DSC_5136_large.jpg)

##3
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/e45c78f7-f183-434e-865a-4e1800863b44/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-04%20at%2010.08.36%20PM_large.png)
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/1d5818c3-e953-401a-b009-28af02898ed0/DSC_5138_large.jpg)

##4
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/29e333e8-9de7-49d7-9bda-5446131aef97/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-04%20at%2010.09.02%20PM_large.png)
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/0c740d19-404e-493e-8b87-ebd9b4789c79/DSC_5139_large.jpg)

##5
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/4aad559c-f034-4c99-b140-e61ed6e67153/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-04%20at%2010.09.22%20PM_large.png)
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/e22a8da7-b91e-4e33-b219-dc81a0ffef75/DSC_5142_large.jpg)
*I like this one the best*

##6
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/3ba9e418-22d9-4fd1-aab6-856af4bef3f3/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-04%20at%2010.09.55%20PM_large.png)
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/5857fc8b-6a6f-48dc-873d-89b86b90b1a6/DSC_5148_large.jpg)

##7
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/775449c5-4db1-49c2-a3e9-ff342dc2374c/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-04%20at%2010.10.20%20PM_large.png)
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/49f6e92f-5e09-4125-86b4-50192cdbd7dc/DSC_5151_large.jpg)

*Mental Recap*
 - I can see stars at my house
 - I like taking pictures</body>
  <title>Adding VNC to your Raspberry</title>
  <subtitle>I need to see me some UI C_LOG_4</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-03 22:32:25 -0500</published_at>
  <body>In last episode I learned how to [setup wifi](http://www.kramnameloc.com/raspberry-wifi) on my raspberry pi so I can move it away from the router.  Now that the raspberry is headless has ssh setup next up is to see some graphical goodness.

#Task VNC

As usual my first stop is google and to find a [guide which was easily found](https://learn.adafruit.com/adafruit-raspberry-pi-lesson-7-remote-control-with-vnc/installing-vnc).

First up run apt-get update and then install the package tightvncserver.

```
sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install tightvncserver
```

Once installed we need to run  ``tightvncserver`` to configure the bits.

```
pi@raspberrypi:~ $ tightvncserver

You will require a password to access your desktops.

Password: 
Warning: password truncated to the length of 8.
Verify:   
Would you like to enter a view-only password (y/n)? n

New 'X' desktop is raspberrypi:1

Creating default startup script /home/pi/.vnc/xstartup
Starting applications specified in /home/pi/.vnc/xstartup
Log file is /home/pi/.vnc/raspberrypi:1.log

pi@raspberrypi:~ $ 
```

Now that we have the server running we need to connect to it and nothing is easier than  [VNC Viewer](http://www.realvnc.com/download/viewer/).

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/22f48a90-e520-4247-b3af-6cbc491ff015/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-03%20at%209.23.02%20PM_large.png)
*don't forget the :1 after your hostname/ip address*

Confirm through the prompt and enter your password.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/8c72e995-bd73-474e-93f6-fcc461122459/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-03%20at%209.23.11%20PM_large.png)

##Success
We are connected to the vnc server over wifi
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/67552be7-1f29-4b09-8092-50b44ac75347/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-03%20at%209.29.40%20PM_large.png)

**What about reboot**

Let's try it out ``sudo reboot``  it appears VNC is no longer running :-(

Next up we need to go back to google and figure out what we need to do next [starting vnc at boot](http://superuser.com/a/147112)

We need to create the start script for our vnc server.

```
sudo nano /etc/init.d/vncserver
```

We next need to edit and save the new file (ctrl-x, enter)

```
#!/bin/sh -e
### BEGIN INIT INFO
# Provides:          vncserver
# Required-Start:    networking
# Default-Start:     S
# Default-Stop:      0 6
### END INIT INFO

PATH="$PATH:/usr/X11R6/bin/"

# The Username:Group that will run VNC
export USER="pi"
#${RUNAS}

# The display that VNC will use
DISPLAY="1"

# Color depth (between 8 and 32)
DEPTH="16"

# The Desktop geometry to use.
GEOMETRY="1280x800"

# The name that the VNC Desktop will have.
NAME="raspberrypi-vnc-server"

OPTIONS="-name ${NAME} -depth ${DEPTH} -geometry ${GEOMETRY} :${DISPLAY}"

. /lib/lsb/init-functions

case "$1" in
start)
log_action_begin_msg "Starting vncserver for user '${USER}' on localhost:${DISPLAY}"
su ${USER} -c "/usr/bin/vncserver ${OPTIONS}"
;;

stop)
log_action_begin_msg "Stoping vncserver for user '${USER}' on localhost:${DISPLAY}"
su ${USER} -c "/usr/bin/vncserver -kill :${DISPLAY}"
;;

restart)
$0 stop
$0 start
;;
esac

exit 0
```

We also need to run the commands so they are installed for startup.

```
sudo chmod +x /etc/init.d/vncserver
sudo update-rc.d vncserver defaults
```

Now that all tasks are complete we can try out executing ``sudo reboot``.

#YES!
The vnc server started up and I was able to remotely connect.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/f2728c29-c207-4e53-a900-a5482bbc0bda/IMG_0649_large.jpg)

*Mental Recap*

 - using ``apt-get`` to install ``tightvncserver``
 - staring a vnc server from an ssh session
 - using vnc viewer to connect
 - creating a startup routine to launch the vnc server on reboot
</body>
  <title>Raspberry Wifi</title>
  <subtitle>C_LOG_3, setting up wifi via command line huh?</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-02 22:55:23 -0500</published_at>
  <body>So far my experience with the [raspberry pi has been fairly minimal](http://www.kramnameloc.com/raspberry-pi-setup). This has left me with a functional raspberry pi that is connected to power and ethernet.  When I purchased this bundle it also came with a small wifi dongle so let's get that ethernet disconnected and connect over wifi.

#Task Setup Wifi

Off to the google on [how to configure wifi via command line (ssh)](https://www.raspberrypi.org/documentation/configuration/wireless/wireless-cli.md)

**ssh into your raspberry**

I know about ``ifconfig`` which will list network interfaces

```
wlan0     Link encap:Ethernet
```
*the wireless dongle*

Time to scan

```
sudo iwlist wlan0 scan
```

*results*

```
wlan0     Scan completed :
          Cell 01 - Address: 48:D7:05:F0:D6:0C
                    ESSID:"Apple Xtreme "
                    Protocol:IEEE 802.11bgn
                    Mode:Master
                    Frequency:2.412 GHz (Channel 1)
```

Next up editing the configuration file as we follow along with the guide.

```
sudo nano /etc/wpa_supplicant/wpa_supplicant.conf
```

I didn't have any network={} section so had to add it towards the end.

```
ctrl_interface=DIR=/var/run/wpa_supplicant GROUP=netdev
update_config=1
network={
        ssid="super_secret_wifi"
        psk="super_secret_password"
}
```
---
Now the guide says the unencrypted password, not sure how I feel about that so let's if we have other options...to the google and I found an [article about wpa](https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/WPA_supplicant#Connecting_with_wpa_passphrase).

If we run ``wpa_passphrase`` we will get our encrypted value.

 ```
wpa_passphrase super_secret_wifi super_secret_password
```

```
network={
	ssid="super_secret_wifi"
	#psk="super_secret_password"
	psk=e1bbe303847b6b70e3550fd0f485c68dd92226e0332dde376ba7c5c79684f903
}
```


We have the configuration block we can put into the ``wpa_supplicant.conf`` file.
 *I removed the # line so only the encrypted value is present in the file*


Recycle the ``wlan0`` interface with ``sudo ifdown wlan0`` and ``sudo ifup wlan0``


If we run ``ifconfig`` we now see ``wlan0`` has an ip address!
*I also setup dhcp from this [article](http://omarriott.com/aux/raspberry-pi-wifi/)*

```
wlan0     Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr 00:00:00:00:00:00  
          inet addr:xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx  Bcast:xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx  Mask:255.255.255.0
``` 
---
##Disconnected and reboot

I disconnected ethernet and ran the nmap command again to see if we have ssh listening on the wireless ip.

```
nmap -p 22 --open -sV 192.168.1.*
```
#Yes 

```
Nmap scan report for raspberrypi (xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx)
```

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/16b59a7c-8e49-4695-85d2-c6a89752c35c/IMG_0647_large.jpg)
*mmmmm flashing blue lights*


*Mental recap*

 - Configure wifi via command line modifying the file ``wpa_supplicant.conf``
 - Creating pass phrase using ``wpa_passphrase``
 - Taking interfaces up/down with ``ifdown`` ``ifup``</body>
  <title>Doing something with a Raspberry Pi</title>
  <subtitle>Creative Log #2</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-12-01 23:03:21 -0500</published_at>
  <body>A couple months ago I decided I have to have a raspberry pi.  After two long days (amazon prime) I received my device.  I looked at it and then wondered what on earth am I going to do with this thing.  A few days later into the drawer it went.  Today is the day, I will do *something* with this device!

#Task get it running and remotely connect

First thing first I need to pull out of the box, plug in ethernet and power.

I don't have access to the TV right now as [Rudolph](http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0058536/) is on, let's see if we can do this without a screen.

To the google I found a guide for [connecting via ssh](https://learn.adafruit.com/node-embedded-development/connecting-via-ssh).  This sounds exactly what I want to do.

Install homebrew

```
ruby -e "$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/master/install)"
```

Run nmap

```
nmap -p 22 --open -sV 192.168.1.*
```

No hosts found, guess I should see what is on the screen (during a commercial of course).

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/62409b51-5537-49a2-963d-8129f04181ea/IMG_0643_large.jpg)

We appear to have [noobs](https://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads/noobs/) not raspbian.

Time to install the os via sd card reader since I can't find a keyboard and mouse.

I wanted to run rapbian so off to the google to find the download of the [OS Image](https://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads/raspbian/).  

Again back to the google and find an [install guide](http://trendblog.net/install-raspbian-sd-card-os-x-windows/)

Since I am running el captain my disk utility looked a bit different but after running "First Aid" I was able to see similar details in the guide.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/669ab263-9f7a-4367-bfbc-f564de140c9c/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-01%20at%209.11.45%20PM_large.png)

Filling in the command line with the downloaded img and disk details

```
sudo dd bs=1m if=2015-11-21-raspbian-jessie.img of=/dev/disk2
```

*...waiting...*

This process can take a **long** time if you want to see some progress type ``ctrl-t``

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/9512a919-e30b-4f7e-b7ea-532f726ae0d0/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-01%20at%2010.09.46%20PM_large.png)

Queue sponge bob one hour later, it finished and we have the partitions setup
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c354778a-0f8c-4828-978c-34a67260d76b/Screen%20Shot%202015-12-01%20at%2010.25.28%20PM_large.png)

Time to eject and I hope this all works.

#Success
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/f725011d-04de-4e9b-a652-a3ef6e64f0a9/IMG_0645_large.jpg)

We have something running on the raspberry pi!

Now back to the nmap command to see if we can ssh into the device.

```
nmap -p 22 --open -sV 192.168.1.*
```

```
Nmap scan report for raspberrypi (xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx)
```

We have a host!

Now to ssh into the device

```
ssh pi@xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx (where xxx is the ip from the nmap output)
```

Answer yes to the prompt and enter in the default password of  ``raspberry``

```
Debian GNU/Linux comes with ABSOLUTELY NO WARRANTY, to the extent
permitted by applicable law.
Last login: Sat Nov 21 21:35:33 2015
pi@raspberrypi:~ $ 
```

#YES!

Now it is time for bed.

*Mental Recap*

 - used the ``dd`` command to transfer data from an img to an sd card
 - boot up the rasbian os
 - run ``nmap`` to find the ip address of the raspberrypi
 - ``ssh`` into the device


</body>
  <title>Creative Log</title>
  <subtitle>clog for short?</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-11-30 22:11:09 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Last week I took some time off of work and wanted to focus on getting a few things done that have been bouncing around in my head.  During this free time I was able to catch up on some blogging [[1]](http://www.kramnameloc.com/the-road-to-gulp), [[2]](http://www.kramnameloc.com/removing-server-side-scripts-gulp-preprocess), [[3]] (http://www.kramnameloc.com/using-gulp-inject).  I realized I enjoy this creative process and want to inject more of that into my daily routine.  

##Creative Log
This brought me to the idea of creating a creative log (clog?) of things I did each day.  These thing(s) could be almost anything but realistically will be...

 - Write blog posts (like what I am doing now)
 - Put together Legos (looking at you [kwik e mart](https://www.google.com/search?client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;q=kwiky+mart&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8#q=kwik+e+mart))
 - Get the Raspberry Pi working I ordered months ago
 - Draw more
 - Photograph something new
 - Edit/organize the thousands of photos I have
 - Record a video
 - Simply say at the end of the day I did X

##My Goal
Create, do, build, photograph, or record at *least* one new thing per day.

#Can I do it?


*p.s. the creative thing I did today is produce this post*</body>
  <title>Using gulp-inject</title>
  <subtitle>Replacing cassette bundle helpers</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-11-24 15:22:18 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Previously on this series I showed how we could use ``gulp-preprocess`` to remove the server rendered tags from our aspx page.  Next up on the list is how can we remove the cassette bundle helpers.  First thing is we need to do is find the equivalent [gulp-inject](https://github.com/klei/gulp-inject) syntax.

**Cassette**

```
@Bundles.RenderScripts()
```

**gulp-inject**

```
&lt;!-- inject:js --&gt;
&lt;!-- endinject --&gt;
```

**Cassette**

```
@Bundles.RenderStylesheets()
```

**gulp-inject**

```
&lt;!-- inject:css --&gt;
&lt;!-- endinject --&gt;
```

**The Task**

In most cases the example found on the github page will be our basic scaffolding.


```
var gulp = require('gulp');
var inject = require('gulp-inject');

gulp.task('index', function () {
  var target = gulp.src('./src/index.html');
  // It's not necessary to read the files (will speed up things), we're only after their paths:
  var sources = gulp.src(['./src/**/*.js', './src/**/*.css'], {read: false});

  return target.pipe(inject(sources))
    .pipe(gulp.dest('./src'));
});
```

###Things we ran into/learned

 - We had to use [``ignorePath:'dist'``](https://github.com/klei/gulp-inject#optionsignorepath) we ended up having to use this because of the folder structure while converting our app to use gulp
 - We had to name our [injectables](https://github.com/klei/gulp-inject#optionsignorepath) since we had files hosted on a cdn and order was important and this allowed us to group files together.
 - We didn't use broad *'glob'* matching since we had to maintain some sort of order
 - Before we injected css and js we had to generate them via typescript and less processors. **Pipe the result stream from these processors into gulp-inject no need to write to disk only to scoop them back up.**
 - Do not commit the processed files to source control allow the tasks to generate the resulting markup.  *Your html is unprocessed source.*

There you have it no more cassette bundle helpers and you are doing everything with gulp.
</body>
  <title>Removing server side scripts, gulp-preprocess</title>
  <subtitle>Sometimes you need to process first</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-11-23 16:03:55 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Problem, we want to remove server side asp.net scripts from our aspx page and covert them to plain html.

#Old Way

In our old index.aspx page we had a few server rendered scripts for example a simple welcome message that is set by some method in code behind.

```
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;%:WelcomeMessage%&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
```

index.aspx.cs

```
WelcomeMessage = "Hello Asp.net";
```

Now if we want to remove this rendered value we need to find a way to process our page so the variable is replaced with our message.

#New Way
Since we are using gulp as our task runner we are going to use [gulp-preprocess](https://github.com/mallowigi/gulp-preprocess) to preprocess our html.

We echo out the welcome message

```
&lt;h1&gt;&lt;!-- @echo WelcomeMessage --&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

```

And the gulp task

```
var gulp = require('gulp'),
    preprocess = require('gulp-preprocess');

gulp.task('html', function() {
    gulp.src('./app/*.html')
        .pipe(preprocess({
            context: {
                WelcomeMessage : 'Hello Preprocess'
            }
        })) //To set environment variables in-line
        .pipe(gulp.dest('./dist/'))
});
```

*the context contains our variable to echo out*

The resulting processed html file.

```
&lt;h1&gt;Hello Preprocess&lt;/h1&gt;
```

There we have it, we were able to remove our server rendered tag with a simple gulp task.
</body>
  <title>The road to gulpjs</title>
  <subtitle>Embracing webapp builds</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-11-23 15:23:39 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Since the inception of the web app we have been using asp.net ideas inside of our angular application.  This was a logical choice at the start since we were .net developers at heart.   During the past year we came to the realization we needed to change things and embrace modern web app tooling for our angular site.

#Old Way

 - [cassette](https://www.nuget.org/packages/Cassette/) was our bundling and uglification framework of choice.
    - We used a bundle.txt to get all of our bundles to behave correctly.
 - Javascript was in source (even though we were using TypeScript)
  - **Please do not commit compiled js into source control**
 - [cassette.msbuild](https://www.nuget.org/packages/Cassette.MSBuild/)
  - msbuild file to turn on concatenation, uglification, and caching via cassette-cache.
 - Server side tags were used to output configuration and help with rendering the bundles via cassette.

#Why
 - Using asp.net frameworks in a full angular site we ended up using only a minimal amount of asp.net in the web app and introduced an unneeded dependency. (we still needed it for the api but the web app didn't need it)
 - The build process was not as refined, web project was just a dump of assets.
 - We had random build issues with versions of msbuild.  Msbuild, cassette.msbuild, and tfs appears (to us) to be very fragile)
  - We also had msbuild tasks for C# compilation and intermixed nodejs execution of js unit tests which caused confusion on what was executing what.
 - The web app was tightly coupled to the api and it was not easily deployable just by itself.
 - It just felt wrong.

#New Way
 - [gulp](http://gulpjs.com) will be our task runner for the web app builds.
 - Many *many* gulp plugins
  - [gulp-uglify](https://github.com/terinjokes/gulp-uglify), used to uglify the js in production deployments.
  - [gulp-concat](https://github.com/contra/gulp-concat), used to create our bundles.
  - [gulp-preprocess](https://github.com/jas/gulp-preprocess), preprocess our html so we can remove server side tags.
  - [gulp-typescript](https://github.com/ivogabe/gulp-typescript), compile our typescript files to javascript for deployment.
  - [gulp-inject](https://github.com/klei/gulp-inject), getting our css and js files into our html so we can remove the cassette bundle helpers.
  - [gulp-if](https://github.com/robrich/gulp-if), help with setting up dev/staging/production builds.
  - [gulp-less](https://github.com/plus3network/gulp-less), getting our ``less`` files to ``css``

More to come....</body>
  <title>Refactor Old Code to Unit Test</title>
  <subtitle>Even old code can be unit tested</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-07-26 07:43:10 -0400</published_at>
  <body>I originally wrote this article on 4/10/10 which is now over five years ago!  I am posting it in its original form to get it online.

Begin time warp...

###How to refactor your code to aid in unit testing
One of the biggest problems that occur with legacy code is the problem of testability.  Many times developers are afraid to make the simplest changes to an existing project since they are unfamiliar with the code base and they don’t want to introduce any unforeseen problems.  In my past life we used to use win forms for our testing or even a console application (even if we ever used them we usually built and pushed out to development/staging/or even production and clicked a few buttons on the web form and crossed our fingers).  One way to help alleviate this pain is to introduce some unit tests into the system before you do any potentially breaking changes.  By doing this you setup a base line for a particular method or class.  If your changes cause one of these base line tests to fail you know you need to rework your change so the whole system functions properly.  This practice will reassure you that your changes will not have unintended effects on the system plus you will take pride in the fact you left the code base off better than it did when you started.

Our Example Our example will deal with a simple video store processor.   We have three simple poco models, Movie, Customer, and Customer Profile.

```csharp
public class Movie {
	public int Id {get;set;}
	public string Title {get;set;}
	public string Rating {get;set;}
}

public class Customer {
	public int Id {get;set;}
	public string FirstName {get;set;}
	public string LastName {get;set;}
	public string EmailAddress {get;set;}
}

public class CustomerProfile {
	public int Id {get;set;}
	public int CustomerId {get;set;}
	public bool EmailNotifacation {get;set;}
}

```

Our processor has one simple method on it named RentMovie(Customer, Movie). 

```csharp
public class VideoStoreProcessor {
	public void RentMovie(Customer customer, Movie movie) {
		Database database = DatabaseFactory.CreateDatabase();

		DbCommand outstandingRentalsCommand = database.GetStoredProcCommand("CheckForOutstandingRentals");
		database.AddInParameter(outstandingRentalsCommand, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32);

		//Check if the customer has an rental spot open.
		bool canRentMovie = Convert.ToBoolean(database.ExecuteScalar(outstandingRentalsCommand));

		if (canRentMovie) {
			//Rent the movie and mark it for shipment
			DbCommand command = database.GetStoredProcCommand("RentMovieToCustomer");
			database.AddInParameter(command, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customer.Id);
			database.AddInParameter(command, "@MovieId", DbType.Int32, movie.Id);
			database.ExecuteNonQuery(command);

			CustomerProfile customerProfile = null;
			DbCommand profileCommand = database.GetStoredProcCommand("GetCustomerProfile");
			database.AddInParameter(profileCommand, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customer.Id);
			using(IDataReader reader = database.ExecuteReader(profileCommand)) {
				if (reader.Read()) {
					customerProfile = new CustomerProfile();
					customerProfile.CustomerId = customer.Id;
					customerProfile.Id = Convert.ToInt32(reader["Id"]);
					customerProfile.EmailNotifacation = Convert.ToBoolean(reader["EmailNotification"]);
				}
			}
			if (customerProfile != null) {
				if (customerProfile.EmailNotifacation) {
					var mailMessage = new MailMessage("yourgettingamovie@markflix.com", customer.EmailAddress);
					mailMessage.Subject = "You are getting a movie!";
					mailMessage.Body = string.Format("You are going to get {0} in 1-2 days", movie.Title);

					using(var smtpClient = new SmtpClient("localhost")) {
						smtpClient.Send(mailMessage);
					}
				}
			}
		} else {
			//Add the movie to thier queue
			DbCommand command = database.GetStoredProcCommand("AddMovieToCustomersQueue");
			database.AddInParameter(command, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customer.Id);
			database.AddInParameter(command, "@MovieId", DbType.Int32, movie.Id);
			database.ExecuteNonQuery(command);
		}

		XDocument document = XDocument.Load("MovieReport.xml");
		if (document.Root != null) {
			document.Root.Add(new XElement("Movie", new XAttribute("id", movie.Id),
			new XAttribute("title", movie.Title),
			new XAttribute("rentedBy", customer.Id)));
			document.Save("MovieReport.xml");
		}
	}
}
```

From this you can see things are not very nice, the method is very long and appears to that it might need a bit of clean up at least.  First things first, let’s refactor with ReSharper to extract some methods to make our intent a bit clearer.
After our first round of refactoring

```csharp
public class VideoStoreProcessor
{
	public void RentMovie(Customer customer, Movie movie)
	{
		bool canCustomerRentAMovie = CanCustomerRentAMovie(customer.Id);
		if (canCustomerRentAMovie)
		{
			//Rent the movie and mark it for shipment
			RentMovieToCustomer(customer.Id, movie.Id);
			CustomerProfile customerProfile = GetCustomerProfile(customer.Id);
			if (customerProfile != null)
			{
				if (customerProfile.EmailNotifacation)
				{
					SendNotification(customer, movie);
				}
			}
		}
		else
		{
			//Add the movie to thier queue
			AddMovieToCustomersQueue(customer.Id, movie.Id);
		}

		AddMovieToReport(customer, movie);
	}

	private void AddMovieToReport(Customer customer, Movie movie)
	{
		XDocument document = XDocument.Load("MovieReport.xml");
		if (document.Root != null)
		{
			document.Root.Add(new XElement("Movie", new XAttribute("id", movie.Id), new XAttribute("title", movie.Title), new XAttribute("rentedBy", customer.Id)));
			document.Save("MovieReport.xml");
		}
	}

	private void AddMovieToCustomersQueue(int customerId, int movieId)
	{
		Database database = DatabaseFactory.CreateDatabase();
		DbCommand command = database.GetStoredProcCommand("AddMovieToCustomersQueue");
		database.AddInParameter(command, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customerId);
		database.AddInParameter(command, "@MovieId", DbType.Int32, movieId);
		database.ExecuteNonQuery(command);
	}

	private void SendNotification(Customer customer, Movie movie)
	{
		var mailMessage = new MailMessage("yourgettingamovie@markflix.com", customer.EmailAddress);
		mailMessage.Subject = "You are getting a movie!";
		mailMessage.Body = string.Format("You are going to get {0} in 1-2 days", movie.Title);
		using (var smtpClient = new SmtpClient("localhost"))
		{
			smtpClient.Send(mailMessage);
		}
	}

	private CustomerProfile GetCustomerProfile(int customerId)
	{
		Database database = DatabaseFactory.CreateDatabase();
		CustomerProfile customerProfile = null;
		DbCommand profileCommand = database.GetStoredProcCommand("GetCustomerProfile");
		database.AddInParameter(profileCommand, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customerId);
		using (IDataReader reader = database.ExecuteReader(profileCommand))
		{
			if (reader.Read())
			{
				customerProfile = new CustomerProfile();
				customerProfile.CustomerId = customerId;
				customerProfile.Id = Convert.ToInt32(reader["Id"]);
				customerProfile.EmailNotifacation = Convert.ToBoolean(reader["EmailNotification"]);
			}
		}

		return customerProfile;
	}

	private void RentMovieToCustomer(int customerId, int movieId)
	{
		Database database = DatabaseFactory.CreateDatabase();
		DbCommand command = database.GetStoredProcCommand("RentMovieToCustomer");
		database.AddInParameter(command, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customerId);
		database.AddInParameter(command, "@MovieId", DbType.Int32, movieId);
		database.ExecuteNonQuery(command);
	}

	private bool CanCustomerRentAMovie(int customerId)
	{
		Database database = DatabaseFactory.CreateDatabase();
		DbCommand outstandingRentalsCommand = database.GetStoredProcCommand("CheckForOutstandingRentals");
		database.AddInParameter(outstandingRentalsCommand, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customerId);
		//Check if the customer has an rental spot open.
		return Convert.ToBoolean(database.ExecuteScalar(outstandingRentalsCommand));
	}
}
```

There that looks a bit better, we reduced the noise from the main method and we can follow the flow of the RentMovie method a bit clearer.  Looking over this we see that we have some dependencies we need to worry about if we want to truly do some unit testing on this method.  From here it looks like we have a dependency on a database to execute some stored procedures, a notification service that sends emails, and some sort of report that appends information to an xml file.  All of these external dependencies are road blocks for our goal of unit testing this method.  To accomplish this we are going to extract some interfaces.

###Extracting our dependencies
####```IVideoProcessorDataAccess```
From this we appear to need to extract three interfaces for our dependencies.  For our database calls we have for calls.  ```CanCustomerRentAMovie```, ```RentMovieToCustomer```, ```GetCustomerProfile```, and ```AddMovieToCustomersQueue```.  From this lets create an interface named ```IVideoProcessorDataAccess```

```csharp
public interface IVideoProcessorDataAccess
{
	bool CanCustomerRentAMovie(int customerId);
	void RentMovieToCustomer(int customerId, int movieId);
	void AddMovieToCustomersQueue(int customerId, int movieId);
	CustomerProfile GetCustomerProfile(int customerId);
}
```

 Our next step would be to derive a type from ```IVideoProcessorDataAccess``` called ```SqlVideoStoreDataAccess```

```csharp
public class SqlVideoProcessorDataAccess : IVideoProcessorDataAccess
{
	public bool CanCustomerRentAMovie(int customerId)
	{
		throw new NotImplementedException();
	}

	public void RentMovieToCustomer(int customerId, int movieId)
	{
		throw new NotImplementedException();
	}

	public void AddMovieToCustomersQueue(int customerId, int movieId)
	{
		throw new NotImplementedException();
	}

	public CustomerProfile GetCustomerProfile(int customerId)
	{
		throw new NotImplementedException();
	}
}
```
 
 Since we named everything the same as we did in our initial refactoring lets go ahead and copy the method body implementation inside of this newly created class.

```csharp
public class SqlVideoProcessorDataAccess : IVideoProcessorDataAccess
{
	private readonly Database _database;
	public SqlVideoProcessorDataAccess()
	{
		_database = DatabaseFactory.CreateDatabase();
	}

	public bool CanCustomerRentAMovie(int customerId)
	{
		DbCommand outstandingRentalsCommand = _database.GetStoredProcCommand("CheckForOutstandingRentals");
		_database.AddInParameter(outstandingRentalsCommand, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customerId);
		//Check if the customer has an rental spot open.
		return Convert.ToBoolean(_database.ExecuteScalar(outstandingRentalsCommand));
	}

	public void RentMovieToCustomer(int customerId, int movieId)
	{
		DbCommand command = _database.GetStoredProcCommand("RentMovieToCustomer");
		_database.AddInParameter(command, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customerId);
		_database.AddInParameter(command, "@MovieId", DbType.Int32, movieId);
		_database.ExecuteNonQuery(command);
	}

	public void AddMovieToCustomersQueue(int customerId, int movieId)
	{
		DbCommand command = _database.GetStoredProcCommand("AddMovieToCustomersQueue");
		_database.AddInParameter(command, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customerId);
		_database.AddInParameter(command, "@MovieId", DbType.Int32, movieId);
		_database.ExecuteNonQuery(command);
	}

	public CustomerProfile GetCustomerProfile(int customerId)
	{
		CustomerProfile customerProfile = null;
		DbCommand profileCommand = _database.GetStoredProcCommand("GetCustomerProfile");
		_database.AddInParameter(profileCommand, "@CustomerId", DbType.Int32, customerId);
		using (IDataReader reader = _database.ExecuteReader(profileCommand))
		{
			if (reader.Read())
			{
				customerProfile = new CustomerProfile
				{
				CustomerId = customerId, Id = Convert.ToInt32(reader["Id"]), EmailNotifacation = Convert.ToBoolean(reader["EmailNotification"])}

				;
			}
		}

		return customerProfile;
	}
}
```

####```IVideoStoreNotifications```
Our next dependency is our email notification system we have for our video store processor.  We will go through our next step and create an interface for our video store notifications.

```csharp
public interface IVideoStoreNotifications
{
	void SendNotification(Customer customer, Movie movie);
}
```

And next derive a type that handles our notifications.
This will end up looking like the following:
SmtpVideoStoreNotifications

```csharp
public class SmtpVideoStoreNotifications : IVideoStoreNotifications
{
	public void SendNotification(Customer customer, Movie movie)
	{
		var mailMessage = new MailMessage("yourgettingamovie@markflix.com", customer.EmailAddress)
		{
		Subject = "You are getting a movie!", Body = string.Format("You are going to get {0} in 1-2 days", movie.Title)}

		;
		using (var smtpClient = new SmtpClient("localhost"))
		{
			smtpClient.Send(mailMessage);
		}
	}
}
```

####```IVideoStoreReporter```
Our last interface will be called ```IVideoStoreReporter``` which will handle our reporting in our method ```RentMovie```.

```csharp
public interface IVideoStoreReporter
{
	void AddMovieToReport(Customer customer, Movie movie);
}
```

And the derived type
####```XmlVideoStoreReporter```

```csharp
public class XmlVideoStoreReporter : IVideoStoreReporter
{
	public void AddMovieToReport(Customer customer, Movie movie)
	{
		XDocument document = XDocument.Load("MovieReport.xml");
		if (document.Root != null)
		{
			document.Root.Add(new XElement("Movie", new XAttribute("id", movie.Id), new XAttribute("title", movie.Title), new XAttribute("rentedBy", customer.Id)));
			document.Save("MovieReport.xml");
		}
	}
}
```

###Constructor injection
Great now you are saying we have all of these classes and interfaces now what are we supposed to do?  Our next step is to refactor our VideoStoreProcessor more by adding two constructors.  One that takes no parameters and one that takes our three dependencies we extracted above.

```csharp
public VideoStoreProcessor()
{
}

public VideoStoreProcessor(IVideoProcessorDataAccess dataAccess, IVideoStoreNotifications storeNotifications, IVideoStoreReporter reporter)
{
	_dataAccess = dataAccess;
	_storeNotifications = storeNotifications;
	_reporter = reporter;
}
```

This is starting to shape up nicely.  But we are missing one important piece of the puzzle, if we use the parameter-less constructor we need to specify types for our interfaces.  Change your parameter-less constructor to call our concrete types.

```csharp
public VideoStoreProcessor() :  this  ( new  SqlVideoProcessorDataAccess ( ) ,  new  SmtpVideoStoreNotifications ( ) ,  new  XmlVideoStoreReporter ( ) ){
}

public VideoStoreProcessor(IVideoProcessorDataAccess dataAccess, IVideoStoreNotifications storeNotifications, IVideoStoreReporter reporter)
{
	_dataAccess = dataAccess;
	_storeNotifications = storeNotifications;
	_reporter = reporter;
}
```

Perfect!
Now let’s finish up and refactor our RentMovie method to use these newly injected dependencies.

```csharp
public void RentMovie(Customer customer, Movie movie)
{
	bool canCustomerRentAMovie = _dataAccess.CanCustomerRentAMovie(customer.Id);
	if (canCustomerRentAMovie)
	{
		//Rent the movie and mark it for shipment
		_dataAccess.RentMovieToCustomer(customer.Id, movie.Id);
		CustomerProfile customerProfile = _dataAccess.GetCustomerProfile(customer.Id);
		if (customerProfile != null)
		{
			if (customerProfile.EmailNotifacation)
			{
				_storeNotifications.SendNotification(customer, movie);
			}
		}
	}
	else
	{
		//Add the movie to thier queue
		_dataAccess.AddMovieToCustomersQueue(customer.Id, movie.Id);
	}

	_reporter.AddMovieToReport(customer, movie);
}
```

Awesome!  All of our dependencies have been extracted. 

###What this means for unit testing.
With these extracted dependencies this means we can create fakes and mocks for our data access layer, notifications, and reporter interfaces.
For example let’s say we create a test method that verifies that the method AddMovieToReport method is called in our RentMovie method on our VideoStoreProcessor.

```csharp
[TestMethod]
public void RentMovie_Information_WritesToReporter()
{
	//Arrange
	var reporterMock = new Mock&lt;IVideoStoreReporter&gt;();
	reporterMock.Setup(r =&gt; r.AddMovieToReport(It.IsAny&lt;Customer&gt;(), It.IsAny&lt;Movie&gt;())).AtMostOnce();
	var processor = new VideoStoreProcessor(new FakeDataAccess(), new FakeNotifications(), reporterMock.Object);
	//Act
	processor.RentMovie(new Customer(), new Movie());
	//Assert
	reporterMock.VerifyAll();
}
```

In our arrangement in our unit test we can see we are creating a FakeDataAccess, FakeNotifications and a Mock of IVideoStoreReporter.  (This is using Moq which is outside the scope of this post).  Our first question might be what are these fake classes?
These are simply derived classes from our interface that do not do anything at all and are called Fakes.

```csharp
public class FakeNotifications : IVideoStoreNotifications
{
	public void SendNotification(Customer customer, Movie movie)
	{
	}
}

public class FakeDataAccess : IVideoProcessorDataAccess
{
	public bool CanCustomerRentAMovie(int customerId)
	{
		return true;
	}

	public void RentMovieToCustomer(int customerId, int movieId)
	{
	}

	public void AddMovieToCustomersQueue(int customerId, int movieId)
	{
	}

	public CustomerProfile GetCustomerProfile(int customerId)
	{
		return new CustomerProfile();
	}
}
```

These don’t do anything because our concern of our test does not care about the dataaccess layer or the notification layer; we just want to verify the AddMovieToReport method was called.  If you run this test everything passes and the use of the Mocking framework allowed us to verify that the method was called.
Now let’s say down the line we accidentally remove the call to AddMovieToReport.  Since we have this unit test in place as soon as we run our tests again we will get immediate notification that something is broken.

I hope this post has been informative and can assist you in extracting some dependencies in some existing code so unit testing can be part of each developer’s lives.</body>
  <title>Kid's Day 2015</title>
  <subtitle>BYKTWD - Bring your kid to work day</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-05-03 19:48:57 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Every year [Members 1st FCU](https://www.members1st.org) invites associates to bring their kid to work to learn about Members 1st FCU and participate in activities organized by associates.  Each associates that volunteers helps put together a little activity for the children highlighting a business unit.

 - Tele-branch
 - Security
 - Learn about being a Teller 
 - Data Center Tour
 - Computer lab activity (*That's Me*)

Over the past few years I did not participate for one reason or another (even though I should have looking back), but this year was the year.  While judging a [middle school computer fair](http://www.caiu.org/services/technology/computer-fair.aspx) there was an excellent presentation about the [Makey Makey](http://makeymakey.com) [(video)](https://vimeo.com/60307041) by an employee at [Ritter Insurance](https://www.ritterim.com) showing how you could make controllers with alligator clips and a computer.

The day after seeing that awesome presentation I brought the idea to the IT kids day group and thought it would be a good fit for the IT based activity.  The group began pondering and googling of potential activities.  We came up with four stations where the kids would assemble a makey makey and play with their creation.

##Mario Doh!
The first station was ran by [Jessica Hutchinson](https://www.linkedin.com/pub/jessica-hutchinson/27/a41/756) where the kids would create and assemble a video game controller using either Play Doh ® or drawing a controller using a thick pencil.
![Mario Doh!](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/6768dcbb-30dc-4492-aaf5-602aa717bd47/IMG_2865_large.jpg)
The kids really enjoyed this station (was voted most popular) since it allowed them to build and play a video game!
![Doh Controller](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/730d975e-6bf2-4b64-8f58-60e02e446d47/IMG_0670_large.jpg)
[game](https://scratch.mit.edu/projects/1758457/)

##Bongo
The next station was ran by [Evania Mans](https://www.linkedin.com/pub/evania-mans/41/a21/3b7).  This station involved taking the Makey Makey and creating a pair of bongo drums by jamming the alligator clips into the fruit.
![Bongo](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/48a6b468-40ed-47c2-b723-a44343272fdf/IMG_2864_large.jpg)
(*This action shot was staged, pretend it has the bongos on the screen and the clips are actually hooked up*)
![Cantaloupe Bongo](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/2f5df240-fbe8-4cc6-9914-3b999b7aea71/IMG_0664_large.jpg)
[game](http://makeymakey.com/bongos/)

##Banana Piano
The banana piano station was ran by [Mark Coleman - (Me)](http://www.kramnameloc.com).  This station allowed the kids to assemble a piano and use the bananas as keys on the keyboard.  Looking back at the station it was a bit of a challenge for the kids to open the clips to attach to the banana. It was actually easier to just jab them into the banana instead.
![Banana Panana](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/dcab077e-7231-4587-9989-eeeed7eab4a2/IMG_2863_large.jpg)
The fully functional banana piano is pictured below.  I could not be out done by the Mario Station which meant I loaded up Pac Man, however playing pac man with bananas is surprisingly difficult.
![Banana Piano](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/eb9c2079-9d04-4556-ac27-6b32d9bdea8a/IMG_2859_large.jpg)
[piano](https://scratch.mit.edu/projects/2543877/)
[pac man](https://scratch.mit.edu/projects/14608394/)

##Flower Power
The last station was ran by [Rene Payo](https://www.linkedin.com/pub/renee-payo/97/655/46a) which had the kids build a piano style controller but it used flowers to activate the piano.
![Flower Power](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/8fadb68c-ecd0-4363-adf1-98d75a3d6b17/IMG_2866_large.jpg)
We didn't have real flowers to use so we had to do a bit of improvisation to get things working correctly
![Flowers](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/fb673322-77d4-4c51-a68b-587f237aa62a/Untitled_large.png)
[Piano](http://makeymakey.com/piano/)

Kids day this year went amazingly and I wish I had enough ambition and motivation as the other volunteers to do it in years past, they truly are winners as I just tagged along this year to experience the joy in helping kids learn.
</body>
  <title>Programming Resources</title>
  <subtitle>Brain dump</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-04-25 11:46:22 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Two weeks ago an associate requested to shadow myself and the development team to learn more about what we do as they are interested in development.  I unfortunately only had two hours with them to dump tons of information into their brain which most likely resulted in overload.  To help combat this I provided a list of random topics to help them learn and learn about in the future.  I present you my list of random things that is no where complete but a starting point to learn about development.

##General
 - [Stackoverflow](http://www.stackoverflow.com): The best QA site on development topics [(my profile)](http://stackoverflow.com/users/181776/mark-coleman)
 - [Codecademy](http://www.codecademy.com): Learn to code in your browser
 - [Pluralsight](http://www.pluralsight.com): Online training for all things development and IT, free 90 day trial for students
 - Learn [git](https://try.github.io/levels/1/challenges/1): When I went to college they never taught source control, it would have been so helpful early on.

##HTML Stuff
 - [JsFiddle](http://jsfiddle.net): Zero friction html/js/css site when sometimes you want to try something without launching an IDE or a web server. [my profile](http://jsfiddle.net/user/markcoleman/fiddles/)
 - [Plnkr ](http://plnkr.co): Zero friction html/js/css site, also very popular a bit more robust.
 - [Firebug](http://getfirebug.com): My defacto web debugger
 - [Bower](http://bower.io): Web package management, why hunt for packages when you can install than via command line.

##.NET
 - [C# virtual academy](http://www.microsoftvirtualacademy.com/training-courses/c-fundamentals-for-absolute-beginners): Learn C# from Microsoft
 - [dotnetfiddle.net](https://dotnetfiddle.net): Zero friction C# development in your browser. 
 - [nuget.org](http://www.nuget.org): Package management for .net projects.

##JavsScript
 - [Jquery](https://www.jquery.com): If you do web development it is great to learn as there are a plethora of plugins.
 - [AngularJs](https://angularjs.org): One of the many web frameworks, currently my favorite.
 - [NodeJs](https://nodejs.org): Love JavaScript? how about javascript outside of the browser.

##IDE/Tools
 - [Visual Studio Community Edition](https://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/products/visual-studio-community-vs.aspx): Now free so no reason not to use it especially if you do C#
 - [ReSharper](https://www.jetbrains.com/resharper/): Alt-Enter all the things! Helps in refactoring, code style, templates, reveals potential bugs, and so much more.
 - [WebStorm](https://www.jetbrains.com/webstorm/): My favoriate html/JavaScript IDE
 - [Sublimetext](http://www.sublimetext.com): Don't use it but still very popular.

##Books
 - [C# in depth](http://www.manning.com/skeet3/): Learn C# from the [master](http://stackoverflow.com/users/22656/jon-skeet)
 - [Clean Code](http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0132350882/ref=pd_lpo_sbs_dp_ss_1?pf_rd_p=1944687742&amp;pf_rd_s=lpo-top-stripe-1&amp;pf_rd_t=201&amp;pf_rd_i=0137081073&amp;pf_rd_m=ATVPDKIKX0DER&amp;pf_rd_r=1ZB0FFBKY429VSX933G0): Learn about good and bad code
 - [Code Complete](http://www.amazon.com/Code-Complete-Practical-Handbook-Construction/dp/0735619670/ref=pd_sim_b_2?ie=UTF8&amp;refRID=1TJE4WY815WTNFZ0RG0R): The definitive guide to what it means to produce clean high quality code.</body>
  <title>Gated Checkins</title>
  <subtitle>When sometimes you are not sure...</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-04-21 11:17:47 -0400</published_at>
  <body>This might be old news for some but figured I would share.

One feature of TFS is it allows you to perform a [gated checkin](https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd787631.aspx) where the checkin will only occur if the build/tests are successful.  I used this in the past a few times when I was making some changes that were conjecture if it would fix the problem on the build server.  (binding redirects, path issues, and failures that only seem to occur on the build server)


#Create a shelve of your changes
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/d6b60418-e883-45c6-b6e8-66997e3505f2/01%20-%20shelve_large.png)

#Queue Build
 - Go to the build tab in team explorer and right click on “Development” then click on “Queue New Build…”
 - Under the general tab, adjust the “What do you want to build?” to be “Latest sources with shelveset”
 - Pick the shelveset name
 - Tick the “Check in changes after successful build”
 - Click “Queue"

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a1b29f38-d910-4755-be12-4b23f8ed0ab0/02%20-%20queue_large.png)

This will cause a build to start on the build server with the latest sources in source control and your shelve set changes.  If all goes well the shelveset will be checked in at the end of the build.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/83fa7bc3-83cf-49b3-bd52-b2ed3a5f6b4a/03%20-%20history_large.png)


*note: Your changes will remain checked out locally, but if you get latest your checked out changes will match what is in source control and will now be synchronized*
</body>
  <title>Alter scope via Console</title>
  <subtitle>angular.element() is your friend</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-04-11 09:35:39 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Yesterday I was tasked with changing some verbiage inside of an AngularJs application that is only displayed under a certain condition via ngIf.  How can I validate the changes to the application without mucking up the boolean logic to display the div?

Given the following
```
  &lt;div ng-if="isNewUser"&gt;
    Welcome new user to the site.
  &lt;/div&gt;
```
```
  $scope.isNewUser = false; //some complex logic
```

I want to view the welcome message without touching the ```isNewUser``` condition.  Granted I could register a new user to cause this logic to evaluate to true but I am lazy.

You can interact with your angular application via the console using ```angular.element()```

```
var elm = document.getElementById("main");
angular.element(elm);
```

This allows you to access the scope

```
console.log(angular.element(elm).scope().isNewUser);
&gt;&gt; false
```

From there you can simply set the scope property to true and force a digest cycle with apply

```
angular.element(elm).scope().isNewUser = true;
angular.element(elm).scope().$apply();
```

Inside of your application you should see the ```ngIf``` evaluate and the welcome message will be shown.

Simple but effective.

You can try it out for yourself on [jsfiddle](https://jsfiddle.net/markcoleman/tmwa0xtk/embedded/result/).

*to access the frame in chrome change the console target to fiddle.jshell.net*</body>
  <title>TinyPng to the Rescue</title>
  <subtitle>Performance gains don't always mean refactoring</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-04-01 10:18:37 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Over here at [Members 1st FCU](https://myonline.members1st.org) we have been focusing on improving overall performance of our application so we reply to user requests faster.  Over the past few weeks we have been refactoring, hacking, and slashing our code base and saw some great gains.  Today I remembered that performance doesn't always mean refactoring code it can also mean optimization of requests and particularly that means image size.

The easiest solution to optimize your sites image payload is run the files through [TinyPng](http://www.tinypng.com)

![Tinypng](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/00c4e7ca-9d6c-41ac-952a-b6b0f1179330/tinypng_large.png)

We processed all of our images and ended up saving about 200k which is a great savings in bandwidth and users data costs.</body>
  <title>News to me, New Relic Categories &amp; Labels</title>
  <subtitle>Group all the things!</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-03-30 12:24:00 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Today I learned something new about [New Relic](http://www.newrelic.com) today that helps  with separating applications in APM.  

 - First click on *show labels*

![Show Labels](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/b6f7f5dd-068e-42e9-8e69-08fa9b971321/show_large.png)

 - Under your application you will see a ⊕ icon that will allow you to add an existing Category/Label or create a new one in the format of **Category:Label**

![Add Category:Label](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/6a4ac486-57fd-4f08-b7fb-65ab360be8b2/add%20_large.png)

 - After you set a few labels you can now use them in the search box above all of your applications.

![New Search Options](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/20d27024-8bc4-495f-af71-14a7e608792f/search_large.png)

 - If you click on one of the items in the search drop down you now can roll up to an environment or all applications tagged with a particular label.  

![Roll Up](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/727a272a-84c8-42a2-8f27-6435b760b271/roll%20up_large.png)

Now we have nice organized applications in the APM.</body>
  <title>Protractor Finding an Element</title>
  <subtitle>Using by.css()</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-02-15 16:33:00 -0500</published_at>
  <body>In the first post we showed how we can easily get [setup with protractor and an angularjs application](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/getting-started-with-protractor).  Next up we want to continue our journey and use protractor to find an element on a page and assert that the text is a given value.  To get this started we need to tweak our original application slightly.

#Example App
First thing we needed to do is actually create an application as prior we only had tests.  Our application is very simple (for now).  It has the following:

 - app.js which contains the ```protractor``` module and one controller ```MainCtrl```
 - index.html that is a basic setup of a page using [bootstrap](http://getbootstrap.com) and some lovely [SAMUEL L. IPSUM](http://slipsum.com)

#Finding an Element
Now that we have our example app setup let's go ahead and try to find the ```&lt;h1&gt;``` under the jumbotron.  To do this we need to us the [```by.css()```](http://angular.github.io/protractor/#/api?view=webdriver.By.css) method in conjunction with ```element()```  Once we get the element we can use a normal ```expect()``` clause to validate the header contains the appropriate text.

```
describe('go go protractor homepage', function() {
    it('should have a jumbotron header', function(){
        browser.get('http://localhost:8080');
        expect(element(by.css('.jumbotron h1')).getText()).toBe("Go Go Protractor");
    });
});
```

The ```by.css()``` method is powerful in the fact you can pass in css selectors to locate an element, with this being said it is not jQuery and you need to use valid css selectors to locate the element. e.g. you can't use the jQuery ```:visible``` extension.

#Test Refactor
If you look at our two tests they both start with ```browser.get()```.  We can refactor this method out to the ```beforeEach()``` call inside of our describe to reduce in duplication.

```
describe('go go protractor homepage', function() {
    beforeEach(function(){
        browser.get('http://localhost:8080');
    });
    it('should have a title', function() {
        expect(browser.getTitle()).toEqual('Go Go Protractor');
    });
    it('should have a jumbotron header', function(){
        expect(element(by.css('.jumbotron h1')).getText()).toBe("Go Go Protractor");
    });
});
```

There that feels better! Always be refactoring!

#Conclusion
Finding elements by css is simple to use inside of your end to end tests to validate your page contains certain values.  Next up we will expand on this with a few other common selectors you might use in your tests.

[Code on github](https://github.com/markcoleman/ProtractorExamples/tree/07ea347a9d0cc758ed780fb27ea9d36ffb73df8f)</body>
  <title>Getting started with Protractor</title>
  <subtitle>End to end tests for AngularJs</subtitle>
  <published_at>2015-02-06 14:13:19 -0500</published_at>
  <body>The web development team at Members1st FCU has been using angularjs for the past two years.  It has been a learning experience developing a fairly large scale JavaScript based application.  One thing we have been procrastinating on is writing of end to end test (or system tests) that test interactions with the UI all the way down to the core data processor.  This concept was new to me and the team so after a few headaches we got it down to a few simple steps to get setup.

#Installing
The first thing you need is node

Windows [Chocolatey](https://chocolatey.org) ```choco install node``` or OSX [Home Brew](http://brew.sh) ```brew install node```

*if you are using windows you also need [java](http://java.com/en/download/)

Next run ```npm init``` which will guide you through the process of creating a ```package.json``` file that describes the package and related dependencies.

To install protractor run ```npm install protractor --save-dev```.  The save dev flag adds this to your dev dependencies for the project.  (You can also install this globally if you like as well)

Example ```package.json``` file

```
{
  "name": "ProtractorDemo",
  "version": "0.0.0",
  "description": "protractor demo",
  "main": "index.js",
  "scripts": {
    "test": "echo \"Error: no test specified\" &amp;&amp; exit 1"
  },
  "author": "Mark Coleman",
  "license": "ISC",
  "devDependencies": {
    "protractor": "~1.6.1"
  }
}
```

#Getting Setup
Once you have node, (java if windows,) and protractor we need to configure it.

Run ```node_modules/protractor/bin webdriver-manager update``` command that will download and configure the chrome web driver.

Sample script in ```package.json``` to automate this step, ```npm run setup```

```
"scripts": {
    "setup":"npm install &amp;&amp; node node_modules/protractor/bin/webdriver-manager update",
    "test": "echo \"Error: no test specified\" &amp;&amp; exit 1"
},
```

Once you have everything setup you need to start the [selenium server](http://www.seleniumhq.org/) ```node node_modules/protractor/bin webdriver-start```

You can also add in a script inside of ```package.json``` to simplify this process ```"start" : "node node_modules/protractor/bin/webdriver-manager start",``` then you can run ```npm run start```

At this point protractor is setup and configured now we can start creating a test.

#Create conf file
We need to create a ```conf.js``` file which stores the configuration for protractor.  The selenium address is the default configuration so shouldn't need adjusted.  I also separated the tests into suites for future test suite separation.

```
exports.config = {
    seleniumAddress: 'http://localhost:4444/wd/hub',
    suites: {
        homepage: 'homepageSpec.js'
    }
}
```

#Writing a Test
Protractor tests are written similar to jasmine tests but with the introduction with ```browser``` that allows you to navigate to a page and get the page title.

```
describe('angularjs homepage', function() {
    it('should have a title', function() {
        browser.get('http://www.angularjs.org');
        expect(browser.getTitle()).toEqual('AngularJS — Superheroic JavaScript MVW Framework');
    });
});
```

Once your test is created you can run the test by running the command ```node node_modules/protractor/bin/protractor conf.js``` (make sure the selenium server is still running)

You can also create a script inside of the ```package.json```

```
"test": "node node_modules/protractor/bin/protractor conf.js"
```  

Running the test using npm ```npm run test```

#Conclusion
After following these steps you should be able to have a very basic protractor test setup which verifies the title of a page.  In the next iteration we will expand on this basic example.

[Code on github](https://github.com/markcoleman/ProtractorExamples)
</body>
  <title>Sharing Configuration</title>
  <subtitle>Building up a Unity Container with multiple config files</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-12-02 11:54:32 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Inside of our Online Banking application we utilize Unity as our container of choice for inversion of control.  We also got into the practice of placing some of our configuration for our services into the ```app/web.config``` of our applications.  This worked out for quite a few months having this configuration duplicated into these separate ```*.config``` files however we recently missed one file during a deployment.  Being good developers we can't let this happen again and realized we needed to somehow share a global configuration to reduce duplication.

During our research we ran across ```configSource``` which seemed promising however it extracted the whole container via ```&lt;unity configSource="bin\global.config"/&gt;``` and resulted in further complication.  Next up was to try ```OpenMappedExeConfiguration``` which allowed us to load configuration from multiple files into our one container.


###Example

We have three separate *.config files.  Where the ```app.config``` is the configuration for our application but we also want to share configuration from two other files.

UnitySectionA.config

```
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?&gt;
&lt;configuration&gt;
  &lt;configSections&gt;
    &lt;section name="unity" type="Microsoft.Practices.Unity.Configuration.UnityConfigurationSection, Microsoft.Practices.Unity.Configuration"/&gt;
  &lt;/configSections&gt;
  &lt;unity xmlns="http://schemas.microsoft.com/practices/2010/unity"&gt;
    &lt;namespace name="ConsoleApplication" /&gt;
    &lt;assembly name="ConsoleApplication" /&gt;
    &lt;container&gt;
      &lt;register type="IConfigA" mapTo="ConfigA" /&gt;
    &lt;/container&gt;
  &lt;/unity&gt;
&lt;/configuration&gt;
```
UnitySectionB.config

```
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?&gt;
&lt;configuration&gt;
  &lt;configSections&gt;
    &lt;section name="unity" type="Microsoft.Practices.Unity.Configuration.UnityConfigurationSection, Microsoft.Practices.Unity.Configuration"/&gt;
  &lt;/configSections&gt;
  &lt;unity xmlns="http://schemas.microsoft.com/practices/2010/unity"&gt;
    &lt;namespace name="ConsoleApplication" /&gt;
    &lt;assembly name="ConsoleApplication" /&gt;
    &lt;container&gt;
      &lt;register type="IConfigB" mapTo="ConfigB" /&gt;
    &lt;/container&gt;
  &lt;/unity&gt;
&lt;/configuration&gt;
```

*note the two unity config files are linked to the project and set to copy to output which will place them in the ```bin``` folder.*

App.config

```
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?&gt;
&lt;configuration&gt;
  &lt;configSections&gt;
    &lt;section name="unity" type="Microsoft.Practices.Unity.Configuration.UnityConfigurationSection, Microsoft.Practices.Unity.Configuration"/&gt;
  &lt;/configSections&gt;
  &lt;unity xmlns="http://schemas.microsoft.com/practices/2010/unity"&gt;
    &lt;namespace name="ConsoleApplication" /&gt;
    &lt;assembly name="ConsoleApplication" /&gt;
    &lt;container&gt;
      &lt;register type="IConfigC" mapTo="ConfigC" /&gt;
    &lt;/container&gt;
  &lt;/unity&gt;
  &lt;startup&gt;
    &lt;supportedRuntime version="v4.0" sku=".NETFramework,Version=v4.5" /&gt;
  &lt;/startup&gt;
&lt;/configuration&gt;
```

Then in our program we open up each separate config file and grab the config section and call the ```LoadConfiguration()``` extension method.

Grabbing SectionA

```
var unityAFileMap = new ExeConfigurationFileMap { ExeConfigFilename = unityAPath };
Configuration unityAConfiguration = ConfigurationManager.OpenMappedExeConfiguration(unityAFileMap, ConfigurationUserLevel.None);
var unityASection = (UnityConfigurationSection)unityAConfiguration.GetSection("unity");

container.LoadConfiguration(unityASection);
var configA = container.Resolve&lt;IConfigA&gt;();
Console.WriteLine(configA.Name);
```

Grabbing SectionB

```
var unityBPath = Path.Combine(AssemblyDirectory, "UnitySectionB.config");
var unityBFileMap = new ExeConfigurationFileMap { ExeConfigFilename = unityBPath };
Configuration unityBConfiguration = ConfigurationManager.OpenMappedExeConfiguration(unityBFileMap, ConfigurationUserLevel.None);
var unityBSection = (UnityConfigurationSection)unityBConfiguration.GetSection("unity");

container.LoadConfiguration(unityBSection);
var configB = container.Resolve&lt;IConfigB&gt;();
Console.WriteLine(configB.Name);
```

Load app.config

```
container.LoadConfiguration();
var configC = container.Resolve&lt;IConfigC&gt;();
Console.WriteLine(configC.Name);
```

Resolve a service from the container registered in code:

```
container.RegisterType&lt;IServiceService, ServiceService&gt;();

var service = container.Resolve&lt;IServiceService&gt;();
Console.WriteLine(service.GetName());
```

###Conclusion
With this approach we now are able to share configuration between multiple projects be it web based, console, or even windows services.  This reduces the need duplication of our configuration and helps make the application a bit more manageable.  I feel we are going to expand this idea further to help clean up our application configuration.


Example code on [github]
(https://github.com/markcoleman/ExternalUnityConfiguration/tree/master)</body>
  <title>Installing Windows 10 (In Pictures)</title>
  <subtitle>Running Windows 10 in a Parallels</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-10-08 19:22:02 -0400</published_at>
  <body>I always love to install new operating systems and always update my software to the latest and greatest version.  I do do this a bit cavalier at times but have been lucky (so far).  Since I am a strict mac user doing this was super easy as I was able to spin up a new VM in parallels without any trouble at all.

Since I love guides and pictures here is the install in Pictures!

**Download the ISO**
I signed up for the [Windows Insider](http://windows.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/preview) program and downloaded the ISO.

**Read the knowledge base article**
Parallels has a handy [article](http://kb.parallels.com/en/122745) on how to install Windows 10 inside of parallels for mac.  Once downloaded and extracted choose copied
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/db00fa6b-5e24-49d8-9ada-fc25a314b644/01-Moved-Copied_large.png)

**Connect the ISO**
Configure your VM and connect the downloaded ISO to your VM.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c91d271d-1281-4fb2-a88e-f2e949813810/02-config_large.png)

**First Boot**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a1752da5-c2ea-4288-a172-ce5411293732/03-first%20boot_large.png)

**Windows 10 Startup**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/20d1a664-96ec-4c81-bd3d-ad8b2809b907/04-startup_large.png)

**Confirm the terms**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/1425f4d4-473d-4e96-b4c5-981bde963850/05-confirm_large.png)

**Select the drive**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/1977bd8c-1dc5-4feb-be6b-86755a3b7040/06-drive_large.png)

**Installing...**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/60ddbb2d-b426-41bb-921d-68537ad348d0/07-install_large.png)

**Express Setup**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/436def6e-ea7b-4968-b81c-c4603be2257f/08-express%20setup_large.png)

**First time seeing the desktop**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/03871778-5430-4406-bbdb-9d22cead80ac/09-desktop_large.png)

**The Start Menu is back**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/9e0a98dc-f334-46ac-b4c8-d8c0d9056c1d/10-new%20start%20menu_large.png)

**Install Tools**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/755186b7-f6b6-4ba3-9e3b-2a4109b3d1ba/11-install%20tools_large.png)

**Allow Prompt**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/e9ec7c46-0475-4594-bfce-e971294c3b2f/12-connect_large.png)

**Run Windows Update**
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/e86fe25b-230d-40cf-ab97-12aa427b9971/13-run%20update_large.png)

We now have Windows 10 installed in a Parallels VM, have fun!</body>
  <title>Programmers Day 2014</title>
  <subtitle>A technology themed scavenger hunt!</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-09-17 20:02:53 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Earlier this year I learned of [Programmers Day](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Programmers'_Day) and I figured this would be the perfect opportunity to get the development team together and have some fun and dare I even mention it.... *"Team Building"* (gasps!)  The first thing we needed to figure out is what on earth could we do that would be fun that incorporates some sort of programming fun?  A few ideas were thrown around but we ended up with a programmer themed scavenger hunt.  Each location would contain a clue to the next location encoded in some sort of programming task or a simple question.  


###How to Play

* The development team is broken out into 3-4 person teams
* Each team leaves on a schedule (around 5-10 minutes) this was done to keep each location open and limit teams following each other around
* At each location the team must find the corresponding programmer token that is hidden at the location
* The team decodes the puzzle and goes to the next location
* The team follows the clues and the team with all the tokens and the fastest time wins

###The Hunt

* Teams Starts in Room 116 and is presented the following clue *"This is where we go to get me a pick me up."*

* Team rushes to the break Room by the coffee machine and finds the [Java] token and finds a clue encoded in binary
```01001101 01111001 00100000 01101100 01101001 01100111 01101000 01110100 00100000 01100101 01101101 01101001 01110100 01110100 01101001 01101110 01100111 00100000 01100100 01101001 01101111 01100100 01100101 01110011 00100000 01101000 01100101 01101100 01110000 00100000 01111001 01101111 01110101 00100000 01101011 01101110 01101111 01110111 00100000 01110100 01101000 01100101 00100000 01110100 01101001 01101101 01100101 00100000 01100001 01101110 01100100 00100000 01110100 01100101 01101101 01110000 01100101 01110010 01100001 01110100 01110101 01110010 01100101 ```
[Hint](http://jsfiddle.net/markcoleman/mmeqjf43/embedded/result/)
*[decoded]“My light emitting diodes help you know the time and temperature”*

* The team goes to the sign in the front of the building and finds the [binary] token along with another clue in JavaScript.
```console.log(rot13("haqre n cvpavp gnoyr”));```
[Hint](http://jsfiddle.net/markcoleman/j1rc8h8g/1/)
*[decoded]“Under a picnic table”*

* The team now goes to the picnic tables and finds the [JavaScript] token.
*I once was a whole number OS but now have added 1/10 to my name.  Find where I am installed for the next clue, ITS/Dev Area*

* The team goes to the ITS Dev Area and finds the  [Microsoft] token along with a sql statement for the next clue.
```SELECT CHAR(82) + CHAR(79) + 
                        CHAR(79) + CHAR(77) + 
                        CHAR(32) + CHAR(49) +
                        CHAR(50) + CHAR(49) AS [Next Location]```
*[decoded]"Room 121"*

* The team goes to room 121 and finds the [Sql] token and an `&lt;html/&gt;` snip it.
```
&lt;h1&gt;&amp;reg;&amp;Egrave;&amp;Tcaron;&amp;Uacute;&amp;reg;&amp;Ntilde;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&amp;Tcaron;&amp;Oacute;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&amp;Tcaron;&amp;Hcirc;&amp;Egrave;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;&amp;Sacute;&amp;Tcaron;&amp;Agrave;&amp;reg;&amp;Tcaron;&lt;/h1&gt;
```
[Hint](http://jsfiddle.net/markcoleman/mwe23xqx/embedded/result/)
*[decoded] Return to the start*

* The team returns to room 116 and finds the [Html] token.

###Conclusion
All in all this event turned out to be a lot of fun for everyone.  We hope to make this a yearly tradition!
</body>
  <title>Octopack with Cassette</title>
  <subtitle>Getting your bundles packaged via Octopack</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-05-13 22:21:38 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Recently at work we started doing some research on [Octopus Deploy](http://octopusdeploy.com)  to automate our deployment procedures so the process is defined and easily repeatable.  One of our applications required a bit of a tweak since we utilize the asset bundling library Cassette and the msbuild target.

##Sample Asp.net application
To get started I simply crated a default asp.net web application and added in a few js and css files to simulate assets required for our web application.

##OctoPack
The first package we need to install is octopack which is a package used in octopus deploy that helps create nuget packages for our deployment process.
```Install-Package OctoPack```

##Cassette
Since we are using cassette to bundle our application the next package we need to install is of course cassette.
```Install-Package Cassette.Aspnet```

##Cassette MSBuild
In our example we are also going to use the msbuild package to cache our bundled assets in the ```cassette-cache``` folder of our web application.
```Install-Package Cassette.MSBuild```

##Setup bundles
Now that we have our nuget packages installed we need to setup our bundles for cassette.  The first thing we need to do is create our bundle configuration.

```
using Cassette;
using Cassette.Scripts;
using Cassette.Stylesheets;

namespace Octopack.Cassette
{
    public class CassetteBundleConfiguration : IConfiguration&lt;BundleCollection&gt;
    {
        public void Configure(BundleCollection bundles)
        {
            bundles.Add&lt;StylesheetBundle&gt;("css");
            bundles.Add&lt;ScriptBundle&gt;("js");
            bundles.Add&lt;ScriptBundle&gt;("lib");
        }
    }
}
```

After the bundle configuration is taken care of we need to write those bundles to the page 

```
&lt;%
    Bundles.Reference("css");
    Bundles.Reference("lib"); 
    Bundles.Reference("js");
%&gt;
```

and in the body

```
&lt;%:Bundles.RenderScripts() %&gt;
```

##Run OctoPack, get the nuspec
Now that we have everything setup it is time to get our nuget package setup via octopack.  I found the easiest way to get started is to run octopack which will automatically generate a ```nuspec``` file.

```msbuild .\Octopack.Cassette.sln /t:Build /p:RunOctoPack=true```

When the command finishes you can find the ```nuspec``` file under the following path:

```
..\Octopack.Cassette\obj\octopacking\Octopack.Cassette.nuspec
```

##Modify the nuspec

I moved the ```nuspec``` file from that path to the root of the application and adjusted the ```&lt;files/&gt;``` element to include the ```cassette-cache``` folder that is generated by the cassette msbuild target.

```
&lt;package&gt;
  &lt;metadata&gt;
    &lt;id&gt;Octopack.Cassette&lt;/id&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;0.0.0.0&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;authors&gt;markcoleman&lt;/authors&gt;
    &lt;owners&gt;markcoleman&lt;/owners&gt;
    &lt;requireLicenseAcceptance&gt;false&lt;/requireLicenseAcceptance&gt;
    &lt;description&gt;Octopack with Cassette.MsBuild&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;releaseNotes&gt;&lt;/releaseNotes&gt;
  &lt;/metadata&gt;
  &lt;files&gt;
    &lt;file src="cassette-cache\**\*.*" target="cassette-cache" /&gt;
    &lt;file src="Views\Web.config" target="Views\Web.config" /&gt;
    &lt;file src="js\**\*.*" target="js" /&gt;
    &lt;file src="lib\**\*.*" target="lib" /&gt;
    &lt;file src="css\app.css" target="css\app.css" /&gt;
    &lt;file src="index.aspx" target="index.aspx" /&gt;
    &lt;file src="Web.config" target="Web.config" /&gt;
    &lt;file src="bin\*.*" target="bin" /&gt;
  &lt;/files&gt;
&lt;/package&gt;
```

##Correcting the order
The final step is making sure the cassette target runs before the octopack target which can be done by adding a BeforeTargets attribute to the bundle target which will ensure that this will run and generate the cache folder before the octopack target runs.


```
  &lt;Target Name="Bundle" AfterTargets="Build" BeforeTargets="OctoPack"&gt;
    &lt;Exec Command="&amp;quot;$(msbuildtoolspath)\msbuild.exe&amp;quot; $(ProjectDirectory)cassette.targets /p:OutputPath=$(OutputPath) /t:Bundle /nr:false" /&gt;
  &lt;/Target&gt;
```

##The result
After everything is bundled together we end up with a nuget package with everything that is required to deploy our application including the cassette cache bundle.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/8b207f76-ed68-4ada-baa0-95dff32da2d1/Screen%20Shot%202014-05-13%20at%207.13.06%20PM_large.png)

#Conclusion
I will have to say I am loving what Octopus is doing for us in making our deployments easier.  It also is to incorporate to existing build targets to get exactly what you need packaged into your nuget package.

[Coode on github](https://github.com/markcoleman/Octopack.Cassette/tree/master)
</body>
  <title>AngularJs with no local js</title>
  <subtitle>Using the built in directives to build a simple contact form app.</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-05-04 20:34:26 -0400</published_at>
  <body>#The Idea
A few weeks ago I was pondering what kind of an app you could build with AngularJs without actually writing any JavaScript.  I have been toying with this idea off and on since then and have something that is functional, meets my expectations, and I didn't write any JavaScript.  

#What To Build
Given my constraints of not writing any JavaScript I had to keep the idea fairly simple but also something that could be potentially a real world scenario.  I decided on building a Contact Us form that asked for your name, contact method, and optional comments.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/924719d7-b90c-47fe-baf3-e2042434a30b/01-contact%20form_large.png)

#Getting Started
Since I didn't want to write any local JavaScript I still needed a way to serve the content to the browser.  The easiest way for me to handle this was to setup a node server using [express](http://expressjs.com).  With express installed (and me not knowing zero about express) I ended up with the following ```server.js``` file which hosted my local content and accepted a post to "save" my contact form.

```
var express = require('express')
    , app = express()
    , directory = __dirname;

app.use(express.static(directory))
    .use(express.bodyParser());

app.post("/save", function(req, res){
    console.log(req.body);
    res.redirect(301, 'thankyou.html');
});

app.listen(8080,function(){
    console.log("Listening on 8080 and serving content from " + directory);
});
```
From my limited expressjs knowledge I was able to setup a server that listens on port 8080, serves static content from the root of the site, accepts a post to the url ```/save```, parse the form parameters in ```req.body```, and issue a redirect to ```thankyou.html```.  Now that we have that part out of the way how about we get to something I know a little bit more about, angularjs.

#The Html
The first step we have is to create our html for the form and since I know bootstrap, how about we use that for some simple style.

```
&lt;body&gt;
&lt;div class="container-fluid"&gt;
    &lt;div class="row"&gt;
        &lt;div class="col-md-10 col-md-offset-1"&gt;
            &lt;h1&gt;
                AngularJs With No Local Js
            &lt;/h1&gt;

            &lt;form name="contactForm" method="post" action="save" class="form-horizontal"
                  role="form"&gt;
                &lt;fieldset&gt;
                    &lt;legend&gt;Contact Form&lt;/legend&gt;
                    &lt;div class="form-group"&gt;
                        &lt;label for="contactName" class="col-sm-2 control-label"&gt;Contact Name&lt;/label&gt;

                        &lt;div class="col-sm-10"&gt;
                            &lt;input type="text" id="contactName" name="contactName" required=""
                                    class="form-control" placeholder="Your first and last name"/&gt;

                            &lt;div&gt;
                                &lt;div class="alert alert-danger"&gt;
                                    &lt;span&gt;Contact name is required.&lt;/span&gt;
                                    &lt;span&gt;Contact name must be less than 40 characters.&lt;/span&gt;
                                &lt;/div&gt;
                            &lt;/div&gt;
                        &lt;/div&gt;
                    &lt;/div&gt;
   &lt;!-- 
Rest Omitted
--&gt;
```

#Adding Angularjs via some directives
Now that we have the base line it is time to add in some directives to make this static content dynamic based upon user selection and form validity.

##The Cast of Characters
[```ngModel```](https://docs.angularjs.org/api/ng/directive/ngModel)
Since we need to handle user input we require the usage of  ```ngModel``` so we can evaluate the validity of our form fields and display appropriate content to our user.

*Example of ngModel on the drop down list*

```
&lt;select ng-model="contactMethod" required="" class="form-control"&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Email&lt;/option&gt;
    &lt;option&gt;Telephone&lt;/option&gt;
&lt;/select&gt;
```

[```input```](https://docs.angularjs.org/api/ng/directive/input)
Speaking of form field validity using the ```input``` directive allows us to set constraints on max length, required fields, and min length.  We can use these validation options to display relevant messages to the user filling out our contact form.

*Example of max length and required on the contactName*

```
&lt;input type="text" id="contactName" name="contactName" ng-model="name" required="" ng-maxlength="40" class="form-control" placeholder="Your first and last name" /&gt;
```

[```ngSwitch```](https://docs.angularjs.org/api/ng/directive/ngSwitch)
Our form contains a drop down list asking for the user's contact method of either email or telephone.  Depending on what option is selected we want to show the appropriate form field and label.  We could use ```ngIf``` for this but using ```ngSwitch``` allows us to present only the fields required in a nice switch statement style syntax.

*Example to display telephone if the drop down is selected*

```
&lt;div ng-switch-when="Telephone"&gt;
    &lt;label for="telephone" class="col-sm-2 control-label"&gt;Telephone&lt;/label&gt;

    &lt;div class="col-sm-10"&gt;

        &lt;input type="tel" id="telephone" name="telephone" ng-model="telephone" required="" class="form-control" placeholder="Your telephone number" /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
```

[```ngIf```](https://docs.angularjs.org/api/ng/directive/ngIf)
Because we have a dynamic elements on the page based up on form validity we can utilize ```ngIf``` to display those error messages when invalid input is entered. (```ngShow``` could be used here as well but ```ngIf``` only adds the items to the dom if the expression is true)

*Example displaying an error message if the telephone field is empty*

```
&lt;div class="alert alert-danger" ng-if="contactForm.telephone.$dirty &amp;&amp; contactForm.telephone.$error.required"&gt;
    &lt;span&gt;Contact telephone is required&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
```

[```ngDisabled```](https://docs.angularjs.org/api/ng/directive/ngDisabled)
The last directive we are going to use is ```ngDisabled``` which allows us to disable the submit button if our form is not valid.

*Example to disable the submit button*

```
&lt;input type="submit" class="btn btn-primary btn-large" ng-disabled="contactForm.$invalid" value="Submit" /&gt;
```

#Conclusion
This was a fun exercise to see what you can actually do with AngularJs and not actually write any JavaScript.  In the end we built a contact form, had client side validation, displayed dynamic content based upon model state, and was able to submit our form via a post action.  Now would I do this on a real site?  Probably not as this example is very trivial and adding anything of substance would make our application very brittle with overly complex expressions in the view.

[Code on github](https://github.com/markcoleman/AngularJsWithNoLocalJs)</body>
  <title>Isolate NCrunch Unit Tests</title>
  <subtitle>Bang my head against the keyboard</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-03-28 11:26:01 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Today has been a bang my head on the keyboard type of morning.  This morning I set out to write tests to make sure the actions inside of our project are audited correctly by sending messages to a message queue.  Now as a good developer we don't want to test the action of sending to the message queue but just that the message was sent to the method on the ```ILog``` interface.  This seemed simple enough so let's get started.

Our audit service uses something similar to [```this.Log()```](https://github.com/ferventcoder/this.Log) which has some static methods to retrieve the correct logger for the type.  We have this abstracted away in a static container [I know not ideal, but what we have so far] so we can swap it out easily for unit tests to use a ```NullLog``` or in this case a ```TestableLogger```

I started out with the following logic

```
var testableLogger = new TestableLogger();
Log.Container = new UnityContainer().RegisterInstance&lt;ILog&gt;(testableLogger);
```

Everything worked perfectly and my Assert was happy

```
GenericAuditMessage genericAuditMessage = testableLogger.AuditMessages.Cast&lt;GenericAuditMessage&gt;().FirstOrDefault();
Assert.IsNotNull(genericAuditMessage);
```

Feeling a slight moment of happiness I went onto my next test and that one failed and now my first test that passed failed again.

##What is going on?
I figured it had to be something with the static variable so off to google I went to get some answers.  The first thing I saw that was promising was this answer on [stack overflow](http://stackoverflow.com/questions/12685690/ncrunch-all-test-pass-first-run-but-fails-after-code-change-and-when-run-all-bu).  From that I tried to use the debug with an existing task process which showed me that at one point the list had 3 items but in the assert it was 0.  There has to be a way to isolate these tests.

##Isolated Attribute
Well that was simple enough, add the isolated attribute to your test.

```
        [TestMethod]
        [Isolated]
```

After I added this to the offending tests everything was green again.


##Conclusion
This problem resulted from the design of the application (which is on my mental to do list), but if you ever run into a problem with a static variable and NCrunch give the ```[Isolated]``` attribute a try.</body>
  <title>How To: Unshelve To A Different Branch in TFS</title>
  <subtitle>to the command line!</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-03-19 09:19:07 -0400</published_at>
  <body>In the past week we were working out of a shelveset inside of TFS and soon realized we needed a branch as working out of the shelveset was not going to work any longer.

I created the new branch, pulled it down, and unshelved the changes while in the new branch.  When this action completed I looked around and wondered what happened to my changes?  Looking in "Pending Changes" the changes were pulled down, but to the original branch.  

#To the Google!
After a quick google I turned up the following [article describing](http://www.tomdupont.net/2013/10/unshelve-to-different-branch-in-tfs.html) what I needed to do.  The only change I needed was the sheveset was located on another TFS user.

#Install Power Tools
To perform this action you need to have TSF power tools installed, since we are running 2013 I [downloaded the 2013 version](http://visualstudiogallery.msdn.microsoft.com/f017b10c-02b4-4d6d-9845-58a06545627f)  from msdn.

#PowerShell
Now that power tools are installed we can go ahead and open up powershell and run the following command.

```
PS C:\Development&gt; tfpt unshelve "ShevesetName;UserName" /migrate /source:"$/Project/Source" /target:"$/Project/Target"
```

Just fill in the ```"SheveSetName;UserName"``` and the ```/source``` and ```/target``` branch pieces.

#Dialog
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/5fcbc0d0-60a2-4a95-8252-4be483fa2636/Screen%20Shot%202014-03-19%20at%209.05.39%20AM_large.png)
After you run the command you will be presented with a dialog prompting you if you wish to unshelve the changes.

#Resolve Dialog
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/f53697de-48da-4a61-aa79-9f7bbad3937c/Screen%20Shot%202014-03-19%20at%209.08.06%20AM_large.png)
Once you start the unshelve process you will be shown a merge dialog asking you how to resolve any conflicts present between the sheveset and the target branch.  After you click "Auto-merge All" you will see the power shell prompt start scrolling as it adds/deletes/auto-merges the files from the sheveset and the target branch.  When this finishes you can close down this dialog and the unshelve to a new branch is complete.

#Conclusion
This process was hidden inside of the TFS power tools but was easy to accomplish.  I am not sure why power tools are required and this can't be just part of TFS but at least there is a way to get it done.


</body>
  <title>SXSW'14 Day 4</title>
  <subtitle>Workshop, Keynote, and a quick session</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-03-10 23:57:38 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Day 4 for me consisted of a workshop, watching a keynote in the afternoon and watching a quick 15 minute talk from Scott Hanselman.

#[Data to Go: Mobile API Design](http://schedule.sxsw.com/2014/events/event_IAP17442)
Three principles for mobile api design

 - Reduce round trips to the server
 - Control verbosity
 - Restrict access

Learned something new, **Genymotion, faster android emulator**

##Reduce round trips to the server
Resource constrained environment

 - CPU
 - Memory
 - Bandwidth
 - Battery

Users are impatient
 
- Reduce network overhead
- Brevity trumps discoverability
- RESTful vs. RESTish

In mobile when activity starts the modem needs to power up into full power mode.  When this occurs you should try to take advantage of this time as much as possible.  This allows for much data transfer during this peak time.

Show me the cache, should you just cache?

 - Memory, uses up memory
 - Disk, uses up disk
 - Invalidation, when is cache dirty?

*Cache strategies are hard, you cant always simply cache responses*

Control Verbosity

 - Remove empty data
 - Remove irrelevant data
 - GZIP compression

Sip, don’t chug.

 - Less data is faster
 - Less data is less expensive

Knobs and dials

 - Pagination
 - Sort
 - Search
 - Filter

Object Expansion
Specifying verbosity level on per request basis

 - Abstract verbosity level, making levels to return how much data you want returned
 - Custom media type, applicaiton/cat.simple+json (small cat) application/cat.large+json (full cat)
 - Specifying response fields in the request, [list of fields you want returned]
 - Collection vs. resource, respond with a subset for collection groups, resource has all details


Authorization

 - Invalid credentials
 - Rate limit
 - Unsupported operation system
 - Obsolete application version
 - Blacklisted IP address

Do

 - HTTPS/SSL
 - Access token header
 - 2-step verification

Don’t

 - Session
 - Cookies
 - CSRF tokens
 - Oath* (unless api is public)
 - HMAC*

Wait.. I thought OAuth was good?

 - Which implementation?
 - Ok for public
 - Designed for 3-legged communication over un-encrypted connections
 - Apps can be decompiled to determine basing algorithm if done client-side.
 - Introduces significant overhead.
 - OAuth2 = Security Sadness


The Future 

 - SPDY
 - Binary Transfer Formats
  - Protobuf
  - BSON
  - Thrift
 - Websockets
 - HTTP 2.0



#Tomorrow is the close of the interactive conference and when I learn about hardware! 😀</body>
  <title>SXSW'14 Day 3</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-03-10 01:36:29 -0400</published_at>
  <body>Today was sort of slow for me since things started later at 11am (because of the time change).

**randome notes from the day**

#Building next generation User Experiences at NASA
**The Moon**
Software that helps scientists plan out experiments for the orbiter, users where actually the software in a different way to find the location of the orbiter. Designed a interface about this new need. 

**Mars**
Built mission control and scheduling software. Also was the entry point to get data from the rover.  Turns out people that where never intended to use the software are actually using the software. Redesign to focus on this new type of user. Lost science discussion that occurs before the tools is used.  They built Pinterest for the rover. Snapshot of all of the tasks and recent activity that occurs on the rover in a title styled display.  Interface for all users that makes everyone able to access this complex data, however it gives the user option to open in the expert interface. 

**Deep Space**
NASA have a philosophy of using checklists to get things done.  They had a redesign of the deep space link that didn't work. 

After talking to the link operators they realized two things, they had troubles with window management and they lived in the command line. 

The prototype took lots of this information to consolidate and embraced the command line. Predictive commands

**Kepler and Distant a Worlds**
New ways to visualize data, if you do not tell your story someone else will do it for you. 

**Final Take Aways**

 - Software should be visual
 - Software needs to be inviting
 - Software should be inventive 
 - Software should tell a story 
 - You need to talk with your users to understand their particular needs.

#Reorienting UX Design for the internet of Things
Internet of things is a network of uniquely identifiable objects that are interconnected. 

 - Cheap, powerful cpu, data everywhere, open cloud API's are everywhere. 
 - People get interrupted at least 80 times a day. 
 - Designing for things today you do not always have the users full attention. 
 - Attention is rare today
 - Deliver single and ambient information
 - Data without interpretation is just quantified noise. 
 - Service design is all areas of an item. Includes all touch points in a task. 


#The Next Mobile Experience

 - We have out dated habits and expectations
 - No rectangles are located in nature's building blocks
 - Organize information organically
 - Organic structures + relevant information + control = efficient
 - Gestures have no standards, which can result in confusing experiences for each app. 
 - Gestures are like a language, consistent and easy to understand

#[Be Awesome Without Their Permission](http://schedule.sxsw.com/2014/events/event_IAP27473)
The last session was with Alexis Ohanian which he talked about his experiences with the start of reddit.  I did not take any notes on this talk but it was very inspirational for you to do great things.

</body>
  <title>SXSW'14 Day 2</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-03-09 11:15:02 -0400</published_at>
  <body>#Breakfast
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/1348319e-11b3-4780-aa46-dac592c2d38a/IMG_1918_large.jpg)
Since I had a late night last night breakfast was in the form of a free Monster drink obtained from the registers lounge.

#SXXPress
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a9b06635-b073-408f-b792-3a8acf0b40f9/IMG_1919_large.jpg)
Back again to the SXXPress pass line on level 4, going up the escalator you can see the number of people milling around on the floor.  Getting up to the fourth floor there was a long line.  I feared it was not for the SXXPress line, but it was, so I decided to come back later realizing some of the passes might be sold out.

#How to say fuck no and still have them love you
This session I actually accidentally attended, but I am glad I did after listening to the speaker.  It discussed how the design process works as his company.  You give solutions not options and show the process how you came to that outcome.  This allows for the client to focus on the "what".

Some take away notes:

 - Success is by working with decision makers and not committees. 
 - They don't give options they give solutions. 
 - No one is an expert anymore, buy a dslr you are a photography. All information is online. 
 - Being an expert is something that is lost. 
 - Preach what you practice, you need to discuss what and why you did something. 
 - No Options, only solutions.  Justify every decision they make. 
 - With mechanical engineer you can prove why something is a bad idea.  With design there is in definitive proof that an idea is wrong. 
 - Ask the question why five times allows you to get down to the root of the problem. 
 - Clients always focus on the how, font size, logo size, colors. They should focus on the what
 - You need direct contact, going through a proxy can't work. You get sign off with wrong assumptions. 
 - Everything for the first proposal should be in blacks and white so there is no preference to color. 
 - Never say "I like it" that is personal preference. 
 - Sketches are ideas and not solutions. 
 - If you get bad ideas from clients, you need to come back with a better idea  
 - Never send over a design without some sort explanation on why the direction for the design. 
 - You can't give a informed opinion when someone just drops something in front of you. 

#Hungry
Since I have yet to actually have any food of substance I figured I will head to my next session and stop by a food stand near the room figuring I will have plenty of time (20 minutes from start).  I managed to eat up my time and by the time I got the door 100ft away the session was full.  *That will teach me to try to eat*

#Exploring Gesture in Interface Design
I got to this session late, but it was interesting to hear how gestures and other forms of feedback influence devices and humans interact with them.

A few take aways

 - Talk about how feedback in gesture based style devices gives better experience with the device. 
 - Gestures were conceived in 1983
 - Standards are good and bad.  A good balance allows you to use standards but the ability to use your device your way. 
 - Nothing is a one size fits all. 


#CSS Preprocessor Myths
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/073b894a-7146-470e-8f32-f059a88ee769/IMG_1920_large.jpg)
Since we recently started using less at work this session was a perfect fit for me.  The session ended up being a refresher on some of the topics I read about in the past regarding to less/sass.  Once again this ended up being one of the sessions I know I *should* go to for work as it relates but at the end of the day I would have been better off going to something outside of my comfort zone.  I did have a few take aways which will be good to share with the team back home.

Informal poll shows sass leading the way in Europe. 

In USA, big portion of users asked do not use a pre processors. Sass is also the most popular. 

Why use it?

 - CSS is repetitive
 - CSS doesn't have variables
 - Plan CSS is inflexible, limited reusability. 
 - Complex websites are hard to maintain

The Myths

 - Adds complexity to the development process
 - You lose control over the final code
 - Adds overhead to the website
 - Adds extra dependencies to your development workflow
 - Too hard to debug

&gt;God, SCSS looks like JavaScript and Php mated in a drunken state - Christian Heilmann

**Debunking the Myths**
Complexity

 - Nesting is a natural way of coding.
 - Named variables are easier to manage than individual values like colors 
 - You don't have to use all the functionality

Lose Control

 - If your CSS code is currently horrible, your sass will undoubted be horrible. 
 - Sass doesn't write code by itself
 - Use expanded output option during development

Overhead

 - Compiled file is just plain CSS 
 - Automatically minify/compress the CSS output 
 - Easy to add (or remove) vendor evil prefixes
 - Seem less file concatenation, so you can maintain the styles easier

Dependencies

 - Your current setup already has dependencies
 - If you don't use a pre processor, you need a post processor
 - Many tools are available for free

Hard to Debug

 - Organized code shouldn't be hard to debug
 - There are ways
 - It's getting better

Techniques and Tips

 - Sass debug info
 - Sass debug info, shows the sass line number in the CSS output so you can easily reference the original location
Source maps
 - Chrome 30+ includes source map support for sass 3.3 and Less 1.5. Allows for the map file to identify the original file location. 

File organization

 - Divide and conquer
 - Master the import files  and file concatenation
 - It's easier to find a rule in a small file
 - Import within media queries so you don't have to repeat media queries
 - Make one file by component/section with all it's media queries

Nesting

 - Apply the inception rule, do not go greater than 3 levels deep

Pitch

 - Hoisin.scss, light and extensible, responsive, doesn't make any design assumptions. Start point to write your code.  Content first and performance first.
 
Which one is the best?

 - All have about the same functionality
 - Use the one that fits in your workflow and feels better to you.
 
Final Considerations

 - Source Control, ignore compiled css/compile on deployment


#Lunch
Now that my session is over I figured I should get a proper lunch.  I talked to a few people at the conference recommended [Casino El Camino](http://www.casinoelcamino.net)  It did not disappoint!

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/124ee1e0-6008-47c1-bd7d-e19465749d7b/IMG_1921_large.jpg)
*KC Burger with Beer Braised Pork Belly*

#Always Be Testing Novelty in A/B Tests
The last workshop for the day was talking about A/B testing in terms of email marketing to raise funds for the Obama reelection campaign.   This workshop was really good for me as it gave me insight on how various email campaigns work and what kind of tactic you should take to increase clicks and money.

Some take aways

 - Words are important words like now convey to the user that this is just the next step

Tools Used

 - Optimize league 
 - Blue state digital

Novelty factor

 - Basically a tactic hat is effective nit because it is awesome but simply because it is eye catching. 
 - Supporter records
 - Adding a p.s.

 - Mix control group with some of these novelty testing

Case studio, ugly email

 - Sometimes pretty does not mean better, simple and plain looks more like a real person sent it.
 - Ugly yellow highlighting can be a novelty effect

Case Study, email volume

 - Two emails in a day did not result in a scary amount of unsubscribes.  Everything more resulted in just extra money. 
 - More emails resulted in more money
 - **Time of day is not really important, just don't send the middle of the night.** 
 - Adding  in 🔔 in subjects increases novelty effect.

#[Predestination](http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2397535/)
I decided to end my day by seeing a movie. I did not know anything about this movie but was a great watch.  It kept you guessing until the end.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/f8469746-c456-46de-b58d-3a7579c02842/IMG_1923_large.jpg)</body>
  <title>SXSW'14 Day 1</title>
  <subtitle>SXSW'14 Day 1</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-03-09 03:19:01 -0400</published_at>
  <body>This post is a day late, however better late than never.

#Wholly Burgers
The day started off at [Wholly Burgers](http://www.whollycowburgers.com) for some breakfast.  I randomly found this place after a simple google search looking for breakfast in Austin.  I arrived after a walk and asked them what is good for breakfast and decided on the French Toast.  In what seemed to take a bit longer than it should have the breakfast food arrived and it was good.  I will say the sausage patty was the best part.

#SXXPress
After breakfast was obtained it was time to get to the SXXPress pass line in the hopes to get some passes so I don't have to wait in the long badge lines to see a few movies today.  I arrived a little after 10am and was presented with no lines (good) however passes for [Chef](http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2883512/) were all gone (oh no).  I got in line anyways and made sure to secure my passes to [Cosmos](http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2395695/) and [13 Sins](http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2059171/)

#Lean UX
Now that the early morning activities where finished up time to get to my first session.  A book reading from [Lean UX].   (http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920021827.do)  This talk was short but was very insightful on how you can take agile approaches to design and how you can incorporate this ideas into your processes.  This small taste on Lean UX brought me wanting more and I will soon be reading his book in the coming months.

#BBQ Crash Course
I actually forgot I registered for this event during checkout last year until I saw it on the schedule.  After my first session my only gap in time was now and I had to run over to get me some BBQ.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/77b38609-42d7-4d01-bc5d-e7cee7d39f9a/IMG_1898_large.jpg)
As you can see my plate was full, it was fuller but I managed to eat some while obtaining more BBQ.  Everything was good, however for me the star of the plate was brisket from the various vendors.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a3ff3c2a-cd47-4d86-8ad7-30ab0363cb0b/IMG_1900_large.jpg)

#[5 Things Every Developer Needs to Know About Design](http://schedule.sxsw.com/2014/events/event_IAP27303)
After stuffing my face I needed to rush over to the Radisson for my first full session.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/98aa36f0-3581-4090-8ec7-3052eb8ee536/IMG_1901_large.jpg)
A few take aways from this session notes...

*Attractive things work better.*

 - Layout - order, variety, contrast, symmetry, tension, balance (two different objects with the same weight), scale, (you don't have to make big to increase scale), texture, space. Stability body content. Excitement header
Golden ratio, 
 - Using imagery, better to show than tell, leading the eye, pay attention to direction. Use icons and shapes, round things are easier to look at instead of sharp edges.
 - Color, use to emphasis importance, not to just decorate a page, understand color intensity. 
 - Using Typography, serif fonts lead into each letter making it easier to read, sans good for adding emphasis very distinct letters. 
Serif for headings (slab, Rockwell), sans for body copy. Limit to no more than three fonts. 
 - Feedback, have others help you.  [Bēhance](http://www.behance.net) allows for new feedback and track some revisions.  

#[Rich Web Experiences &amp; the Future of the Web](http://schedule.sxsw.com/2014/events/event_IAP27377)
This session turned out to be a crash course of all things new that are in the web.

 - [Clip paths](https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/clip-path), can transition and alter interfaces. Revel and hide content
 - [Mask images](http://tympanus.net/codrops/2013/12/02/techniques-for-creating-textured-text/), allows for textures on top of content
 - Blend modes, background image blend modes with multiple background images. (Experimental)
 - Filters, saturate, contrast, blur, etc. filters can be stacked
 - Vector, images sag a few libraries noted are Raphaël.js (compatibility) d3.js (graph and dats), snap.js (new modern svg)
 - 2d canvas,  easel.js, processing.js, pixi.js
 - Voice, API for interesting navigation options.
 - Webgl, a few libraries noted are three.js, Babylon.js, pixi.js
 - Video, 
 - Sprite Sheets, combine images lower requests
 - Semantics, the mark up and the text in the document
 - WebRTC, real time audio video chat
This talk was ok, but was such a crash course in all things new and exciting it was hard for me to focus on a particular aspect and how I could utilize this in my day job.

#Responsive Web Design When Things Are Teh Sux0r
This was my first workshop and while it was a goo refreshing I unfortunately was not exposed to new ideas or concepts.  The workshop focused on responsive layouts and how you can utilize some core web design ideas to get your sites to the next level.  The workshop was good, but just unfortunately not for me.

#Chef
Now after my interactive sessions were over for the day time to go stand in line and try to get into see the movie Chef.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/ebf6043d-e9bd-4dc2-bfc8-9078529b2cc9/IMG_1902_large.jpg)
The line was long and went around the block but I was able to get in to see the movie.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/d5cd02a4-e1d7-40de-b372-07d2032e4605/IMG_1906_large.jpg)

#Cosmos
This was an episode screening of the pilot and I will say I am excited to see more of what this show has to offer.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/8b463f70-627d-496e-b485-cc6922032fb6/IMG_1914_large.jpg)

#13 Sins
This was an unknown movie to me, but was intrigued by the plot.  It was exciting to see the ever increasing tasks the main character had to preform to win the prize.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/45d3e8e7-58bd-433f-96f3-8d4480c049fd/IMG_1916_large.jpg)

#Sleep
It was a long day, so time to get some sleep</body>
  <title>Arriving to Austin</title>
  <subtitle>Day Zero of SXSW</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-03-06 23:29:08 -0500</published_at>
  <body>I went to SXSW last year and had a great time experiencing all that SXSW has to offer.  When it came around to "what conferences would you like to go to?" time at work I said, "I would like to go back to SXSW!"  From the twitter sphere sxsw might be old hat for some, but for me it is a chance to learn new things, talk to new people, and get out of my comfort zone of building financial applications.

#Leaving From Home
This turned out to be quite the ordeal.  I know leaving from our local airport you need about 5 minutes of time to get from the ticket counter to your gate, but being myself I always like to give myself a few extra minutes (cough, 1 ½ hours).  About ½ hour until my I leave to my connecting flight I get the following:

&gt;United flight UA from Chicago, IL (ORD - O'Hare) to Austin, TX (AUS) on March 6 is canceled.
To see available options, go to united.com/flightupdates, access an airport kiosk or see a United representative at the airport.

#Great! To the Phone!
My only option at this point was to call customer service since the reservation system online would just give me an error, plus I am ½ until I have to board my flight to Chicago! Do I get on? Do I wait?  It felt like forever, but as the door closed to my flight the representative said, "You have a seat, get on your flight" **awesome!**

#On the Plane
It was interesting to see the Susquehanna river during the winter time partially frozen.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/114ab677-a5e2-49c4-a91f-9ae1175dcfef/IMG_1890_large.jpg)

#Arriving In Chicago
On the arrival to Chicago I was able to witness the frozen lake of Michigan from the aircraft.  According to various news outlets it is around [90% frozen](http://chicago.cbslocal.com/2014/03/03/lake-michigan-90-percent-covered-in-ice-equals-highest-level-ever/)

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/483d04fb-f705-452f-9de6-36fffbd9a812/IMG_1892_large.jpg)

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/4bcaab5d-f639-49a5-a15b-0d0212aa1b77/IMG_1893_large.jpg)

#In Chicago Airport
Nothing really exciting to report at the airport.  I arrived, found some lunch, made sure I had a seat (and I did), and waiting for my flight

#On the Plane
Finally, I am on the plane to Austin!  I sit down in my seat and prepare to relax for the trip to Austin.  About 5 minutes a lady goes over the intercom and says "This plane is inoperable, we have another plane at gate B7"

#Off the Plane
I get off the plane and run over to gate B7, and wait.  I also wait some more.

#Back On the Plane
After some more waiting, I am back on the plane!  Finally, time to get to austin!

#The Flight
During the flight we had a light snack of roasted vegetables and some fruit.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/d1e49a5c-bb0b-4389-b423-f433b05edabc/IMG_1894_large.jpg)

Also during this time I realized it would be a good time to work on my up and coming blog post regarding AngularJs, "AngularJs with User Js"

```
&lt;span ng-show="contactForm.contactName.$dirty"&gt;
            &lt;span ng-show="contactForm.contactName.$error.required"&gt;Contact name is required&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span ng-show="contactForm.contactName.$error.maxlength"&gt;Max of 40&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;label for="contactName"&gt;Contact Name&lt;/label&gt;
                    &lt;input type="text" id="contactName" name="contactName" ng-model="name" required=""
                           ng-maxlength="40"/&gt;

                    &lt;br/&gt;

                    &lt;label&gt;Contact Method&lt;/label&gt;
                    &lt;select ng-model="contactMethod" required=""&gt;
                        &lt;option&gt;Email&lt;/option&gt;
                        &lt;option&gt;Telephone&lt;/option&gt;
                    &lt;/select&gt;

                    &lt;div ng-switch on="contactMethod"&gt;

                        &lt;div ng-switch-when="Email"&gt;
                            &lt;label for="email"&gt;Email&lt;/label&gt;
                        &lt;span ng-show="contactForm.email.$dirty"&gt;
            &lt;span ng-show="contactForm.email.$error.required"&gt;Contact name is required&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;
                            &lt;input type="email" id="email" name="email" ng-model="email" required=""/&gt;
                        &lt;/div&gt;
                        &lt;div ng-switch-when="Telephone"&gt;
                            &lt;label for="email"&gt;Telephone&lt;/label&gt;
                        &lt;span ng-show="contactForm.telephone.$dirty"&gt;
            &lt;span ng-show="contactForm.telephone.$error.required"&gt;Contact telephone is required&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/span&gt;
                            &lt;input type="tel" id="telephone" name="telephone" ng-model="telephone" required=""/&gt;
                        &lt;/div&gt;
                    &lt;/div&gt;
```

It is starting to come quite nicely, It is amazing what can be done with the build in directives.

#At the Hotel
The plane lands, I wait in the taxi line, and get to my hotel.  There really is nothing exciting to talk regarding that leg of my travel.

#Getting the Badge
Now that I am at the hotel, my next task is to make the trek to the convention center so I can pick up my badge.

#Badge Obtained
The registration process was just like last year.  I went into Expo Room 1, gave my badge quick pick up code and Id and walked out the door with my badge.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/b45a107e-47c4-4641-bea1-ff41bf6b5b8c/IMG_1897_large.jpg)

#Time To Find Food
Now that I got my badge and my bags of stuff, I need food.  Last year I went to [Banger's](http://bangersaustin.com) and decided to make a return visit.  I got a few select local brews and an awesome fried chicken meal (battered and fried chicken sausage, mash, biscuit, and gravy).  The food and beer was amazing!  I highly recommend this place if you find yourself in Austin.

#Back To The Hotel
I know from last year, I need to take it easy at least a few nights.  Being in SXSW leaves you with a lot of good memories and a lack of sleep.  So tonight I end the night a bit early.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/0056f5db-8442-4890-8be0-38ea5e5baafb/IMG_1896_large.jpg)

#Until Tomorrow</body>
  <title>My First Azure Mobile Service for iOS</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-03-02 09:12:38 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Recently I have been exploring and learning as much as I can regarding azure.  So far I learned how to [build a vm in the cloud](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/my-first-azure-vm), perform some [load testing](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/load-testing-in-the-cloud), and [deploy a website via git](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/i-just-deployed-to-azure-via-git).  Next up on my list is to learn about Mobile Services.  First thing I am going to learn is how to configured it and create a sample iOS project that stores and retrieves data from azure.

*Steps I took, your mileage may vary*

###Log into the portal
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c320148c-49da-4ad9-8cc4-a81beb6a8c2f/01%20-%20mobile%20services_large.png)
Logically the first thing you need to do is log into the azure portal and click on "Mobile Services" and then "Create A New Mobile Service"

###Pick Url
From there you are presented a wizard that guides you through the process of creating your first mobile service.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/5eb13839-1df0-4463-82fd-04469e6494f2/02%20-%20create_large.png)

###Setup Sql Server Info
Since I picked to create a new sql server I had to fill out the settings for the sql db.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/8d303696-9312-4561-9ad7-6a147b7cbc3f/03%20-%20create%20-db_large.png)

###Creating mobile service and Sql
After you complete those two steps your first mobile service will be configured and created.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/e202e953-fc0e-4a28-965b-72e02bed33c2/04%20-%20creating_large.png)

###Getting Started
After a few minutes your mobile service is created and you are presented with a getting started page which includes sample code for various mobile platforms.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/d01366ed-7e7e-4a83-bb97-f92ba85b7480/05%20-%20getting%20started_large.png)

#iOS
In this example I am going to use iOS as the platform to consume my first mobile service.  The demo project I am going to create is the Master Detail project type when creating a new Xcode project.

*Disclaimer, I am a C# developer by day so any tips on how to improve this is greatly appreciated.*

###Adding the client
After I created the Master Detail project I have to add in the SDK for iOS that allows me to communicate to my mobile service.  From the getting started guide you [download the SDK](https://go.microsoft.com/fwLink/?LinkID=266533&amp;clcid=0x409).  After you have it downloaded the guide simply mentions dragging and dropping the two framework files into your project.  Make sure to check the box to copy to the project.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/cf7ffd02-686c-4f35-8b50-dcdbb5e7692c/06%20-%20drag%20and%20drop_large.png)


##Or use CocoaPods
Last week when I learned about [error logging with Raygun for iOS](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/capture-errors-in-ios-with-raygun) I was introduced to [cocoapods](http://cocoapods.org) which is a dependency manager for objective-c projects.  I like this idea so we can reference the azure sdk via a PodFile and not deal with drag and drop or downloading from a site.  

###Create a PodFile
```
touch PodFile
```
###Add in your dependency
```
pod 'AzureSDK-iOS', '~&gt; 1.1'
```
###Install your dependencies
```
pod install
```
###Open your project
```
 open iOS\ With\ Azure.xcworkspace/
```


##Using the Client
Now that we have the client framework installed we can start using it.  Under the getting started welcome page it gives you tasks needed to interact with your mobile service.

###Add to AppDelegate.h
The first thing you need to do is create a property to hold your MSClient, I used the guide and added this to the AppDelegate.h file in the iOS project.

```
#import &lt;UIKit/UIKit.h&gt;
#import &lt;WindowsAzureMobileServices.h&gt;

@interface AppDelegate : UIResponder &lt;UIApplicationDelegate&gt;

@property (strong, nonatomic) UIWindow *window;

@property (strong, nonatomic) MSClient *client;

@end
```
###Add to AppDelegate.m
Since we now have a property in our header file we can instantiate our MSClient inside of the ```didFinishLaunchingWithOptions``` method.  This code snip it was also obtained from the getting started guide for iOS. 

```
- (BOOL)application:(UIApplication *)application didFinishLaunchingWithOptions:(NSDictionary *)launchOptions
{
    
    self.client = [MSClient clientWithApplicationURLString:@"https://yourSite.azure-mobile.net/"
                                            applicationKey:@"yourApplicationKey"];
    
    // Override point for customization after application launch.
    if ([[UIDevice currentDevice] userInterfaceIdiom] == UIUserInterfaceIdiomPad) {
        UISplitViewController *splitViewController = (UISplitViewController *)self.window.rootViewController;
        UINavigationController *navigationController = [splitViewController.viewControllers lastObject];
        splitViewController.delegate = (id)navigationController.topViewController;
    }
    return YES;
}
```

###Add to MasterViewController.m
Now that we have a client setup what can we use it for?  Well since our project is a master detail application we can use mobile services to store our objects in azure.

First thing we need to add is the #import statements so we can use our MSClient located in our AppDelegate

```
#import &lt;WindowsAzureMobileServices.h&gt;
#import "AppDelegate.h"
```

###Get Data From Mobile Service Table
I added the loading logic into the ```viewDidLoad``` function that will populate our ```_objects``` array which was present in the default master detail project.  The method to retrieve the client and getting a reference to the Items table was also obtained from the getting started guide in the portal.

```
- (void)viewDidLoad
{
    [super viewDidLoad];
	// Do any additional setup after loading the view, typically from a nib.
    self.navigationItem.leftBarButtonItem = self.editButtonItem;

    UIBarButtonItem *addButton = [[UIBarButtonItem alloc] initWithBarButtonSystemItem:UIBarButtonSystemItemAdd target:self action:@selector(insertNewObject:)];
    self.navigationItem.rightBarButtonItem = addButton;
    self.detailViewController = (DetailViewController *)[[self.splitViewController.viewControllers lastObject] topViewController];
    
    addButton.enabled = NO;
    
    //get data from azure mobile services
    MSClient *client = [(AppDelegate *) [[UIApplication sharedApplication] delegate] client];
    MSTable *itemTable = [client tableWithName:@"Item"];
    [itemTable readWithCompletion:^(NSArray *items, NSInteger totalCount, NSError *error) {
        
        if (!_objects) {
           _objects = [[NSMutableArray alloc] init];
        }
        
        for(NSDictionary* object in items){
            [_objects insertObject: object atIndex:0];
            NSIndexPath *indexPath = [NSIndexPath indexPathForRow:0 inSection:0];
            [self.tableView insertRowsAtIndexPaths:@[indexPath] withRowAnimation:UITableViewRowAnimationAutomatic];
        }
        addButton.enabled = YES;
    }];
    
}
```

###Insert Data To Mobile Services
Since our master detail project also had a simple hook to add items to the list this was a good opportunity to add our objects to the azure table.  The insert snip it was obtained from the getting started guide with modifications so it fits inside of our demo app.

```
- (void)insertNewObject:(id)sender
{
    
    NSString *UUID = [[NSUUID UUID] UUIDString];
    
    //insert data into mobile services
    MSClient *client = [(AppDelegate *) [[UIApplication sharedApplication] delegate] client];
    NSDictionary *item = @{ @"text" : UUID };
    MSTable *itemTable = [client tableWithName:@"Item"];
    [itemTable insert:item completion:^(NSDictionary *insertedItem, NSError *error) {
        if (error) {
            NSLog(@"Error: %@", error);
        } else {
            NSLog(@"Item inserted, id: %@", [insertedItem objectForKey:@"id"]);
            
            [_objects insertObject: insertedItem atIndex:0];
            NSIndexPath *indexPath = [NSIndexPath indexPathForRow:0 inSection:0];
            [self.tableView insertRowsAtIndexPaths:@[indexPath] withRowAnimation:UITableViewRowAnimationAutomatic];

        }
    }];
}
```

###Remove Data From Table
The last action you can perform in the master detail application is removing an item.  This allows us the ability to remove data from the azure table by deleting the item based on it's id.

```
- (void)tableView:(UITableView *)tableView commitEditingStyle:(UITableViewCellEditingStyle)editingStyle forRowAtIndexPath:(NSIndexPath *)indexPath
{
    if (editingStyle == UITableViewCellEditingStyleDelete) {
        
        //remove the item from mobile services
        MSClient *client = [(AppDelegate *) [[UIApplication sharedApplication] delegate] client];
        MSTable *itemTable = [client tableWithName:@"Item"];
        
        NSDictionary* item = _objects[indexPath.row];
        NSString* itemId = [item valueForKey:@"id"];
        
        [itemTable deleteWithId:itemId completion:^(id itemId, NSError *error) {
           
            [_objects removeObjectAtIndex:indexPath.row];
            [tableView deleteRowsAtIndexPaths:@[indexPath] withRowAnimation:UITableViewRowAnimationFade];
        }];
        

    } else if (editingStyle == UITableViewCellEditingStyleInsert) {
        // Create a new instance of the appropriate class, insert it into the array, and add a new row to the table view.
    }
}
```

###Run the app
Now that we have all the pieces in place we can run our application which will allow us to add, delete, and retrieve items from our azure mobile service.

![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/de97c838-8627-40a2-9bc7-8b424580e04b/07%20-%20running%20app_large.png)

###Back to the portal
After you add in a few items and you go back to he portal you can see the data that is now in our table.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/2760c763-8c6e-4b42-9602-5f7ca37e7ede/08%20-%20view%20data_large.png)

#Conclusion
Once again azure impresses me with the ease to get started with it's services.  

[Code on github](https://github.com/markcoleman/iOSWithAzure)</body>
  <title>Installing Octopus Deploy</title>
  <subtitle>Adventures in automated deployment</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-02-26 22:28:39 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Now that [I have two VMs setup inside of azure](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/my-first-azure-vm) it is time to install [Octopus Deploy](http://octopusdeploy.com) to begin my attempt at automated deployment.  I am going to show the basic steps I went through to see if I can figure things out without reading my documentation (for now).

#Install The Server
###License and download
The first thing have to do is get a trial license to octopus so I can install the server. This license was obtained on the website [here](http://octopusdeploy.com/licenses/trial) .  When you submit the form you can download the [server install here](http://octopusdeploy.com/downloads) .

###Run the installer
I like installers like this, no configuration, just a simple install location!

###Getting Started
Now that we have it installed let's see what we need to do next to get things running.  Here are the screens I captured during the server install process.

###Welcome
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/ce2e492f-37cf-4f29-9bf8-a892a787bfb5/01-welcome%20-%20server_large.png)

###License
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/aa53ebf6-6e51-4af3-8b50-3ee36277565f/02-Lic%20-%20Server_large.png)
Simply paste in the license you received via email into the text area.

###Storage
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c93f8b2a-25d1-4da1-948d-20913f6065f5/03-%20storage%20-%20server_large.png)
I changed the value to ```D:\Octopus``` not really sure why I did this but felt like a good idea.

###Web Portal
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/927bc9f1-8c75-49cb-b25b-b78e33170a89/04-%20portal%20-%20server_large.png)
I left the default settings for the web portal since I have nothing else installed on this fresh azure vm.

###Authentication
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/d07f72ef-27a9-4820-9eac-516046e6cce7/05%20-%20auth%20-%20server_large.png)
Since I have only two simple vms azure I decided to go with the username/password authentication.  When we install this on the production server we will probably leverage active directory.

###Install
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/baf8b73f-6bbf-4a62-b1d8-9ed02786c5c6/06%20-%20install%20-%20server_large.png)
The one thing I thought was interesting is the ability to view the install script which means you must be able to install this via command line which is cool.  

##Manager
After you have it all installed you are presented with a manager window for the Octopus Server.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/ad255740-8a1d-4827-aae1-34cbe9dd443c/07%20-%20manager%20-%20server_large.png)

Now that we have this installed let's see how we install a tentacle.

#Install A Tentacle
###Download tentacle software
If you go back to the [download page](http://octopusdeploy.com/downloads), download, and install the tentacle.  Once again no configuration during setup, nice!

**Screens captured during the tentacle setup.**

###Welcome
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/4ac09ef2-c01f-406c-b871-ecc248d172f4/08%20-%20welcome%20-%20tent_large.png)

###Storage
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/e7dea5cf-8946-4717-9e8d-90458499b9d1/09%20-%20storage%20-%20tent_large.png)
I let these values as the defaults for now and will need to do a bit more research on what these values mean for a production install.

###Communication
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/8ceae60a-0204-4e1e-906e-a2896747cc3e/10%20-%20comm%20-%20tent_large.png)
This is the one setting I decided to research to understand the difference between listening or polling.  The documentation and install recommends listening as it is less cpu intensive.  Next screen asks for the thumbprint value which can be obtained from the octopus server, so back to the server we go.

###Add Environment on Octopus Server
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/4ae305c2-3b65-424a-9eea-63c0c4c2bc01/11%20-%20add%20env%20-%20server_large.png)
Since this is a fresh install I was able to click on Environment and create an Octopus environment.

###Add Machine to Environment
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/5b8a9302-c23e-4b6e-a689-4fb40608ad22/12%20-%20add%20machine%20-%20server_large.png)
Once I had an environment setup now I need to add a machine to that environment.  This step also displays the thumbprint value mentioned in the tentacle install.

###Back to Tentacle Configuration
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/729a23ba-f324-462a-9a3e-cfe2784a36d4/13%20-%20add%20print%20-%20tent_large.png)
With the newly obtained thumbprint value I pasted the value into the tentacle configuration.

###Install
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/eb76c9f3-bbb1-4d69-bbfc-e0ae7e12c9da/14%20-%20install%20-%20tent_large.png)
Now we are able to install the tentacle configuration.

###Manager
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/b8e96dde-172f-465d-9491-4f0cffab8365/15%20-%20manager%20-%20tent_large.png)
After the configuration is applied we are displayed a similar manager screen for the tentacle.

###Back to Server
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/af66c110-0972-4834-adc4-34043c9967f5/16%20-%20machine%20setting%20-%20server_large.png)
Now that the tentacle is configured I clicked on "Discover" to connect the Server to the Tentacle. **I did run into an error the first time because my fresh VM didn't have the port opened up for the communication from the server to the tentacle.  To fix simply open up Windows Firewall and allow communication over the port you configured**

###Configured
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/312454be-5b11-4cfc-84dd-56de992b7801/17%20-%20machine%20-%20server_large.png)
It now looks like we have an Octopus Server and one tentacle configured.  This wasn't hard at all.

#Conclusion
So far installation was painless and very straight foreword.  This is the first step for my goal of automated deployment.  Next up let's see what this thing can do, but for now I will consider this a win for tonight!

</body>
  <title>My First Azure VM</title>
  <subtitle>It was easy!</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-02-26 20:14:06 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Recently I began doing some preliminary research on [Octopus Deploy](http://octopusdeploy.com) for automated deployment of our .net application.  With the nature of deployment I thought it might be interesting to set up an environment with a few servers to see how this all works together.  Because of this idea I don't feel like doing this myself, maybe I can leverage azure and some of my monthly credits to get up and running quickly.

I read about using gallery images to setup a windows server, how about we try this out and see how easy or hard it ends up being.

Steps involved for me *your milage my vary*
###Log into the portal
First off you need to log into the azure portal.

###Click Virtual Machines
I navigated to the virtual machines icon on the left and click on the create virtual machines link as I had no virtual machines setup prior.

###Create New VM
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/73b5fa6a-5bfe-4592-a79e-deb1c4d53ff6/new%20vm%20portal_large.png)
A create new VM form showed up from the bottom.  Since I wanted to create something from the gallery I decided to click the link "From Gallery"

###Selecting Microsoft Windows Server
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/9f2ea11e-e130-412a-96fd-fdf788ed6d1d/select%20windows_large.png)
Now since I wanted to create a Windows Server I selected the Windows Server Essentials image.

###Server Name and User
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/3115389c-594c-4081-8ec8-5f9ad8b9ab2a/server%20details_large.png)
The next screen I saw was some initial configuration for the Vm including server name and the first user in the system.

###Cloud Service, region, storage, etc
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/9db2fc23-3905-44cb-8032-66f0220fd318/vm%20configuration_large.png)
This next screen talks about cloud service, region, storage, and a few other options.  I decided to leave these at the default as I need to do a bit more research on what each one means.

###Setup Ports
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/93015541-a4b4-401b-9f32-96ac4f357a79/setup%20ports_large.png)
Next you can configure which endpoints are exposed on this server.  This allows you to RDP in, power shell, open up HTTP, etc.  Once again I left the default configuration and clicked the ✓.

###Creating VM
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/b4f149d2-ae43-40d2-8b86-061374ce38e7/Creating%20your%20Vm_large.png)
After a few seconds the VM started the provisioning process.  Since I didn't have a cloud service setup it created that first and then the actual virtual machine.  After a few minutes everything was created and we were running.

###It is running!
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/3aaba21b-b89a-4850-be1e-6939df2a2c03/it%20is%20running_large.png)
After the Vm was created I clicked on the VM and then the connect icon on the bottom task bar.  This downloaded an rdp file that allows you to remotely connect to your azure vm.
*I was unable to RDP into the azure vm from my mac as I found from this [answer](http://stackoverflow.com/questions/13248955/cant-rdp-to-azure-on-mac-os-x).  Once I connected from Windows 8.1 I had no problems.*

#Conclusion
Well after a few minutes and some basic configuration I had a fresh new VM setup and running waiting for my input.  It was easy!</body>
  <title>Capture Errors in iOS with RayGun</title>
  <subtitle>.Net developer tries to get Raygun working in iOS</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-02-25 22:14:21 -0500</published_at>
  <body>As you might know I am a .net developer with a recent love of JavaScript and AngularJs.  At my job we also built two mobile applications which caused us to jump on the Objective-C and Java bandwagon to support iOS and Android.  (Xamarin looks awesome and we need to try it out soon).  With that being said we are receiving complaints that are app is crashing unexpectedly which we just can't seem to reproduce locally or on any of the devices we have at our disposal.  How can we track down these errors?  Raygun has an iOS client, maybe we can use that to track down our problem.

#Install CocoaPods
The first thing we need to do is install [CocoaPods](http://cocoapods.org).  Now what is CocoaPods?  CocoaPods is a dependency management utility that is for Objective-C projects that appears to be similar to NuGet in the .Net world.

The first thing I did was install cocoapods via terminal
```
sudo gem install cocoapods
```

#Create Application
For our example I created a simple master detail application so I had a bare bones example project.  After we have our application created quit Xcode so we can configure our Raygun dependency.

#Setup Application
Now we need to add in our Raygun dependency.

Navigate to your project directory in terminal and run the following command
```
touch PodFile
```
This will create an empty PodFile which we will use for our dependencies.
```
platform :ios
pod 'Raygun4iOS'
```
Now run pod install to pull down our dependencies.
```
pod install
```

#Add in RayGun
We our dependencies installed we need to open our project.  When using CocoaPods you can't open up the project file anymore but instead you need to run the following command to open up the workspace.

```
open RayGunExample.xcworkspace
```
![Xcode](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/7c39ab94-b309-46e3-818d-945e8fef73f8/Screen%20Shot%202014-02-25%20at%209.45.03%20PM_large.png)

Inside our workspace navigate to the ```AppDelegate.m``` file inside of your project and add the following statement.
```
#import &lt;Raygun.h&gt;
```
Inside of the ```didFinishLaunchingWithOptions``` function I added the Raygun snip it to get things wired up and working.
```
[Raygun sharedReporterWithApiKey:@"YOUR_API_KEY_HERE"];
```
Now we are ready to throw an error.

#Throw an Error
As not being an Objective-C developer I had to google how to throw an exception.  I placed this code inside the ```newDetailItem``` method so the application crashes when a user views detail in our master detail application.
```
- (void)setDetailItem:(id)newDetailItem
{
    [NSException raise:@"Invalid value" format:@"number of %d is invalid", 42];
    if (_detailItem != newDetailItem) {
        _detailItem = newDetailItem;
        
        // Update the view.
        [self configureView];
    }

    if (self.masterPopoverController != nil) {
        [self.masterPopoverController dismissPopoverAnimated:YES];
    }        
}
```

#The dSym
**This part I am not sure about, but I did the following steps**
We need to produce an archive so we can extract the dSym file.  This is done by doing the following actions.
Select iOS
![Select iOS](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/9dcc8977-518a-4daa-a703-aca81bed1e3b/pick%20iOS_large.png)
From the menu select Product-&gt;Archive

Now the organizer will open up and you can right click on your archive and pick "Show in finder"

Inside of the finder window right click on the archive and select"Show Package Contents"

Open up dSym folder, inside of this folder is your dSym file you want to upload to Raygun.

Go into raygun and upload the file "RayGunExample.app.dSYM" in the dSym center under Application Settings.

#Run Your App
Build your application and deploy to the simulator or your physical device.  Tap on the "+" to create a record and tap to go into the detail view.  Since we have the exception located the app will crash immediately.  I did this a few times so we have a few items inside of Raygun.

#Back To Raygun
Now if you log into raygun you should see your exception in the application dashboard.
![Error Details](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c20c1fa2-3685-4a76-997a-9a6c992abb28/raygun%20view_large.png)
We now have exception logging for our iOS application and now we can hopefully figure out the cause of our mysterious error.

#Conclusion
This was incredibly easy to setup even for an Objective-C novice like myself.  I **think** I have everything setup, but once we integrate this into our real application we can hopefully track down the problem(s) some users are reporting in our reviews.

[Code on github](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/capture-errors-in-ios-with-raygun)</body>
  <title>Load Testing In The Cloud</title>
  <subtitle>Visual Studio Online and TFS makes this process easy.</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-02-21 13:08:37 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Recently I attended an event discussing how to leverage Azure for development and test scenarios.  The event was presented at a high level and covered topics like setting up virtual machines, creating cloud services, web roles, worker roles, and a bit on visual studio online.  The one topic presented about visual studio online was load testing in the cloud.  I dabbled with load testing a few months ago setting up a local agent and local test controllers which was time consuming so making this process easy peaking my interest quickly.

#Setup
- Since we are talking about the cloud, we might as well use the website I setup inside of azure [previously](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/i-just-deployed-to-azure-via-git).  I did however make a few changes to include a top navigation and a few additional pages so our webtest performs a few actions.
![Website Home](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/1080518f-e2ea-4295-9614-8b2762f022e2/ijustdeployed_site_large.png)
- You have access to Visual Studio Online with TFS and connected in Team Explorer
- You can create a Load Test inside of Visual Studio Ultimate

#Creating the WebTest
####Creating the Project
The first thing that we need to do is create the web test. This is accomplished by creating a new "Web Performance Load Test" Project inside of Visual Studio.
![Creating the WebTest](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/d3c02900-c990-4fd5-aa20-c537b7bdacfc/02-add%20webtest_large.png)

####Solution View
Once the project is created you will see one file that ends in ```.webtest```.  This is the file were will create our web test.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/a0fdba5e-7d88-45cf-bcb8-d31ad4bcb60c/03-solutionview_large.png)

####Add Recording
Next thing we need to do is create a recording of the actions we want to perform on our web site.  This is done by opening up the ```.webtest``` file and clicking on the "Add Recording" button.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/65d62df8-72db-40ba-899e-5568eefae5c4/04-addrecording_large.png)

####Recording View
Once you clicked on the button Internet Explorer will launch with an add-on enabled that tracks your actions.  (If this is not shown make sure the add-on is enabled inside of Internet Explorer)
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/92ca0dde-1e4b-45f9-8c47-c1d76ab61a93/05-recordingview_large.png)

####Recording Output
After you are done recording your actions click stop recording in the add-on and you will return to the ```.webtest``` file.  Looking over the file you will see all the actions that you performed on the website.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/79454c15-df4c-4054-8e3d-5ba9adc26ee2/06-recordingoutput_large.png)

####Running Local
Before we start running our load test it is a good idea to verify that your webtest functions correctly and run the test locally.  
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/d177a95e-400d-499c-954a-f92094561d54/07-runninglocal_large.png)

#Create Load Test
####Add LoadTest
Now that we see the webtest is validated we need to add a "Load Test".  This is done by adding a new file to your project.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c676afee-94c0-4248-bc8b-05736866e3f6/08-add%20load%20test_large.png)

####Add Load Test Dialog
After the load test is added to your project you will be presented with a dialog to configure your test.  We are only concerned about a few items in this test.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/350afeef-db2a-4c17-912c-b8bde6d8d42e/09-load%20test%20dialog_large.png)

####Change Step Load
One of the options we want to alter is the load we are going to put on our site.  I decided to do a Step Load which starts at 10 users and steps up every 10sec by 10 users until a maximum of 200 concurrent users.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/713499dd-2bff-4592-84e8-e813b85e0a8d/10-change%20step%20load_large.png)

####Add Web Test
The next part and the most important part is adding in your webtest to your load test.  You can add in multiple web tests but since we only created one we only have access to this one webtest.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/1ab65d9f-a224-4798-ace4-a978d4e1a9ab/11-add%20web%20test_large.png)

####Duration
I also decided to change the duration to 5minutes so we can capture data inside of the portal while the load test is running.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c11da3f3-af14-418b-aa1c-844eb77e7b09/12-duration_large.png)

####Load Test
After you have all the settings changed you can see the configuration tree in the load test file inside of visual studio.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/fc789508-1034-4eb1-afc0-de1ef721f56b/13-load%20test_large.png)

#Configure for the Cloud
####Add Test Settings
Next we need to create a separate "Test Settings" file so we can configure our load test to run on Visual Studio Online.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/dbb53083-1de9-49b6-abbe-7634c4fa3f01/14-add%20test%20settings_large.png)

####Change Test Settings
The most important setting we need to change is to select the radio button to "Run tests using Visual Studio Team Foundation Service"  After that selection is made you can click apply and close down the dialog.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/7dcc5030-a7e4-45d0-8910-6e460e951ad9/15-run%20tests%20using%20visual%20studio%20team%20foundation%20service_large.png)

####Select Load Test Settings
Now that we have our Tests Settings we need to tell the Load Test to use this file.  This is done by clicking on "Load Test" and selecting the new test settings file.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/9c8e9c23-a11c-4539-b78a-815b6866828a/16-select%20load%20test%20settings%20file_large.png)

#Running Your Test
####Run Load Test
We are now ready to get started by clicking on Run under "Load Test"
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/0a15c46c-a392-4979-97c1-d57003131f6c/17-run%20load%20test_large.png)

####Load Test is Running
At first your load test will be queued for execution and after a few moments your test will begin running.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/abf67df5-961c-48b4-8b07-91ececd43055/18-it%20is%20running_large.png)

####View in Dashboard
If you go into the portal inside of Azure and select your website you can see the results of your currently running load test.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/3bb6f435-4c3e-454f-9b01-e9643625c397/19-view%20in%20dashboard_large.png)

####LoadTest Results
After the test is complete a report is generated that you can use to view various stats and any errors that were encountered during the test.
![Silvrback blog image](https://silvrback.s3.amazonaws.com/uploads/c19827be-c94b-4b4d-910b-79ab5444b514/20-load%20results_large.png)

#Conclusion
Once again Azure and Visual Studio Online makes this process painless.  If you have access to these tools in our organization there the reasons to contract with an outside load test vendor decrease greatly.

[Further Reading on visualstudio.com](http://www.visualstudio.com/en-us/get-started/load-test-your-app-vs.aspx)





 </body>
  <title>I Just Deployed to Azure via Git!</title>
  <subtitle>This is automagical</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-02-19 20:34:41 -0500</published_at>
  <body>I know I am a little late to the party but recently started to learn more about azure.  One of the first things I wanted to learn about is how to deploy my site via git.  I saw this in a few demos in the past but decided to do it myself to see how easy or hard this process is to get setup and running with a very basic example.

*The next steps are the raw process I went through to get my sample site setup and configured.*

##Azure
* Log into management portal
* Click websites
* Click Add New
* Click Web Site
* Click Quick Create
* Enter in your custom url
* Select your region from the drop down list
* Select your subscription from the drop down list
* Click  "CREATE WEBSTE ✔"

##GitHub
* Create your git repository
* Create a simple index.html file containing the following

```
&lt;html&gt;
	&lt;head&gt;
		&lt;title&gt;Hello from Azure!&lt;/title&gt;
	&lt;/head&gt;
	&lt;body&gt;
		&lt;h1&gt;Hello from Azure!&lt;/h1&gt;
	&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
```

* Commit your change locally and sync to github


##Back to Azure
* Log into the management portal
* Click Websites
* Click the website you want to setup for git deploy
* Go to Quick Glance on the dashboard view (Lower left)
* Select  "→ Setup deployment from source control" 
* Click github
* Authorize your github account
* Select the reposiotry you wish to setup for deployment
* After a few seconds your site will now be live


##Watching the magic
* Make a change to your local repository

```
&lt;html&gt;
	&lt;head&gt;
		&lt;title&gt;Hello from Azure!&lt;/title&gt;
	&lt;/head&gt;
	&lt;body&gt;
		&lt;h1&gt;Hello from Azure!&lt;/h1&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;
			This was published via azure!
		&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
```

* Sync changes to github
* Go back to the website dashboard and click on the deployment tab
* See the magic, the change was picked up and deployed.

##I Made a Mistake!
* Simple go back into the deployment tab on your website and click on the correct deployed version
* Click  "↶REDEPLOY" (bottom black bar) and your site will be reverted back to the previous state.
* Your site is back to the previous state

#This stuff is magic</body>
  <title>Manually Bootstraping AngularJs After Asynchronous Call</title>
  <subtitle>Delay initialization so you can gather config</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-02-13 08:52:18 -0500</published_at>
  <body>This morning while the snow is coming down I decided to browser over to stack overflow and found the question [How can I execute some code asynchronously before methods in my service are called?](http://stackoverflow.com/questions/21753526/how-can-i-execute-some-code-asynchronously-before-methods-in-my-service-are-call/21755018#21755018)

From the context of the question it appears the asker wants to initialize some config before the application is bootstrapped.  This can be done easily be [manually bootstrapping your application](http://docs.angularjs.org/guide/bootstrap).

The basic example in the docs
```&lt;script&gt;
       angular.element(document).ready(function() {
         angular.module('myApp', []);
         angular.bootstrap(document, ['myApp']);
       });
&lt;/script&gt;```

This snippet delays the bootstrap and allows you to bootstrap your app at a later point in time.  (ng-app has to be omitted from the document)

####Answering the question
Since the asker mentions an ajax request to determine which url to use we can easily perform the request (using jquery for simplicity), set the correct url in the ```fail()/done()``` and  bootstrap the application in ```always()```.

Putting it all together we end up with something like the following:

```
var urlToCheck = '/echo/json/';

var myApp = angular.module('myApp', []);

myApp.controller("MyCtrl", ["$scope", "config", function ($scope, config) {
    $scope.url = config.url;
}]);

$.ajax({
    url: urlToCheck
}).fail(function () {
    myApp.constant('config', {
        url: '/fail-url'
    });
}).done(function () {
    myApp.constant('config', {
        url: '/done-url'
    });
}).always(function () {
    angular.bootstrap(document, ['myApp']);
});
```

Simple but effective.

[Example on jsfiddle](http://jsfiddle.net/markcoleman/EWYMZ/)</body>
  <title>Adventures in ScrumBut</title>
  <subtitle>Our first large project using scrum</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-02-12 21:21:49 -0500</published_at>
  <body>With our last project we got on the scum bandwagon as a way to manage our backlog to keep some method to the madness.  Everyone in the team read numerous books, attended various training, and knew how scrum operates. We tried, however fell into the "[scum but](https://www.scrum.org/ScrumBut)" category in the end.  We recently had a project retrospective and came up with a nice laundry list of things we can do to improve with our next release cycle. 

*list derived from group discussion*

####Keep daily stand ups brief
We always had status meetings in the morning which was good to keep everyone on the same page however we tended to diverge in side discussions talking about other areas of the project.  This sometimes meant our stand up meetings ended up lasting over 1/2 hour.  This quickly relates to our next point.
####Team members can leave at the end of the stand up
Many times we would have our standup and then immediately start discussing about other aspects of the project which didn't require everyone to remain in the room.  The other team members felt obligated to stay and listen even if they were not required.
####List any items that need extra discussion
If extra discussion is required make this a talking point for after the standup.  This list allows other team members to see if they need to stay for the extra discussion and if not return to their work area.
####External resources should be brought into conversation
Occasionally during our sprint we had tasks handled by external resources such as sever configuration.  We treated these as tasks assigned to the person that was responsible to get the task done (by talking to the other group).  This resulted in getting second hand knowledge as our team member was a middle man.  We now realize these resources should be brought into the sprint and be part of the standup.  This makes the resource feel part of the project and is contributing to the success of the sprint.
####Do Retrospectives
We did not have many retrospectives during our project which we now know was not ideal.  If we would have had these retrospectives we could have addressed some of these findings earlier.  Because we did not hold these meetings team members felt frustrated with the process.
####Sprint review with owners and stakeholders
This is another area we fell short.  We had some very informal and infrequent review with our owners and stakeholders.  This resulted in some people not feeling part of the project and questioned some of the decisions made by other stakeholders.  We need to increase these reviews and increase transparency so there are no surprises.
####Task bugs
After we went live with release one bugs started to come in and our sprint process floundered.  We created PBIs for bugs which had no tasks.  Things got lost and team members didn't know if the bug was in development, in testing, or even deployed.  We needed some tasks to keep track the status of a bug.
####Bugs must have a severity
Your bug PBI's need to have a severity.  Our post release backlog was filled with bug PBI's of various size and severity but we never gave them a severity or a priority.  This resulted in team members working on the bugs in a random order.  With the priority we could work on the important ones first and keep the lower priority ones for later in the sprint.
####Bugs should include more details
Along with the chaos around a new deployment bugs were added in with details that only made sense at the time.  We were in the habit of entering a bug so it would be recorded and not lost but had no detail if it was for one user all users or how to reproduce the issue.   
####Include Effort for PBI
We had sporadic usage of effort for our PBI's in our backlog.  This resulted in quite a few epics in our sprint.  It was very demoralizing for the team members working on an epic where they could never cross off their PBI off of the list.  We need to add effort to our PBI's so we can identify any potential epics early on and divide up PBI's so they are completed in a sprint.
##Keep communication open with the business
This is probably the most important thing we learned.  We communicated a lot with team members and individuals involved in our scrum project however we need to increase this communication to all areas of the business.  There were a few occurrences where the business didn't understand decisions because they were inadvertently kept out of the loop.

##The future
We recently started up our next sprint and hope to take our lessons learned and improve our process in the coming months.
  </body>
  <title>My Experience with Automated UI Testing</title>
  <subtitle>We failed</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-02-03 21:05:44 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Last time readers I offered some of the lessons I learned while writing [unit tests](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/what-i-learned-about-unit-testing) over a 13 month long project.  We were fairly successful in writing our tests and validating our C# business logic.  Another one of our other goals for the project was to create Automated UI tests using [Coded UI Tests](http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dd286726.aspx) or a similar technology.  This goal was a lofty one for us and I can say unfortunately we **struggled** at getting this idea implemented.

#Why did we fail?

###Changing UI
This was one of the largest projects tackled by our team which resulted in an ever changing UI.  At the start we lacked focus and confidence in what we were developing visually.  We went through many iterations and ultimately brought in a design group to give us direction.  Because of this ever changing UI terrain we were scared that time invested into these tests would result in wasted effort.

###We lacked experience
Another area we had trouble with is writing test cases for our application.  We read many articles on what are test cases and how to write them but we never applied this knowledge.  

###We were scared
I will say we were a bit scared of the unknown when it came to UI testing.  Would our time invested be helpful to the project?  Are we doing it the right way?  How do we use this tool?  Are our test cases valid? 

###We lacked time
I know this sounds like a copout, however with all of the moving pieces in the project and available resources we just did not have the time to invest into creating automated UI testing.

#How can we do better?
###We need to make time
With learning any new framework or concept we need to make time to learn this idea as a group.  

###We need to just do it
We need to get past the scary factor and just do it.  Go outside your comfort zone and learn something new that might be a departure of your current skill set.

###It needs to be part of the sprint
If we add this idea into the sprint it forces us to take the time and create automated UI tests just like we create unit tests.

###Setup your tools
If your UI tests are hard to run they will not be ran and will fall into disrepair. 

#Conclusion
We started some baby steps at integrating these type of tests into our project.  We started a dialogue and began researching how to create tests and how to automate them.  We hope to integrate this practice into new sprints.</body>
  <title>What I learned about unit testing</title>
  <subtitle>Lessons learned in unit testing during a year long project</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-01-22 22:35:00 -0500</published_at>
  <body>If you read my previous post [What have I been doing?](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/what-have-i-been-doing) you know I have been busy working on a team building an Online Banking application.  I have done unit testing in the past but this was the first time where it was done on a large (for me) project.  When we started we had a few goals in regards to unit testing.

 * Write unit tests in C# to cover business logic for our API
 * Write unit tests for our AngularJs application

After our first release I can say we had success on the C# side but unfortunately had minimal success for our AngularJs tests as we had minimal prior experience with JavaScript testing.

##Why it is important
**Unit testing is extremely important in any application of significant scale.**  I can not stress this enough as unit testing helps identify potential problems early on and forces you to think how your application is structured.  If your class/method is difficult to test chances are you need to reevaluate your implementation.  

####Bugs
With any application bugs are going to exist from either coding defects or undefined results from your business rule given a unexpected data.  I can not tell you how mentally satisfying it is for me to write up a failing test after a bug report.  

 * We receive a bug report
 * We recreate the bug with a failed unit test
 * We fix the bug which makes my failed unit test pass
 * We now know with some reasonable assurance that the bug is now fixed

####Changing business rules
We all know that even with the best requirements and specifications changes occur to business rules.  Month one we are told do not allow that person to register and then on month ten we are told that person can now register.  

 * Method has adequate code coverage via unit testing
 * Business rule changes
 * We write failing unit test for the new business rule
 * We make our alterations until the new rule passes
 * We run our existing tests to verify that our old rules still pass

This allows us to have some assurance that our new change to the business rule did not inadvertently break existing rules.

##Know your tools
With any type of unit testing you are going to use some sort of test runner to run your unit tests.  Knowing your toolset greatly increases your chances of succeeding in creating valid unit tests for your project.  If your tests are difficult to run or the results are not known they most likely will be forgotten and broken.

####C&amp;#35;
The tool we used or our C# code was [NCrunch](http://www.ncrunch.net).  NCrunch changed the way we viewed unit testing.  We had it configured to constantly monitor all of our MSTests and run them in parallel giving us immediate results for any possible failures.  NCover also places small dots on each line of code that is covered by our unit tests.  This visual feedback and instantaneous results for passing and failing unit tests allowed us to reach our goal of  incorporating C# unit testing from the start of the project.

####JavaScript
We used [Chutzpah](http://chutzpah.codeplex.com) as a test runner for our JavaScript tests.  We picked this tool since we could also easily integrate our test results inside of TFS.  We also utilized [Karma](http://karma-runner.github.io/) to run our tests to gain the immediate feedback on our tests results.  Even with these tools we only had moderate success with our JavaScript tests.  I think our issues originated from the start because of our fear as it was a new concept for all of the developers on the team.  We hope to improve our code in the future by integration of a full test suite of JavaScript tests.

##Learn when to use Mocks, Stubs, and Fakes
You need to [learn what is the difference is between Mocks, Stubs, and Fakes](http://stackoverflow.com/a/346440/181776) when writing your tests.  Creating a mock to test a method where a fake is appropriate can help reduce the complexity of your code and make your tests easier to maintain.  Another thing we learned is that just because you can use a framework like [Moq](https://github.com/Moq/moq4) does not mean you always should.  We had experiences where we used moq which resulted in a few lines of setup and configuration in each test that could have been simplified with a Stub.

##Your tests are important and need maintained
Early on when creating our tests we suffered for a lot of code duplication where we would copy and paste similar arrangements and build ups for our tests.  For some reason we would tend to let this practice slide.  We would think, *"These are just tests!  They are not production code!  They don't have to be maintained"*  We were wrong!  Do not get lazy when it comes to writing your tests as they **need to be maintained** almost as much as your production code base.  Write helper methods, base classes, custom asserts, and reducing code duplication allows your test to be easier to understand and when changes come in (and they will) you do not spend 10 minutes making a change and 2 hours cleaning up your tests.

##Do it from the start
This one is important, you need to do this this from the start.  Your team should spend time upfront getting your tools setup and your build environment configured so you can make this process part of your development cycle.  This can easily be seen in our project as we could easily create C# unit tests and see their results without much trouble.  Our JavaScript tests on the other hand were foreign to us and resulted in mixed usage in our team and numerous partial successful builds for failed JavaScript tests as they were routinely forgotten.  

##Conclusion
I can say I learned quite a lot about unit testing in our project. I hope you will be were able to learn from some of my experiences so unit testing succeeds in your project.</body>
  <title>What have I been doing?</title>
  <subtitle>I have been busy the past 13 months.</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-01-14 21:36:53 -0500</published_at>
  <body>Over the past year I have been part of a team in charge of building a brand new online banking system for my [current employer](http://www.members1st.org).  Last spring I was fairly active writing articles on [tech.pro](http://www.tech.pro/markcoleman) but over the past few months I have been fairly quiet as items were coming to an end and things became hectic trying to cross our t's and dot our i's without much time to decompress after work (especially to think about technology).  

As of last week I am happy to say our project has [gone live](https://myonline.members1st.org/#/login/home) and now our time has switched to diagnosing bugs and putting out fires.  This means it is now time to get back into blogging and sharing my experiences.

###What did the team build?###
We built and online banking system to replace our aging ```.net1.11``` system from a 3rd party vendor.  We work in a Microsoft shop so our logical choice would be to utilize MVC and build a system with controllers, action filters, and areas.  We looked at what we had to build, our vision of our needs for the future and decided that we wanted to do something different.  We have been hearing a lot about single page applications and decided to look at various frameworks finally deciding on [angularjs](http://www.angularjs.org).  Since we now had a front end framework we also needed a way to get data back and forth from our servers.  Again we looked at WebAPI (which is awesome), however once we looked at [nancyfx](http://nancyfx.org) we fell in love.  Things just seemed to work and had almost zero friction in getting started.  We used numerous other libraries but at its core it all revolves around those two big players.

###How we wanted to build it###
Given that we were starting from scratch we wanted to do this the "right way".  What did it mean to do things the right way for us?

* Use scum
* [Write Unit Tests](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/what-i-learned-about-unit-testing)
* Write Integration/System Tests
* [Write automated UI Tests](https://markcoleman.silvrback.com/experiences-with-automated-ui-testing)
* Profile the application (ignorance is not bliss)
* Do not reinvent the wheel
* Deployment should be easy and continuous to our test server
* Have open communication 
* Have scheduled code reviews
* Perform Spikes
* Create mock ups and wire frames
* Do not develop in a vacuum 
* Think about UI/UX

As you can see these were some lofty goals as this was the first time our team undertook such an ambitious project.

###So how did we do?###
We an amazing job given the bumps and hurdles that got in our way.  We managed to upgrade 60% of the existing user base and serve 7+ million requests to our api in the first week.  I plan to go into detail on a few of these bullet points in upcoming posts.

###What did I personally learn?###
I have to say I learned a great deal over the past year I hope to share with everyone in a series of upcoming posts.  I hope these will be helpful for the reader as finding articles on what someone else did in this situation are in my experience hard to find.

*until another day*
Well I must sign off now as I have another busy day coming up fixing small issues and refining the process so our users who fear change embrace the new system.</body>
  <title>Hello</title>
  <subtitle>Trying out silvrback</subtitle>
  <published_at>2014-01-14 20:14:00 -0500</published_at>
  <body>I am about two weeks late to give a  New Year's resolution, but this year I hope to write more about my experiences when learning and developing software during my career as a developer.

Let's hope this goal starts out well and the trend continues onto the new year.

Now it is time to write my first article.

Wish me luck.</body>
</blog>
